<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>JOSTA</title>
<link>https://www.jostapubs.com/published.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.jostapubs.com/published.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 18:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>RAISINS: Integrating R and AI for Agricultural Data Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Mohammed Hisham M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jithin Chandran</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pratheesh P Gopinath*</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/josta111raisins2025.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15622128"><img src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.15622128.svg" class="img-fluid"></a> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/open--access-yes-brightgreen.svg" class="img-fluid" alt="Open Access"> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/status-peer--reviewed-brightgreen.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Status"></p>
<div style="display: flex; flex-wrap: wrap; gap: 1rem; align-items: center; margin-top: 1rem;">
<!-- Download PDF Button -->
<p><a href="pdfs/josta_raisins.pdf" download="" class="download-btn"> <i class="bi bi-file-earmark-pdf-fill"></i> Download PDF </a></p>
<!-- Copy Citation Button -->
<button id="copy-btn" onclick="copyCitation()" class="copy-btn">
📋 Copy Citation <span id="tooltip">Citation copied!</span>
</button>
</div>
<!-- Hidden Citation Text -->
<p><span id="citation-text" style="display: none;"> Mohammed, H. M., Chandran, J., &amp; Gopinath, P. P. (2025). RAISINS: Integrating R and AI for Agricultural Data Analysis. In <em>Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture</em> (Vol. 1, Number 1). PAPAYA Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15622128 </span></p>
<!-- JavaScript -->
<script>
  function copyCitation() {
    const citation = document.getElementById("citation-text").innerText;
    navigator.clipboard.writeText(citation);
    
    const tooltip = document.getElementById("tooltip");
    tooltip.style.visibility = "visible";
    tooltip.style.opacity = "1";
    
    setTimeout(() => {
      tooltip.style.visibility = "hidden";
      tooltip.style.opacity = "0";
    }, 2000);
  }
</script>
<!-- CSS Styling -->
<style>
.download-btn {
  display: inline-flex;
  align-items: center;
  border: 2px solid #28a745;
  background-color: transparent;
  color: #28a745;
  padding: 8px 14px;
  border-radius: 6px;
  font-weight: 500;
  text-decoration: none;
  transition: all 0.3s ease;
}
.download-btn:hover {
  background-color: #28a745;
  color: white;
}
.download-btn i {
  margin-right: 6px;
}

.copy-btn {
  font-size: 0.9rem;
  padding: 8px 14px;
  border: 1px solid black;
  background-color: white;
  color: black;
  border-radius: 6px;
  cursor: pointer;
  position: relative;
}
.copy-btn #tooltip {
  visibility: hidden;
  background-color: black;
  color: #fff;
  text-align: center;
  border-radius: 4px;
  padding: 2px 6px;
  position: absolute;
  z-index: 1;
  bottom: 120%;
  left: 50%;
  transform: translateX(-50%);
  font-size: 0.75rem;
  opacity: 0;
  transition: opacity 0.3s;
}
</style>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>Statistical analysis serves as the backbone of scientific research, especially in disciplines like agriculture, where field experiments, survey data, and observational studies generate complex datasets. Despite the increasing emphasis on data-driven decision-making in agricultural research, many students, early-career researchers, and practitioners find themselves at a disadvantage when it comes to performing rigorous statistical analyses. The process is often hindered by a combination of factors: the steep learning curve associated with programming languages such as R and Python, the fragmented nature of statistical learning resources, and the lack of user-friendly tools tailored to agricultural research contexts.</p>
<p>While R and Python are powerful, flexible, and widely adopted in academic and professional settings, their command-line interfaces and syntax-heavy operations can be challenging for those without formal training in statistics or computer programming. Beginners frequently struggle with package selection, data cleaning, model specification, and interpretation of results. Furthermore, existing statistical software either lacks the flexibility and transparency of open-source tools or comes with licensing restrictions and high costs that limit accessibility in resource-constrained settings, particularly in developing countries.</p>
<p>In addition, agricultural research involves domain-specific needs such as handling experimental designs (e.g., CRD, RBD, split-plot), analyzing agronomic trials, processing survey data with appropriate sampling designs, and interpreting interactions between multiple environmental and genetic factors. Traditional statistical packages are not always well-adapted to these specific requirements, leaving researchers to either customize solutions on their own or consult specialists — both of which can delay or compromise the analytical workflow.</p>
<p>To bridge this gap, we developed RAISINS (R and AI Solutions for INferential Statistics) — a web-based platform designed to simplify and democratize statistical analysis for agricultural research. RAISINS integrates the power of R, Python, and AI-driven assistance within an intuitive interface that eliminates the need for code-based interaction. By abstracting complex syntax and offering guided, step-by-step workflows for data upload, analysis, visualization, and interpretation, the platform empowers users to focus on scientific inquiry rather than technical execution.</p>
<p>Built on open-source technologies and scalable cloud infrastructure, RAISINS provides modules for commonly used statistical methods — including descriptive analysis, hypothesis testing, regression models, design of experiments, multi environmental trials, and more — while incorporating AI tools that assist in data summarization, analytical suggestions, and natural language explanations of results. This makes it an ideal solution for students, researchers, extension personnel, and educators engaged in agricultural and allied sciences. RAISINS can be accessed online through its official web portal at https://www.raisins.live/.</p>
<p>In this paper, we present the design, features, and use-cases of RAISINS, and demonstrate how it addresses the unique challenges faced in agricultural data analysis by offering an accessible, robust, and intelligent statistical platform.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-models" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-models"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Materials and methods</h2>
<section id="platform-architecture-and-module-validation" class="level3" data-number="2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="platform-architecture-and-module-validation"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Platform architecture and module validation</h3>
<p>RAISINS is a modular cloud-hosted, web-based platform that integrates statistical computing, artificial intelligence, and modern pedagogical design to serve agricultural researchers and students. Built using R, Python, and OpenAI APIs, RAISINS is deployed via Posit Connect Cloud (https://connect.posit.cloud/), enabling browser-based access without requiring any local software installation. The RAISINS platform is modular and each statistical tool within is aligned with the theoretical underpinnings found in globally recognized academic literature.</p>
<p>All modules in RAISINS have been peer-reviewed by domain experts, including statisticians specializing in design of experiments, genetics, and social science research. This ensures both methodological rigor and instructional clarity.</p>
<p>Table&nbsp;1 presents the major analytical domains addressed by RAISINS, the foundational academic references supporting each module domain, organized by area of application.</p>
<div id="tbl-foundation" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-foundation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Foundational literature supporting each RAISINS module domain, organized by area of application.
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-foundation-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 34%">
<col style="width: 65%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Module Domain</th>
<th>Theoretical Foundation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Design &amp; Analysis of Experiments</td>
<td>Montgomery (2017) <span class="citation" data-cites="montgomery2017design">(Montgomery 2017)</span>; Gomez &amp; Gomez (1984) <span class="citation" data-cites="gomez1984statistical">(Gomez and Gomez 1984)</span>; Das &amp; Giri (2018) <span class="citation" data-cites="das2018design">(Das and Giri 2018)</span>; Searle (1997) <span class="citation" data-cites="searle1997linear">(Searle 1997)</span>; Dey (1986) <span class="citation" data-cites="dey1986theory">(Dey 1986)</span>; Cox &amp; Reid (2000) <span class="citation" data-cites="cox2000theory">(Cox and Reid 2000)</span>; Toutenburg &amp; Shalabh (2009) <span class="citation" data-cites="toutenburg2009statistical">(Toutenburg and Shalabh 2009)</span>; Cochran &amp; Cox (1957) <span class="citation" data-cites="cochran1957experimental">(Cochran and Cox 1957)</span>; ; Federer (1985) <span class="citation" data-cites="federer1985experimental">(Federer 1985)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Statistical Genetics</td>
<td>Falconer &amp; Mackay (1996) <span class="citation" data-cites="falconer1996introduction">(Falconer and Mackay 1996)</span>; Lynch &amp; Walsh (1998) <span class="citation" data-cites="lynch1998genetics">(Lynch and Walsh 1998)</span>; Dabholkar (1999) <span class="citation" data-cites="dabholkar1999elements">(Dabholkar 1999)</span>; Gillespie (2004) <span class="citation" data-cites="gillespie2004population">(Gillespie 2004)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Social Science Research</td>
<td>Babbie (2020) <span class="citation" data-cites="babbie2020practice">(Babbie 2020)</span>; Bryman (2016) <span class="citation" data-cites="bryman2016social">(Bryman 2016)</span>; Bhattacherjee (2012) <span class="citation" data-cites="bhattacherjee2012social">(Bhattacherjee 2012)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Statistical Inference and Modeling</td>
<td>Casella &amp; Berger (2002) <span class="citation" data-cites="casella2002statistical">(Casella and Berger 2002)</span>; Hogg, McKean &amp; Craig (2018) <span class="citation" data-cites="hogg2018introduction">(Hogg, McKean, and Craig 2018)</span>; Agresti (2013) <span class="citation" data-cites="agresti2013categorical">(Agresti 2013)</span>; Rao (2009) <span class="citation" data-cites="rao2009linear">(Rao 2009)</span>; Rohatgi (1984) <span class="citation" data-cites="rohatgi1984statistical">(Rohatgi 1984)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Data Visualization &amp; Reporting</td>
<td>Tufte (2001) <span class="citation" data-cites="tufte2001visual">(Tufte 2001)</span>; Cleveland (1993) <span class="citation" data-cites="cleveland1993visualizing">(Cleveland 1993)</span>; Few (2009) <span class="citation" data-cites="few2009now">(Few 2009)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The algorithms and workflows integrated into RAISINS are grounded in established statistical theory, drawing extensively from authoritative texts and peer-reviewed literature. In cases where existing computational implementations were unavailable or insufficient, original algorithms were developed in adherence to rigorous theoretical principles. The platform’s design and interface have been iteratively refined based on user-centered feedback from researchers and educators, ensuring methodological soundness and usability consistent with global standards in scientific research and statistical education.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-packages" class="level3" data-number="2.2">
<h3 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-packages"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Packages and Libraries</h3>
<p>RAISINS integrates a comprehensive ecosystem of open-source R and Python packages to deliver its core functionalities, encompassing statistical modeling, data visualization, artificial intelligence, and interactive web-based deployment. These packages support the platform’s goal of offering high-level statistical capabilities through an accessible and intuitive interface, particularly beneficial for students and researchers in agricultural sciences.</p>
<p>The R-based architecture of RAISINS is built around the <code>shiny</code> framework <span class="citation" data-cites="shiny">(Chang et al. 2024)</span>, which enables the development of dynamic, browser-accessible applications. Data manipulation tasks are performed using <code>dplyr</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="dplyr">(Wickham et al. 2024)</span>, <code>tidyr</code>, and <code>data.table</code>, while data visualization is implemented through <code>ggplot2</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="ggplot2">(Wickham 2023)</span>, along with complementary packages such as <code>ggthemes</code>, <code>plotly</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="plotly">(Sievert 2023)</span>, and <code>ggpattern</code>. For statistical analysis relevant to agricultural experiments and general inference, the platform employs packages including <code>agricolae</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="agricolae">(Mendiburu 2020)</span>, <code>broom</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="broom">(Robinson and Hayes 2024)</span>, <code>effectsize</code>, <code>lsr</code>, <code>car</code>, <code>phia</code>, and <code>FactoMineR</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="FactoMineR">(Husson et al. 2020)</span>. These libraries provide robust support for model fitting, hypothesis testing, effect size estimation, and multivariate analysis.</p>
<p>To enhance user interaction and responsiveness, RAISINS integrates several user interface and usability packages, such as <code>shinyWidgets</code>, <code>shinyalert</code>, <code>shinybusy</code>, <code>shinycustomloader</code>, <code>shinyBS</code>, <code>shinythemes</code>, and <code>colourpicker</code>. The presentation and export of analytical results are managed through tools like <code>rmarkdown</code>, <code>kableExtra</code>, and <code>formattable</code>, ensuring professional and structured output for reports and publications.</p>
<p>The <code>reticulate</code><span class="citation" data-cites="reticulate">(Allaire et al. 2024)</span> package serves as a bridge between R and Python, allowing both languages to be used seamlessly within the same analytical workflow. In RAISINS, reticulate enables the platform to call Python functions, use Python libraries, and exchange data objects between R and Python environments. This integration allows the platform to combine R’s interactive capabilities with Python’s strengths in machine learning, statistical modeling, and AI-driven tasks, thereby enhancing both flexibility and functionality.</p>
<p>Python libraries are used to extend the platform’s analytical and AI-driven features. Packages such as <code>pandas</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="pandas">(The pandas development team 2024)</span> and <code>numpy</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="numpy">(Harris et al. 2020)</span> are employed for efficient data handling, while <code>matplotlib</code> and <code>seaborn</code> support graphical representations. For machine learning and statistical modeling, the platform uses <code>scikit-learn</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="scikit-learn">(Pedregosa et al. 2011)</span> and <code>statsmodels</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="statsmodels">(Seabold and Perktold 2010)</span>. The <code>openai</code> package enables the integration of language models, facilitating intelligent assistance and automated content generation within the platform.</p>
<p>All R and Python packages used in RAISINS are well-maintained, community-supported, and widely recognized within academic and applied data science contexts. Each library is carefully selected based on its performance, stability, and relevance to agricultural research workflows. Modules are thoroughly reviewed by subject-matter experts to ensure methodological accuracy and pedagogical effectiveness, thereby maintaining the platform’s commitment to reproducibility, transparency, and educational value.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="sec-illustrations" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-illustrations"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Illustrations</h2>
<p>The Figure&nbsp;1 illustrates the comprehensive architecture of the RAISINS platform, highlighting its integration of multiple programming languages and technologies. RAISINS combines the statistical computing power of R with the flexibility of Python and the advanced capabilities of AI through OpenAI models. The platform’s user interface is built using Shiny, providing an interactive and user-friendly experience, while the backend seamlessly coordinates R and Python processes. Hosting on Posit Connect Cloud ensures reliable accessibility and scalability for agricultural researchers. This integrated ecosystem enables efficient and robust inferential statistical analysis tailored specifically for agricultural research needs.</p>
<div id="fig-flowchart" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-flowchart-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/raisinsflow.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="300">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-flowchart-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Architecture of the RAISINS Platform: Integration of R, Python, and AI Components through a Shiny-based Web Interface Hosted on Posit Connect Cloud.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="sec-results" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-results"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Results</h2>
<p>The RAISINS platform was developed to address the growing need for accessible, reliable, and AI-enhanced statistical tools tailored to agricultural research. By integrating familiar programming environments with user-friendly interfaces, it aims to bridge the gap between complex statistical methods and researchers’ practical needs.</p>
<section id="modular-structure-and-user-interface-design" class="level3" data-number="4.1">
<h3 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modular-structure-and-user-interface-design"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Modular structure and user interface design</h3>
<p>All analytical modules within the RAISINS platform adhere to a standardized structural layout, ensuring a uniform user experience across various statistical tools. Each module features a primary <code>Analysis</code> tab, which serves as the central workspace. This tab contains nested sub-tabs including <code>Analysis.Results</code>, where users configure model parameters and run statistical procedures; <code>Plots and Graphs</code>, which displays dynamic visualizations; <code>AI Interpretation</code>, where OpenAI-assisted textual summaries explain the results in plain language; and, where applicable, a <code>Multivariate</code> tab offering additional multivariate diagnostics and tests. Supplementing the core analysis, additional top-level tabs include <code>Create Data</code>, which enables users to generate CSV-format datasets for custom input; <code>Datasets</code>, which provides curated example datasets for testing and exploration; and <code>User</code>, where authenticated users can access their profile information and session history. For illustration purposes, selected screenshots from the CRD (Completely Randomized Design) module are presented in Figure&nbsp;2 to demonstrate the consistent tab layout and modular design adopted throughout the platform. A comprehensive module-wise user guide is available at: <a href="https://statoberrypapaya.github.io/RAISINS_TUTORIAL/" class="uri">https://statoberrypapaya.github.io/RAISINS_TUTORIAL/</a>, providing detailed documentation of the functionalities implemented in each component of the RAISINS platform.</p>
<div id="fig-crdmodule" class="quarto-layout-panel">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-crdmodule-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-mainpage" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-mainpage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/crdmainpage.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-mainpage-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(a) CRD module main page
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-auth" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-auth-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/loginpage.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-auth-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(b) Authentication page
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-dash" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-dash-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/crdmainpage1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-dash-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(c) Module dashboard
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-analysis" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-analysis-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/tabular_page.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-analysis-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(d) Result tables in Analysis.Results
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-plots" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-plots-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/plotspage.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-plots-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(e) Plots and graphs
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-ai" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-ai-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/aicrd.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-ai-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(f) AI interpretation
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-mult" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-mult-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/multivariate.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-mult-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(g) Multivariate analysis window
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell-subref quarto-layout-cell" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div id="fig-datasets" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-subfloat-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-datasets-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/figures/dataraisins.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-crdmodule">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-subfloat-caption quarto-subfloat-fig" id="fig-datasets-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
(h) Datasets available for testing
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-crdmodule-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: User interface and modular design of the RAISINS platform: screenshots from the CRD Module illustrating the common tab structure across analytical tools.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="discussion" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion">Discussion</h2>
<p>The RAISINS platform represents a significant advancement in making advanced statistical and AI-driven analytical tools accessible to the agricultural research community. By seamlessly integrating R, Python, and AI capabilities within an intuitive web interface, RAISINS addresses common barriers faced by researchers, such as the complexity of statistical software and interpretation of results. The platform’s emphasis on user-friendliness and automation allows researchers, including those with limited statistical training, to perform rigorous data analysis with confidence. This democratization of statistical tools has the potential to improve the quality and reproducibility of agricultural research outputs. Moreover, the cloud-based deployment ensures scalability and continuous availability, enabling broader adoption across diverse educational and research institutions. The collaborative design and integration of multiple programming environments also open avenues for further enhancements, positioning RAISINS as a flexible and evolving resource in the field of agricultural data science.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The RAISINS platform aims in democratizing access to advanced statistical and AI-powered analytical tools tailored specifically for agricultural research. By integrating the strengths of R and Python programming environments with artificial intelligence capabilities, RAISINS offers researchers an intuitive and comprehensive platform for conducting inferential statistics without requiring extensive technical expertise. Its web-based interface, supported by cloud hosting, ensures that users can access powerful data analysis tools anytime and from anywhere, thereby enhancing collaboration and research productivity. The platform’s ability to simplify complex outputs and support diverse user groups—from students to seasoned faculty—has already contributed to improved data analysis quality and research rigor within agricultural universities. RAISINS not only supports robust statistical inference but also fosters greater confidence among users in interpreting and applying results to their scientific inquiries. This positions RAISINS as a foundational resource in agricultural data science with substantial potential for continued growth and impact.</p>
<section id="future-work" class="level3 unnumbered">
<h3 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="future-work">Future Work</h3>
<p>Future development of RAISINS will focus on expanding its analytical capabilities to cover a wider range of disciplines within agricultural research, including statistical genetics, survey data analysis, and agricultural economics. In addition, the AI components will be further enhanced by training on domain-specific datasets, enabling the platform to provide more accurate, context-aware insights and recommendations. These enhancements aim to solidify RAISINS as a continuously evolving and essential tool for meeting the diverse and growing needs of the agricultural research community.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="acknowledgments" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h2>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-none no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the support and encouragement provided by Kerala Agricultural University throughout the development of this work. We also extend our sincere thanks to the NABARD-KAU-WSU Agtech Launchpad for their invaluable incubation program and continued backing, which have been instrumental in advancing the RAISINS platform.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-agresti2013categorical" class="csl-entry">
Agresti, A. 2013. <em>Categorical Data Analysis</em>. 3rd ed. Hoboken, NJ, USA: Wiley.
</div>
<div id="ref-reticulate" class="csl-entry">
Allaire, JJ, Kevin Ushey, Yuan Tang, Dirk Eddelbuettel, and RStudio. 2024. <em>Reticulate: Interface to ’Python’</em>. <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/reticulate/">https://rstudio.github.io/reticulate/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-babbie2020practice" class="csl-entry">
Babbie, Earl R. 2020. <em>The Practice of Social Research</em>. 15th ed. Cengage Learning.
</div>
<div id="ref-bhattacherjee2012social" class="csl-entry">
Bhattacherjee, Anol. 2012. <em>Social Science Research: Principles, Methods, and Practices</em>. 2nd ed. Global Text Project.
</div>
<div id="ref-bryman2016social" class="csl-entry">
Bryman, Alan. 2016. <em>Social Research Methods</em>. 5th ed. Oxford University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-casella2002statistical" class="csl-entry">
Casella, George, and Roger L Berger. 2002. <em>Statistical Inference</em>. 2nd ed. Cengage Learning.
</div>
<div id="ref-shiny" class="csl-entry">
Chang, Winston, Joe Cheng, JJ Allaire, Yihui Xie, and Jonathan McPherson. 2024. <em>Shiny: Web Application Framework for r</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=shiny</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-cleveland1993visualizing" class="csl-entry">
Cleveland, William S. 1993. <em>Visualizing Data</em>. Hobart Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-cochran1957experimental" class="csl-entry">
Cochran, William G., and Gertrude M. Cox. 1957. <em>Experimental Designs</em>. 2nd ed. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons.
</div>
<div id="ref-cox2000theory" class="csl-entry">
Cox, D. R., and Nancy Reid. 2000. <em>The Theory of the Design of Experiments</em>. 1st ed. Monographs on Statistics and Applied Probability, 86. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC.
</div>
<div id="ref-dabholkar1999elements" class="csl-entry">
Dabholkar, A. R. 1999. <em>Elements of Bio Metrical Genetics</em>. Revised and Enlarged. Concept Publishing Company Pvt. Ltd.
</div>
<div id="ref-das2018design" class="csl-entry">
Das, M. N., and N. C. Giri. 2018. <em>Design and Analysis of Experiments</em>. 2nd ed. New Delhi, India: New Age International Publishers.
</div>
<div id="ref-dey1986theory" class="csl-entry">
Dey, A. 1986. <em>Theory of Block Designs</em>. New Delhi, India: Wiley Eastern Ltd.
</div>
<div id="ref-falconer1996introduction" class="csl-entry">
Falconer, Douglas S, and Trudy FC Mackay. 1996. <em>Introduction to Quantitative Genetics</em>. 4th ed. Longman.
</div>
<div id="ref-federer1985experimental" class="csl-entry">
Federer, W. T. 1985. <em>Experimental Designs</em>. ? New York: The Macmillan Company.
</div>
<div id="ref-few2009now" class="csl-entry">
Few, S. 2009. <em>Now You See It: Simple Visualization Techniques for Quantitative Analysis</em>. Berkeley, CA, USA: Analytics Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-gillespie2004population" class="csl-entry">
Gillespie, John H. 2004. <em>Population Genetics: A Concise Guide</em>. 2nd ed. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-gomez1984statistical" class="csl-entry">
Gomez, Kwanchai A, and Arturo A Gomez. 1984. <em>Statistical Procedures for Agricultural Research</em>. 2nd ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons.
</div>
<div id="ref-numpy" class="csl-entry">
Harris, Charles R., K. Jarrod Millman, Stéfan van der Walt, Ralf Gommers, Pauli Virtanen, David Cournapeau, Eric Wieser, et al. 2020. <em>NumPy: Fundamental Package for Scientific Computing with Python</em>. <em>Nature</em>. Vol. 585. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-hogg2018introduction" class="csl-entry">
Hogg, Robert V, Joseph McKean, and Allen T Craig. 2018. <em>Introduction to Mathematical Statistics</em>. 8th ed. Pearson.
</div>
<div id="ref-FactoMineR" class="csl-entry">
Husson, François, Julie Josse, Sébastien Lê, and Jeremy Mazet. 2020. <em>FactoMineR: Multivariate Exploratory Data Analysis and Data Mining</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FactoMineR">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FactoMineR</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lynch1998genetics" class="csl-entry">
Lynch, Michael, and Bruce Walsh. 1998. <em>Genetics and Analysis of Quantitative Traits</em>. Sinauer Associates.
</div>
<div id="ref-agricolae" class="csl-entry">
Mendiburu, Felipe de. 2020. <em>Agricolae: Statistical Procedures for Agricultural Research</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=agricolae">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=agricolae</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-montgomery2017design" class="csl-entry">
Montgomery, Douglas C. 2017. <em>Design and Analysis of Experiments</em>. 9th ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons.
</div>
<div id="ref-scikit-learn" class="csl-entry">
Pedregosa, Fabian, Gaël Varoquaux, Alexandre Gramfort, Vincent Michel, Bertrand Thirion, Olivier Grisel, Mathieu Blondel, et al. 2011. <em>Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in Python</em>. <em>Journal of Machine Learning Research</em>. Vol. 12. <a href="https://scikit-learn.org/">https://scikit-learn.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rao2009linear" class="csl-entry">
Rao, C. Radhakrishna. 2009. <em>Linear Statistical Inference and Its Applications</em>. 2nd ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons (Wiley-Interscience).
</div>
<div id="ref-broom" class="csl-entry">
Robinson, David, and Alex Hayes. 2024. <em>Broom: Convert Statistical Analysis Objects into Tidy Tibbles</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=broom">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=broom</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-rohatgi1984statistical" class="csl-entry">
Rohatgi, Vijay K. 1984. <em>Statistical Inference</em>. Wiley Series in Probability and Mathematical Statistics. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons.
</div>
<div id="ref-statsmodels" class="csl-entry">
Seabold, Skipper, and Josef Perktold. 2010. <em>Statsmodels: Statistical Modeling and Econometrics in Python</em>. <a href="https://www.statsmodels.org/">https://www.statsmodels.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-searle1997linear" class="csl-entry">
Searle, Shayle R. 1997. <em>Linear Models</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.
</div>
<div id="ref-plotly" class="csl-entry">
Sievert, Carson. 2023. <em>Plotly: Create Interactive Web Graphics via ’Plotly.js’</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=plotly">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=plotly</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-pandas" class="csl-entry">
The pandas development team. 2024. <em>Pandas: Powerful Python Data Analysis Toolkit</em>. <a href="https://pandas.pydata.org/">https://pandas.pydata.org/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-toutenburg2009statistical" class="csl-entry">
Toutenburg, Helge, and Shalabh. 2009. <em>Statistical Analysis of Designed Experiments</em>. 3rd ed. Springer Texts in Statistics. Springer‑Verlag New York.
</div>
<div id="ref-tufte2001visual" class="csl-entry">
Tufte, Edward R. 2001. <em>The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</em>. Graphics Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-ggplot2" class="csl-entry">
Wickham, Hadley. 2023. <em>Ggplot2: Create Elegant Data Visualisations Using the Grammar of Graphics</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dplyr" class="csl-entry">
Wickham, Hadley, Romain Francois, Lionel Henry, and Kirill Müller. 2024. <em>Dplyr: A Grammar of Data Manipulation</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dplyr">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dplyr</a>.
</div>
</div>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="sec-techdetails" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-techdetails">Technical details</h2>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-none no-icon">
<div class="callout-body d-flex">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container">
<p>Due to the ongoing costs associated with hosting and maintaining the RAISINS platform, the authors have adopted a subscription-based model to ensure its sustainability and continued development. The live application is accessible to users at https://www.raisins.live/.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled" title="Publication &amp; Reviewer Details">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Publication &amp; Reviewer Details
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><strong>Publication Information</strong><br>
- <em>Submitted:</em> 15 May 2025<br>
- <em>Accepted:</em> 06 June 2025<br>
- <em>Published (Online):</em> 09 June 2025</p>
<p><strong>Reviewer Information</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Saurav Guha, Ph.D.</strong><br>
Assistant Professor-cum-Junior Scientist<br>
Department of Statistics, Mathematics &amp; Computer Application<br>
Bihar Agricultural University, Sabour, India<br>
<strong>ORCID:</strong> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8960-5062">0000-0001-8960-5062</a></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Manju Mary Paul, Ph.D.</strong><br>
Assistant Professor<br>
Department of Agricultural Statistics<br>
Kerala Agricultural University, Kerala, India</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="section" class="level3 unnumbered">
<h3 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="section"></h3>



</section>
</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>Orignal-Article</category>
  <category>Data-Science</category>
  <category>Software</category>
  <guid>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1/josta111raisins2025.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
