<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>JOSTA</title>
<link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Date Palm Propagation Techniques: A Comprehensive Review</title>
  <dc:creator>Muhammad Ammar Amjad*</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Beenish Chaudhary</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haram Murtaza</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mohsin Raza</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maham Sajid</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Aiman Shahid</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/JOSTA20251224E0.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 


<section class="josta-issue-banner" aria-label="Journal issue banner">
  <div class="jib-wrap">


    <div class="jib-cover">
      <img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/cover.webp" alt="Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture – cover image">
    </div>


    <div class="jib-meta">
      <p class="jib-journal-tag">Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture</p>

      <h2 class="jib-subtitle anchored">
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Volume 02</a>
        •
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Issue 01</a>
        • 2026
      </h2>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">ISSN (online)</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://portal.issn.org/resource/ISSN/3107-6882" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-issn-link">
            3107-6882
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">License</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-license-link">
            CC BY-NC-ND 4.0
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>
    </div>

  </div>
</section>

<style>
  :root {
    --j-navy:#0053ed;
    --j-brown:#8b6a3a;
    --j-green:#0b5a56;
    --j-beige:#f8f3ea;
  }

  .josta-issue-banner {
    background: linear-gradient(115deg, var(--j-beige), #ffffff);
    border-bottom: 2px solid rgba(31, 52, 92, 0.12);
    padding: 1.8rem 1.4rem;
    margin-bottom: 1.6rem;
    font-family: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, "Segoe UI", sans-serif;
  }

  .jib-wrap {
    max-width: 1100px;
    margin: 0 auto;
    display: flex;
    gap: 1.6rem;
    align-items: center;
  }

  /* Cover image — NO ROUNDED CORNERS */
  .jib-cover img {
    display: block;
    max-width: 120px;
    height: auto;
    border-radius: 0;      /* removed curve */
    box-shadow: 0 6px 16px rgba(0,0,0,0.12);
  }

  .jib-journal-tag {
    margin: 0 0 0.4rem 0;
    font-size: 1.15rem;
    font-weight: 700;
    color: var(--j-green);
  }

  .jib-subtitle {
    margin: 0 0 0.7rem 0;
    font-size: 1rem;
    font-weight: 500;
    color: var(--j-navy);
    opacity: 0.85;
  }

  /* Volume/Issue links */
  .jib-vi-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-vi-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  .jib-line {
    margin: 0.15rem 0;
    font-size: 0.95rem;
    display: flex;
    gap: 0.4rem;
    align-items: baseline;
    color: #333;
  }

  .jib-label {
    font-weight: 600;
    color: var(--j-navy);
  }

  /* ISSN link */
  .jib-issn-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
  }
  .jib-issn-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  /* License link */
  .jib-license-link {
    color: var(--j-green);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-license-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: row; align-items: flex-start; }
    .jib-cover img { max-width: 90px; }
    .jib-journal-tag { font-size: 1.05rem; }
    .jib-subtitle { font-size: 0.9rem; }
  }

  @media (max-width: 480px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: column; align-items: flex-start; }
  }
</style>




<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202512.24E0"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/DOI-10.65287%2Fjosta.202512.24E0-blue?logo=doi" class="img-fluid" alt="DOI"></a> <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/18322008"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/View%20on-Zenodo-0b5a56?logo=zenodo&amp;labelColor=d9d9d9.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Zenodo"></a><br>
<img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Open%20Access-Yes-0b5a56?style=flat-square&amp;logo=openaccess&amp;logoColor=white.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Open Access"> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Status-Peer%20Reviewed-1f345c?style=flat-square.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Status"></p>
<!-- josta inline actions: pdf • copy citation • citation count -->
<div class="j-inline" style="margin-top:1rem;">
<p><a href="pdfs/JOSTA-202512-24E0.pdf" download="" class="j-btn" aria-label="download pdf">  <span>download pdf</span> </a></p>
<p>  <span>copy citation</span> <span id="j-tip" class="j-tip" aria-live="polite">citation copied!</span> </p>
<p><span class="j-chip" data-doi="10.65287/josta.202512.24E0" aria-label="citation count"> <span id="j-cite-count" class="j-chip-count">0</span> <span class="j-chip-label">citations</span> </span></p>
</div>
<!-- hidden citation text (kept as plain html) -->
<p id="j-citation-text" style="display:none;">
Muhammad, A. A., Chaudhary, B., Murtaza, H., Raza, M., Sajid, M., &amp; Shahid, A. (2026). Date Palm (Phoenix dactylifera) Propagation Techniques: A Comprehensive Review. Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture, 2(1). https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202512.24E0
</p>
<style>
/* row */
.j-inline{display:flex;align-items:center;gap:1rem;flex-wrap:nowrap}

/* button */
.j-btn{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.5rem;padding:.45rem 1rem;
  border-radius:999px;background:#8b6a3a;color:#fff;text-decoration:none;
  font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;
  box-shadow:0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.1);transition:background .25s ease}
.j-btn:hover{background:#6d532d}

/* copy link */
.j-copy{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.4rem;color:#1f345c;
  text-decoration:none;font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;position:relative}
.j-copy:hover{color:#0b5a56;text-decoration:underline}

/* tooltip */
.j-tip{visibility:hidden;opacity:0;transition:opacity .25s;
  background:#0b5a56;color:#fff;position:absolute;top:-34px;left:50%;
  transform:translateX(-50%);padding:.3rem .6rem;border-radius:6px;font-size:.75rem;white-space:nowrap}
.j-copy:focus .j-tip,.j-copy:active .j-tip{visibility:visible;opacity:1}

/* citation chip */
.j-chip{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.35rem;padding:.25rem .7rem;
  border:1px solid #ddd;border-radius:999px;background:#f8f7f5;
  font:400 .85rem/1 system-ui,"Segoe UI",Roboto,sans-serif;box-shadow:0 1px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.08)}
.j-chip-count{font-weight:700;font-size:1rem;color:#1f345c}
.j-chip-label{text-transform:uppercase;letter-spacing:.2px;color:#8b6a3a}

/* small screens: allow wrap with gentle spacing */
@media (max-width:540px){.j-inline{flex-wrap:wrap;row-gap:.6rem}}
</style>
<script>
function jCopyCitation(){
  const t=document.getElementById("j-citation-text").innerText.trim();
  navigator.clipboard.writeText(t);
  const tip=document.getElementById("j-tip");
  tip.style.visibility="visible"; tip.style.opacity="1";
  setTimeout(()=>{tip.style.visibility="hidden"; tip.style.opacity="0";},1600);
}

document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', async ()=>{
  const chip=document.querySelector('.j-chip'); if(!chip) return;
  const doi=chip.dataset.doi, el=document.getElementById('j-cite-count');
  const api=`https://api.crossref.org/works/${encodeURIComponent(doi)}?select=is-referenced-by-count`;
  try{
    const r=await fetch(api,{cache:'no-store'}); const j=await r.json();
    const n = j?.message?.['is-referenced-by-count'];
    el.textContent = (Number.isFinite(n) ? n : 0);
  }catch{ el.textContent='0'; }
});
</script>
<hr>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>The date palm (Phoenix dactylifera L.) is not merely a tree; it serves as a vital element of life in arid and semi-arid regions, representing significant economic and cultural value <span class="citation" data-cites="Chao2007">(Chao and Krueger 2007)</span>. This fruit-bearing tree plays a crucial role in sustaining food supplies and enhancing economies in several developing countries, emphasizing the importance of effective cultivation and multiplication methods for these trees <span class="citation" data-cites="Soomro2023">(Soomro, Marri, and Shaikh 2023)</span>. However, increasing the number of date palms is more complex than it appears, primarily due to their distinctive biology <span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2015">(Jaradat 2015)</span>. Being long-lived, single-stemmed plants that don’t reproduce naturally, the conventional methods we have used can frequently seem a bit limiting <span class="citation" data-cites="AlKhayri2018">(Al-Khayri et al. 2018)</span>. This inherently slow reproductive rate means that advancing date palm populations or enhancing their characteristics through standard breeding takes time, underscoring the necessity for diverse propagation strategies to navigate these natural limitations <span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span>.</p>
<p>Proficiently propagating date palms is not only about increasing the number of trees planted. It is also crucial for establishing new farms, replacing aging and less efficient trees, and promoting superior varieties that yield larger harvests, have better-tasting fruit, or are resistant to common pests and diseases <span class="citation" data-cites="Hadrami2009">(Hadrami and Hadrami 2009)</span>. The capacity to cultivate more of the top date palm varieties is vital for the sustained health and profitability of the entire date industry <span class="citation" data-cites="Supriatna2024">(Supriatna et al. 2024)</span>. This article intends to thoroughly examine the different methods employed in date palm propagation. This narrative review highlights the details of each technique, evaluate their advantages and disadvantages, compare their effectiveness based on existing research, consider the reasons behind choosing one method over another, delve into the latest innovations in the field, and specifically contrast traditional practices with modern techniques.</p>
</section>
<section id="literature-search-and-selection" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="literature-search-and-selection"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Literature search and selection</h2>
<p>The material was searched from Google Scholar database and the material was searched using different keywords (date palm, propagation, tissue culture, <em>in vitro</em> propagation, date palm biotechnology, CRISPR-CAS9) for integrative reviews published between 1990 to 2025. The total number of papers 36, including research articles, review articles, book chapters, reports and statistical reports.</p>
</section>
<section id="traditional-propagation-by-seed" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="traditional-propagation-by-seed"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Traditional propagation by seed</h2>
<p>Cultivating date palms from seeds, or sexual propagation, is an effective method to produce new plants using seeds from ripe dates. It typically begins with selecting the best seeds from fully matured dates <span class="citation" data-cites="Wakil2015">(Wakil et al. 2015)</span>. After sourcing the seeds, it’s crucial to clean them thoroughly to eliminate any sticky fruit pulp that may be present <span class="citation" data-cites="Alotaibi2023">(Alotaibi et al. 2023)</span>. To enhance the chances of germination, these cleansed seeds are generally soaked in fresh water for approximately 48 to 72 hours, with daily water changes to prevent mold or bacterial growth <span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2013">(Jaradat 2013)</span>. Occasionally, a technique called stratification is utilized, where the soaked seeds are placed in a moist medium, such as sand or vermiculite, and then refrigerated for one to three months. This simulates winter conditions and can significantly improve germination rates <span class="citation" data-cites="Robinson2009">(Robinson 2009)</span>. These preliminary steps are essential for breaking the seed’s dormancy and preparing them for growth, demonstrating a solid grasp of seed biology <span class="citation" data-cites="Nonogaki2017">(Nonogaki 2017)</span>. Once prepared, the seeds can be sown in a potting mixture that provides good drainage, ideally one designed specifically for palm trees, typically made from a blend of peat, perlite, and sand <span class="citation" data-cites="Maid2019">(Maid, Kitingan, and Kodoh 2019)</span>. Maintaining the right moisture level not too wet, and not too dry along with a warm temperature between 80 to 100°F (27°C to 38°C) and some indirect light is crucial for successful germination <span class="citation" data-cites="Bareke2018">(Bareke 2018)</span>. However, one should not anticipate rapid results; date palm seeds can take their time, often requiring several weeks to a few months to germinate, influenced by factors such as temperature and seed quality <span class="citation" data-cites="Mubaiwa2025">(Mubaiwa, Linnemann, and Maqsood 2025)</span>. The particular environmental requirements for these seeds to sprout emphasize the necessity of a controlled environment, especially in their initial stages, reflecting the date palm’s tropical or subtropical nature and its preference for warm, humid conditions during germination <span class="citation" data-cites="Klupczynska2021">(Klupczyńska and Pawłowski 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>One of the major advantages of growing plants from seeds is its straightforward nature, making it easy to start. It is also the fastest method to begin the propagation process <span class="citation" data-cites="Sallon2008">(Sallon et al. 2008)</span>. Perhaps most crucially, seed propagation brings genetic variety into the creation of new plants. This genetic diversity is a significant benefit for breeding initiatives aiming to cultivate improved varieties of date palms, potentially offering greater resistance to diseases, better tolerance for challenging environmental factors such as saline or arid soils, or simply enhancing the quality of the fruit <span class="citation" data-cites="Forneck2005">(Forneck 2005)</span>. Although it may not be the preferred approach for producing exact replicas for commercial agriculture, seed propagation plays an essential role in the long-term genetic enhancement and adaptation of date palms to evolving conditions <span class="citation" data-cites="Salgotra2023">(Salgotra and Chauhan 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Despite its ease, seed propagation has some notable disadvantages that make it less suitable for commercial date farming, where the primary objective is to maintain consistent traits of a selected variety. Date palms are dioecious, meaning they consist of separate male and female trees. Therefore, when seeds are planted, roughly half will turn out to be male, which do not yield fruit. Additionally, it is impossible to distinguish between males and females until they bloom, which typically occurs around seven years later. This inherent unpredictability results in wasted resources in commercial orchards as growers may invest in trees that will never produce fruit. Furthermore, since date palms are heterozygous, offspring grown from seeds will not be exact replicas of the parent trees. Seedlings exhibit significant genetic variation, which can lead to inconsistent fruit quality, differences in ripening times, and unpredictable yields compared to the parent palm. In fact, it is relatively uncommon for more than 10 percent of seed-grown palms to yield fruit suitable for commercial sale. To add to the challenges, date palms grown from seeds require a lengthy maturation period, often taking 8 to 10 years or even more before they begin to produce fruit, significantly diminishing the return on investment for growers. The inconsistency in fruit quality and the timing of harvest further complicates marketing the dates as a uniform product, creating a substantial obstacle in commercial environments. The numerous drawbacks of seed propagation in commercial date production explain why vegetative propagation methods are preferred when the goal is to preserve the purity of a cultivar and guarantee dependable fruit quality and yield <span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012 McDonald2012">(Jain 2012; McDonald and Copeland 2012)</span>.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="traditional-propagation-by-offshoots" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="traditional-propagation-by-offshoots"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Traditional propagation by offshoots</h2>
<p>Cultivating date palms through offshoots, also referred to as asexual or vegetative propagation, is a time-honored technique that utilizes the young plants, known as offshoots or suckers, which grow from buds at the base of the mother plant during its early growth stages <span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span>. These offshoots are genetic clones of the mother plant, ensuring they share the same genetic traits and produce identical desirable qualities. The procedure for detaching these offshoots requires a gentle approach and generally involves several steps. Firstly, you carefully excavate the soil surrounding the base of the offshoot to uncover its connection to the mother plant. Next, most of the leaves are trimmed back, leaving only about a dozen of the newest leaves tied together for easier handling. The roots of the offshoot are then cut back to a length ranging from 2 to 10 cm. Finally, a robust, wide chisel is driven between the offshoot and the mother plant, often utilizing a sledgehammer, to sever their bond. This detachment process demands skill to minimize stress on both the mother plant and the offshoot, as any damage can significantly influence the survival and growth of the offshoot.</p>
<p>The size of the offshoot is a critical factor in its ability to successfully take root and flourish. An ideal base diameter is typically between 10 and 35 cm. Offshoots within this size range usually possess more roots already developed and higher levels of stored carbohydrates and substances that promote root growth, which are essential for their survival and growth after separation. After being detached, the offshoots are usually replanted directly into the field where the new date palm plantation will be set up. Occasionally, they may first spend a year or two in a nursery to establish a stronger foundation before being relocated to their final site. Planting them at the correct depth is also crucial, with the area from which the roots emerge ideally placed 25 to 50 cm below the soil level. Regular watering is essential to maintain adequate soil moisture, particularly during the initial establishment period when the offshoot is forming its new root system.</p>
<p>Propagation through offshoots provides several notable benefits. Primarily, the offspring are genetically identical to the parent plant, guaranteeing that the fruit they yield will maintain the same high standards and desirable properties. This form of “true-to-type” propagation is crucial for commercial cultivators aiming to uphold the specific traits of their selected varieties. Moreover, palms that are cultivated from offshoots tend to bear fruit sooner, generally within 3 to 5 years of planting, which is considerably earlier than the extended timeline required for palms grown from seeds. This early production can lead to significant financial advantages, delivering a quicker return on investment.</p>
<p>On the flip side, there are also certain drawbacks associated with using offshoots. A significant limitation is the number of offshoots that a single mother plant can produce throughout its lifetime, usually ranging from 20 to 30, with only 3 to 4 being viable for planting in a given year. Some high-quality varieties may yield very few or even no offshoots, which further limits the application of this method for expanding their numbers. Consequently, the rate of propagation tends to be relatively slow and often fails to meet the swiftly rising demand for date palm trees. Additionally, the process of separating and planting offshoots demands considerable labor and requires skilled personnel. There is also the potential risk of introducing diseases and pests from the parent palm to the offshoots, with the red palm weevil posing a particularly vital threat. To prevent infestation, cut surfaces must be dressed with insecticides immediately after maintenance operations. This creates a chemical barrier at the injury site, countering the risk posed by semiochemicals released from the wound that otherwise signal suitable egg-laying locations to female weevils <span class="citation" data-cites="Naveed2023">(Naveed et al. 2023)</span>. The survival rates of offshoots can vary significantly, ranging from as low as 10% to as high as 90%, influenced by factors such as the offshoot’s size, the specific variety, and the surrounding environmental conditions. For example, offshoots from the Medjool variety tend to be more difficult to establish than those from varieties like Deglet Nour or Zahidi. Finally, mother palms only generate offshoots during their juvenile stage, which typically lasts around 10 to 15 years, thus limiting the long-term availability of these young plants from older, potentially superior palm specimens.</p>
</section>
<section id="modern-propagation-by-tissue-culture" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modern-propagation-by-tissue-culture"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Modern propagation by tissue culture</h2>
<p>Tissue culture, also known as micropropagation, provides a contemporary approach to the propagation of date palms, enabling the rapid production of numerous plants. This method entails the extraction of small segments of plant tissue, including stem tips, nodes, meristems, embryos, or seeds, and cultivating them into complete plants in a sterile and nutrient-rich environment with precisely managed conditions. Tissue culture significantly surpasses traditional propagation methods by allowing for the production of a larger number of plants in a shorter time. There are two primary pathways for date palm tissue culture: somatic embryogenesis and organogenesis. Somatic embryogenesis refers to the creation of somatic embryos from somatic cells, often beginning with a callus stage, which consists of a cluster of undifferentiated plant cells. These somatic embryos progress through various developmental phases until they mature into fully formed plantlets. Due to its potential for quick and extensive plant production, somatic embryogenesis is commonly chosen in many commercial laboratories. Conversely, organogenesis is characterized by the direct or indirect emergence of new buds or shoots from the initial plant tissue, which later transform into plantlets. A popular technique within organogenesis is shoot tip culture. Direct organogenesis, which bypasses the callus phase, is often preferred as it minimizes the likelihood of genetic variations <span class="citation" data-cites="Rajmohan2011 Zaid2011">(Rajmohan 2011; Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span>.</p>
<p><strong>Steps involved in date palm tissue culture</strong></p>
<p>The general steps involved in date palm tissue culture typically include as indicated <span class="citation" data-cites="CoskunKaplan2025">(Coşkun and Kaplan 2025)</span>:</p>
<p><strong>Selecting and sterilizing the plant material (explant):</strong> The procedure starts with the selection of appropriate plant material, or explants, which may include shoot tips from seedlings or offsets, young flower clusters, or seeds’ embryos. These explants undergo careful sterilization to remove any surface impurities such as bacteria and fungi, as ensuring a sterile environment is essential for the success of tissue culture.</p>
<p><strong>Initiating the culture:</strong> The sterilized explant is placed onto a nutrient-dense culture medium, typically a gel made from agar, which is enriched with specific plant growth regulators like auxins (for example, naphthaleneacetic acid - NAA, 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid - 2,4-D) and cytokinin (such as 6-benzylaminopurine - BA, kinetin). These growth regulators are crucial for either promoting the formation of a callus or the direct development of shoots or embryos, depending on the selected technique. Activated charcoal is frequently incorporated into the medium to absorb any inhibitory substances released by the explant.</p>
<p><strong>Multiplication:</strong> After the initial cultures are established, they are moved to a multiplication medium, which consists of a different ratio of plant growth regulators designed to encourage the proliferation of additional shoots or embryos. To enhance multiplication rates, some laboratories utilize liquid media or temporary immersion systems (TIS), which periodically submerge the cultures in a nutrient solution, thereby improving nutrient absorption and gas exchange.</p>
<p><strong>Rooting:</strong> The multiplied shoots are then separated and placed onto a rooting medium, usually containing a higher concentration of auxins and minimal to no cytokinin. This hormonal configuration stimulates the formation of a robust root system, which is vital for the survival of the plantlets once they are transferred to soil.</p>
<p><strong>Acclimatization:</strong> The final stage consists of gradually acclimating the rooted plantlets to the external environment outside the laboratory. This process, also referred to as hardening, involves slowly decreasing humidity while increasing light intensity and temperature variations to prepare the plantlets for the conditions they will encounter in a greenhouse or nursery before being planted in the field.</p>
<p>Tissue culture provides numerous benefits compared to conventional propagation techniques. It facilitates quick and extensive production of uniform plants in a relatively short timeframe, effectively addressing the slow rate of offshoot production. Plants cultivated through tissue culture are generally free from diseases since they are raised in sterile environments, unlike offshoots, which may transmit illnesses. The plants generated are typically genetically identical (clones), ensuring consistency in growth, development, and fruit quality, which is highly advantageous for commercial production and marketing. Tissue culture can be conducted throughout the year, independent of seasonal changes, ensuring a steady supply of planting material. It is also crucial for preserving elite genotypes, particularly rare or endangered varieties, or those that do not produce offshoots. Moreover, tissue culture methods can be integrated with genetic enhancement techniques such as in vitro mutagenesis and genetic transformation to create improved date palm varieties. Finally, tissue culture plantlets are often more compact and easier to transport than bulky offshoots, thereby lowering transportation expenses and logistical issues <span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span>.</p>
<p>While tissue culture offers numerous advantages, it also presents various challenges. Establishing and maintaining a tissue culture laboratory can involve considerable initial expenses, necessitating investments in specialized infrastructure, equipment, chemicals, and trained personnel. The process requires a certain level of technical skill, as it relies on technicians and researchers who possess specific expertise in plant tissue culture. There exists the risk of soma clonal variation, which can occur when genetic changes arise during tissue culture, especially through somatic embryogenesis that includes a callus stage, resulting in the production of plants that may not be true to the original type. Transferring tissue culture plantlets to their natural habitats can be complicated, and improper acclimatization may result in elevated mortality rates. There is a persistent threat of bacterial and fungal contamination in tissue cultures, which may lead to the loss of entire batches. Physiological issues such as tissue browning and vitrification (hyperhydricity) can also arise in culture, adversely impacting the growth and development of the plantlets; furthermore, premature rooting of buds can disrupt the multiplication phase. Some research has indicated the likelihood of abnormal fruit formation in plants that have been propagated through somatic embryogenesis <span class="citation" data-cites="Herman2015 Oseni2018">(Herman 2015; Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="comparison-of-success-rates-of-different-propagation-techniques" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparison-of-success-rates-of-different-propagation-techniques"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Comparison of success rates of different propagation techniques</h2>
<p>Multiple factors influence the establishment success of offshoots, including their size and specific variety. For instance, Medjool offshoots tend to have lower survival rates compared to varieties like Deglet Nour or Zahidi <span class="citation" data-cites="Alasasfa2022">(Alasasfa 2022)</span>. Typically, offshoots with a base diameter ranging from 10 to 35 cm exhibit the highest survival rates, which can span from 83% to 95%. This highlights the importance of selecting appropriately sized offshoots to enhance their chances of successful establishment.</p>
<p>Conversely, tissue culture frequently achieves very high survival rates once the plants have been properly acclimatized, with certain studies reporting rates nearing 100%. However, the initial stages of tissue culture are at risk of contamination. The time required for the plants to mature and start producing fruit varies between the methods used. Offshoot-grown palms typically begin yielding harvestable fruits within 3 to 5 years. Tissue culture plants can also start fruiting relatively early, usually around 4 years after they are planted. In contrast, palms grown from seeds have a significantly longer juvenile phase, often taking 8 to 10 years or even longer to bear fruit. Research has also compared various tissue culture methods, revealing that temporary immersion systems (TIS) may enhance vigor and achieve a higher acclimatization rate (95%) compared to traditional gel-based systems (82%) <span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2024">(Zaid 2024)</span>.</p>
<div id="tbl-technique" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-technique-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Comparison of different propagation techniques
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-technique-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 30%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Feature</th>
<th>Seed Propagation</th>
<th>Offshoot Propagation</th>
<th>Tissue Culture</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Success Rate</td>
<td>Low and variable (low percentage female, poor quality)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
<td>Moderate to high (size and cultivar dependent)<span class="citation" data-cites="Drummond1919 Alasasfa2022">(Drummond 1919; Alasasfa 2022)</span></td>
<td>High (after acclimatization), initial contamination risk <span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2024">(Zaid 2024)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Time to Maturity</td>
<td>Very long (8–10+ years)<span class="citation" data-cites="McDonald2012">(McDonald and Copeland 2012)</span></td>
<td>Medium (3–5 years)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>Medium (around 4 years)<span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Genetic Uniformity</td>
<td>Low (off-type progeny)<span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span></td>
<td>High (true-to-type)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>High (generally true-to-type, risk of somaclonal variation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Herman2015 Oseni2018">(Herman 2015; Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Multiplication Rate</td>
<td>High (number of seeds)<span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2015">(Jaradat 2015)</span></td>
<td>Low (limited number of offshoots)<span class="citation" data-cites="Hadrami2009">(Hadrami and Hadrami 2009)</span></td>
<td>Very high (potential for mass propagation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Disease Transmission Risk</td>
<td>Low (if seeds are clean)<span class="citation" data-cites="Alotaibi2023">(Alotaibi et al. 2023)</span></td>
<td>Moderate to high (from mother plant)<span class="citation" data-cites="Wakil2015">(Wakil et al. 2015)</span></td>
<td>Low (disease-free plants)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Cost</td>
<td>Low initial cost<span class="citation" data-cites="Sallon2008">(Sallon et al. 2008)</span></td>
<td>Moderate (labor-intensive)<span class="citation" data-cites="Chao2007">(Chao and Krueger 2007)</span></td>
<td>High initial cost (lab setup, expertise)<span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Scalability</td>
<td>Potentially high for breeding<span class="citation" data-cites="Forneck2005">(Forneck 2005)</span></td>
<td>Low for rapid expansion<span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span></td>
<td>High for commercial production<span class="citation" data-cites="Mehbub2022">(Mehbub et al. 2022)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Complexity</td>
<td>Simple<span class="citation" data-cites="Bareke2018">(Bareke 2018)</span></td>
<td>Moderate (requires skill for separation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>High (requires technical expertise)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="choosing-appropriate-propagation-technique" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-appropriate-propagation-technique"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Choosing Appropriate propagation technique</h2>
<p>Selecting the most appropriate technique for propagating date palms largely depends on several factors, with cost frequently being a significant aspect. Propagating through seeds typically acquires the lowest initial expenses but requires a lengthy period before bearing fruit and presents uncertainties regarding fruit quality. Offshoot propagation involves moderate costs, largely due to the labor needed for the separation and planting process. Although tissue culture demands a considerable upfront investment for laboratory setup and staff training, it can become more economically viable over time for large-scale production of high-value varieties, particularly when considering the potential for increased yields and consistent quality. The volume of propagation required is also a crucial factor in determining which method to select. Seed propagation is not ideal for commercially cultivating specific varieties due to the variability in genetics. Offshoot propagation is constrained by the number of offshoots produced by a parent palm. Tissue culture thus emerges as the optimal solution for extensive multiplication to satisfy significant demands for planting material <span class="citation" data-cites="Mehbub2022">(Mehbub et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>For commercial endeavors, preserving the desired traits of a particular variety is essential, making offshoot and tissue culture the favored options over seed propagation. The resources and infrastructure available also influence the practicality of a method. For instance, tissue culture requires specialized lab facilities and a skilled team. The purpose for which the propagated plants will be used is an additional vital consideration. While seed propagation is unsuitable for commercial orchards, it still serves as an important method in breeding programs that aim to create new varieties with enhanced characteristics. Lastly, although the suitability of a region for date palm cultivation is primarily determined by climate and soil conditions, these elements indirectly influence the choice of propagation by affecting the overall success and productivity of the resulting plantation.</p>
</section>
<section id="recent-advancements-and-novel-techniques-in-date-palm-propagation-research" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-advancements-and-novel-techniques-in-date-palm-propagation-research"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Recent advancements and novel techniques in date palm propagation research</h2>
<p>Recent advancements in date palm propagation have shifted from general protocol optimization to targeted solutions for critical production bottlenecks, specifically addressing scalability, genetic fidelity, and biotic stress resistance. Advances in tissue culture techniques include the creation and application of bioreactor-based systems and temporary immersion systems (TIS), which have demonstrated significant potential in boosting the multiplication rate of plants and aiding their adaptation to external growth conditions <span class="citation" data-cites="Anuradha2025">(Anuradha et al. 2025)</span>. Researchers have also been looking into alternative plant material sources for tissue culture, such as young female flower clusters, which may be more accessible than offshoots, especially for uncommon varieties, and could help expedite the overall propagation timeline.</p>
<p>The use of molecular markers (including SSRs, SNPs, DArT) and genetic engineering approaches like CRISPR-Cas9 is increasingly prominent in date palm propagation studies. These methodologies allow for precise identification of various cultivars, ensuring that tissue-cultured plants maintain genetic fidelity, and enable the introduction of advantageous traits such as pest and disease resistance, environmental stress tolerance, and enhanced fruit quality. In vitro mutagenesis, frequently utilizing gamma radiation, is being explored as a strategy to generate genetic variation and develop mutant types with desirable characteristics, including resistance to Bayoud disease, a significant fungal threat to date palms <span class="citation" data-cites="Pandey2024">(Pandey et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>One particularly intriguing research avenue involves resurrecting ancient date palm varieties from seeds discovered at archaeological sites, some of which date back 2000 years. These endeavors underscore the impressive durability of date palm seeds and present a distinctive chance to recover potentially valuable traits that may have vanished over time. Moreover, there is ongoing research aimed at creating cost-effective tissue culture methods to make micropropagation more feasible for a broader spectrum of growers, especially in areas where date palm farming plays a crucial economic role <span class="citation" data-cites="GrosBalthazard2021">(Gros-Balthazard et al. 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>Recent advancements in date palm propagation have shifted from general protocol optimization to targeted solutions for critical production bottlenecks, specifically addressing scalability, genetic fidelity, and biotic stress resistance. To overcome the limitations of low multiplication rates and high acclimatization losses in conventional tissue culture, bioreactor-based Temporary Immersion Systems (TIS) have been introduced, which significantly enhanced nutrient uptake and have been shown to boost acclimatization success rates, compared to traditional gel-based systems. Simultaneously, the risk of somaclonal variation a major threat to commercial uniformity is being addressed through the integration of molecular markers (SSRs, SNPs, DArT), which allow for the precise validation of genetic fidelity at the <em>in vitro</em> stage. Furthermore, to bypass the date palm’s long juvenile breeding phase and combat specific threats like Bayoud disease, researchers are utilizing <em>in vitro</em> mutagenesis and CRISPR-Cas9 gene editing to introduce targeted resistance traits and improve fruit quality. Finally, novel efforts to recover lost genetic diversity involve the resurrection of ancient germplasm from 2,000-year-old seeds, providing a unique reservoir of traits for future breeding programs <span class="citation" data-cites="Pandey2024 Zaid2024">(Pandey et al. 2024; Zaid 2024)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-and-future-perspectives" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-and-future-perspectives"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> Conclusion and future perspectives</h2>
<p>This review has examined the various techniques for propagating date palms, ranging from conventional methods like seed and offshoot propagation to contemporary strategies such as tissue culture. Each technique has its unique advantages and disadvantages, making the selection of a method contingent on particular objectives, operational scale, available resources, and expected results. In commercial production aimed at preserving variety purity and ensuring consistent fruit quality, vegetative propagation through offshoots and increasingly, tissue culture, are favored methods. Although offshoot propagation has historically been the preferred approach, its limitations regarding the speed of plant multiplication and the risk of disease transmission are being mitigated by progress in tissue culture technology.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, future research and development in date palm propagation should target several critical areas. It is essential to further improve tissue culture techniques, particularly for varieties that have proven difficult to grow in vitro. Creating cost-effective and accessible tissue culture solutions will be vital for broader adoption, especially in developing regions where date palm farming is crucial. Ongoing research into in vitro mutagenesis and genetic engineering shows great potential for producing enhanced date palm varieties that exhibit better resistance to environmental stresses and pests, along with superior fruit quality. Investigations aimed at enhancing the acclimatization of tissue culture plantlets will be important for boosting survival rates across various environmental settings. Long-term studies assessing the performance and stability of date palms grown from tissue culture are necessary to thoroughly evaluate their viability throughout their productive lifespan. Lastly, looking into traditional knowledge and practices in regions like Pakistan and exploring how they can be combined with modern techniques could foster more sustainable and culturally relevant methods of date palm farming. Ultimately, choosing the most appropriate propagation technique is crucial for ensuring the sustainable expansion and productivity of the global date palm industry. However, tissue culture is a suitable propagation method in Large-scale commercial production and rapid expansion of elite varieties.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<!-- References will be rendered here -->
<div id="ref-Alasasfa2022" class="csl-entry">
Alasasfa, M. 2022. <span>“Effect of Cultivar and Offshoots Weight on Survival Rate and Some Vegetative Parameters of Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera) in Jordan Valley.”</span> <em>International Journal of Mechanical Engineering Education, Kalahari Journal</em> 7: 110–14.
</div>
<div id="ref-AlKhayri2018" class="csl-entry">
Al-Khayri, J. M., P. M. Naik, S. M. Jain, and D. V. Johnson. 2018. <span>“Advances in Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.) Breeding.”</span> In <em>Advances in Plant Breeding Strategies: Fruits</em>, 3:727–71. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91944-7_18">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91944-7_18</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Alotaibi2023" class="csl-entry">
Alotaibi, K. D., H. A. Alharbi, M. W. Yaish, I. Ahmed, S. A. Alharbi, F. Alotaibi, and Y. Kuzyakov. 2023. <span>“Date Palm Cultivation: A Review of Soil and Environmental Conditions and Future Challenges.”</span> <em>Land Degradation &amp; Development</em> 34: 2431–44. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.4619">https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.4619</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Anuradha2025" class="csl-entry">
Anuradha, M., S. Balasubramanya, G. Subbalakshmi, and P. Shilpa. 2025. <span>“Commercialization of in Vitro Secondary Metabolite Production: Challenges and Opportunities.”</span> In <em>In Vitro Production of Plant Secondary Metabolites: Theory and Practice</em>, 321–46. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-97-8808-8_25">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-97-8808-8_25</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bareke2018" class="csl-entry">
Bareke, T. 2018. <span>“Biology of Seed Development and Germination Physiology.”</span> <em>Advances in Plants &amp; Agriculture Research</em> 8: 336–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.15406/apar.2018.08.00335">https://doi.org/10.15406/apar.2018.08.00335</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bhansali2009" class="csl-entry">
Bhansali, R. R. 2009. <span>“Date Palm Cultivation in the Changing Scenario of Indian Arid Zones: Challenges and Prospects.”</span> In <em>Desert Plants: Biology and Biotechnology</em>, 423–59. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-02550-1_20">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-02550-1_20</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Chao2007" class="csl-entry">
Chao, C. T., and R. R. Krueger. 2007. <span>“The Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.): Overview of Biology, Uses, and Cultivation.”</span> <em>HortScience</em> 42: 1077–82. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTSCI.42.5.1077">https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTSCI.42.5.1077</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-CoskunKaplan2025" class="csl-entry">
Coşkun, Ö. F., and M. Kaplan. 2025. <span>“Edible Succulent Plants: Agricultural Value, Nutritional Characteristics and Micropropagation Approaches.”</span> In <em>Innovative Applications and Research Methods in Agriculture, Forestry and Aquaculture</em>, edited by İ. Daşdemir and H. Yazıcı, 289–312. Platanus Publishing. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18049952">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18049952</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Drummond1919" class="csl-entry">
Drummond, B. 1919. <em>Propagation and Culture of the Date Palm</em>. Bulletin 1016. U.S. Government Printing Office.
</div>
<div id="ref-Forneck2005" class="csl-entry">
Forneck, A. 2005. <span>“Plant Breeding: Clonality—a Concept for Stability and Variability During Vegetative Propagation.”</span> In <em>Progress in Botany: Genetics Physiology Systematics Ecology</em>, 164–83. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-27043-4_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-27043-4_8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-GrosBalthazard2021" class="csl-entry">
Gros-Balthazard, M., J. M. Flowers, K. M. Hazzouri, S. Ferrand, F. Aberlenc, S. Sallon, and M. D. Purugganan. 2021. <span>“The Genomes of Ancient Date Palms Germinated from 2,000 y Old Seeds.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> 118: e2025337118. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2025337118">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2025337118</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hadrami2009" class="csl-entry">
Hadrami, I. E., and A. E. Hadrami. 2009. <span>“Breeding Date Palm.”</span> In <em>Breeding Plantation Tree Crops: Tropical Species</em>, 191–216. New York: Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-71201-7_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-71201-7_6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Herman2015" class="csl-entry">
Herman, E. B. 2015. <span>“Plant Tissue Culture Contamination: Challenges and Opportunities.”</span> In <em>VI International Symposium on Production and Establishment of Micropropagated Plants</em>, 1155:231–38. Acta Horticulturae. Leuven, Belgium: International Society for Horticultural Science. <a href="https://doi.org/10.17660/ActaHortic.2017.1155.33">https://doi.org/10.17660/ActaHortic.2017.1155.33</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jain2012" class="csl-entry">
Jain, S. M. 2012. <span>“Date Palm Biotechnology: Current Status and Prospective—an Overview.”</span> <em>Emirates Journal of Food and Agriculture</em> 24: 386–99.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jaradat2013" class="csl-entry">
Jaradat, A. A. 2013. <span>“Date Palm: Production.”</span> In <em>Dates: Postharvest Science, Processing Technology and Health Benefits</em>, 29–55. Chichester, UK: Wiley-Blackwell. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118292419.ch2">https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118292419.ch2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jaradat2015" class="csl-entry">
———. 2015. <span>“Biodiversity, Genetic Diversity, and Genetic Resources of Date Palm.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Genetic Resources and Utilization: Africa and the Americas</em>, 1:19–71. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-9694-1_2">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-9694-1_2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Klupczynska2021" class="csl-entry">
Klupczyńska, E. A., and T. A. Pawłowski. 2021. <span>“Regulation of Seed Dormancy and Germination Mechanisms in a Changing Environment.”</span> <em>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</em> 22: 1357. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Maid2019" class="csl-entry">
Maid, M., C. Kitingan, and J. Kodoh. 2019. <span>“Managing Planting Materials and Planting Stock Production of Tropical Tree Species.”</span> In <em>Prospects and Utilization of Tropical Plantation Trees</em>, 29–73. London, UK: IntechOpen. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-McDonald2012" class="csl-entry">
McDonald, M. F., and L. O. Copeland. 2012. <em>Seed Production: Principles and Practices</em>. Springer Science &amp; Business Media.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mehbub2022" class="csl-entry">
Mehbub, H., A. Akter, M. A. Akter, M. S. H. Mandal, M. A. Hoque, M. Tuleja, and H. Mehraj. 2022. <span>“Tissue Culture in Ornamentals: Cultivation Factors, Propagation Techniques, and Its Application.”</span> <em>Plants</em> 11: 3208. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11233208">https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11233208</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mubaiwa2025" class="csl-entry">
Mubaiwa, J., A. R. Linnemann, and S. Maqsood. 2025. <span>“New Insights into the Influence of the Characteristic <span>‘Stone’</span> Feature of the Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.) Seeds on Its Sustainable Processing Approaches—a Review.”</span> <em>Food and Bioprocess Technology</em>, 1–33. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-024-03474-1">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-024-03474-1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Naveed2023" class="csl-entry">
Naveed, H., V. Andoh, W. Islam, L. Chen, and K. Chen. 2023. <span>“<a href="">Sustainable Pest Management in Date Palm Ecosystems: Unveiling the Ecological Dynamics of <span>Red Palm Weevil</span> (<span>Coleoptera</span>: <span>Curculionidae</span>) Infestations</a>.”</span> <em>Insects</em> 14: 859.
</div>
<div id="ref-Nonogaki2017" class="csl-entry">
Nonogaki, H. 2017. <span>“Seed Biology Updates–Highlights and New Discoveries in Seed Dormancy and Germination Research.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Plant Science</em> 8: 524. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.00524">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.00524</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Oseni2018" class="csl-entry">
Oseni, O. M., V. Pande, and T. K. Nailwal. 2018. <span>“A Review on Plant Tissue Culture, a Technique for Propagation and Conservation of Endangered Plant Species.”</span> <em>International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences</em> 7: 3778–86. <a href="https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2018.707.438">https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2018.707.438</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Pandey2024" class="csl-entry">
Pandey, N., P. Tripathi, N. Pandey, H. Nakum, and Y. S. Vala. 2024. <span>“Advancements in Date Palm Genomics and Biotechnology Genomic Resources to the Precision Agriculture: A Comprehensive Review.”</span> <em>Preprints</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202406.1327.v2">https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202406.1327.v2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rajmohan2011" class="csl-entry">
Rajmohan, K. 2011. <span>“Date Palm Tissue Culture: A Pathway to Rural Development.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Biotechnology</em>, 29–45. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_3">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Robinson2009" class="csl-entry">
Robinson, M. L. 2009. <span>“Cultivated Palm Seed Germination.”</span> SP-02-09. University of Nevada Cooperative Extension. <a href="https://naes.agnt.unr.edu/PMS/Pubs/2002-3243.pdf">https://naes.agnt.unr.edu/PMS/Pubs/2002-3243.pdf</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Salgotra2023" class="csl-entry">
Salgotra, R. K., and B. S. Chauhan. 2023. <span>“Genetic Diversity, Conservation, and Utilization of Plant Genetic Resources.”</span> <em>Genes</em> 14: 174. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14010174">https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14010174</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Sallon2008" class="csl-entry">
Sallon, S., E. Solowey, Y. Cohen, R. Korchinsky, M. Egli, I. Woodhatch, O. Simchoni, and M. Kislev. 2008. <span>“Germination, Genetics, and Growth of an Ancient Date Seed.”</span> <em>Science</em> 320: 1464. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1153600">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1153600</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Soomro2023" class="csl-entry">
Soomro, A. H., A. Marri, and N. Shaikh. 2023. <span>“Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera): A Review of Economic Potential, Industrial Valorization, Nutritional and Health Significance.”</span> In <em>Neglected Plant Foods of South Asia: Exploring and Valorizing Nature to Feed Hunger</em>, 319–50. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37077-9_13">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37077-9_13</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Supriatna2024" class="csl-entry">
Supriatna, J., A. B. Saluy, D. Kurniawan, and D. Djumarno. 2024. <span>“Promoting Sustainable Performance of Smallholder Oil Palm Farmers: An Analysis of Key Determinants and Strategic Priorities.”</span> <em>International Journal of Productivity and Performance Management</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/IJPPM-12-2023-0647">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJPPM-12-2023-0647</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Wakil2015" class="csl-entry">
Wakil, W., J. R. Faleiro, T. A. Miller, G. O. Bedford, and R. R. Krueger. 2015. <span>“Date Palm Production and Pest Management Challenges.”</span> In <em>Sustainable Pest Management in Date Palm: Current Status and Emerging Challenges</em>, 1–11. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24397-9_1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24397-9_1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zaid2024" class="csl-entry">
Zaid, A. 2024. <em>Date Palm Cultivation</em>. Food; Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4060/cc9251en">https://doi.org/10.4060/cc9251en</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zaid2011" class="csl-entry">
Zaid, A., B. El-Korchi, and H. J. Visser. 2011. <span>“Commercial Date Palm Tissue Culture Procedures and Facility Establishment.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Biotechnology</em>, 137–80. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_8</a>.
</div>
</div>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled" title="Publication &amp; Reviewer Details">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Important</span>Publication &amp; Reviewer Details
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><strong>Publication Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Submitted:</strong> <em>13 December 2025</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Accepted:</strong> <em>20 January 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Published (Online):</strong> <em>22 January 2026</em></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Reviewer Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 1:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 2:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Disclaimer/Publisher’s Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of the publisher and/or the editor(s).<br>
The publisher and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>© Copyright (2025): Author(s). The licensee is the journal publisher. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>, which permits non-commercial use, sharing, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and no modifications or adaptations are made.</p>
</blockquote>



</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Review-Article</category>
  <category>Horticulture</category>
  <category>Plantation-crops</category>
  <guid>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/JOSTA20251224E0.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
