<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>JOSTA</title>
<link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Saline and Sodic Soil Reclamation: Recent Advances and Agronomic Implications</title>
  <dc:creator>Krishna Priyan Ra K*</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vasanth P</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kannappan M</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA202601A408/JOSTA202601A408.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 

<section class="josta-issue-banner" aria-label="Journal issue banner">
  <div class="jib-wrap">


    <div class="jib-cover">
      <img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA202601A408/cover.webp" alt="Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture – cover image">
    </div>


    <div class="jib-meta">
      <p class="jib-journal-tag">Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture</p>

      <h2 class="jib-subtitle anchored">
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Volume 02</a>
        •
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Issue 01</a>
        • 2026
      </h2>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">ISSN (online)</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://portal.issn.org/resource/ISSN/3107-6882" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-issn-link">
            3107-6882
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">License</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-license-link">
            CC BY-NC-ND 4.0
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>
    </div>

  </div>
</section>

<style>
  :root {
    --j-navy:#0053ed;
    --j-brown:#8b6a3a;
    --j-green:#0b5a56;
    --j-beige:#f8f3ea;
  }

  .josta-issue-banner {
    background: linear-gradient(115deg, var(--j-beige), #ffffff);
    border-bottom: 2px solid rgba(31, 52, 92, 0.12);
    padding: 1.8rem 1.4rem;
    margin-bottom: 1.6rem;
    font-family: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, "Segoe UI", sans-serif;
  }

  .jib-wrap {
    max-width: 1100px;
    margin: 0 auto;
    display: flex;
    gap: 1.6rem;
    align-items: center;
  }

  /* Cover image — NO ROUNDED CORNERS */
  .jib-cover img {
    display: block;
    max-width: 120px;
    height: auto;
    border-radius: 0;      /* removed curve */
    box-shadow: 0 6px 16px rgba(0,0,0,0.12);
  }

  .jib-journal-tag {
    margin: 0 0 0.4rem 0;
    font-size: 1.15rem;
    font-weight: 700;
    color: var(--j-green);
  }

  .jib-subtitle {
    margin: 0 0 0.7rem 0;
    font-size: 1rem;
    font-weight: 500;
    color: var(--j-navy);
    opacity: 0.85;
  }

  /* Volume/Issue links */
  .jib-vi-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-vi-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  .jib-line {
    margin: 0.15rem 0;
    font-size: 0.95rem;
    display: flex;
    gap: 0.4rem;
    align-items: baseline;
    color: #333;
  }

  .jib-label {
    font-weight: 600;
    color: var(--j-navy);
  }

  /* ISSN link */
  .jib-issn-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
  }
  .jib-issn-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  /* License link */
  .jib-license-link {
    color: var(--j-green);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-license-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: row; align-items: flex-start; }
    .jib-cover img { max-width: 90px; }
    .jib-journal-tag { font-size: 1.05rem; }
    .jib-subtitle { font-size: 0.9rem; }
  }

  @media (max-width: 480px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: column; align-items: flex-start; }
  }
</style>




<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202601.A408"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/DOI-10.65287%2Fjosta.202601.A408-blue?logo=doi" class="img-fluid" alt="DOI"></a> <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/18669478"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/View%20on-Zenodo-0b5a56?logo=zenodo&amp;labelColor=d9d9d9.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Zenodo"></a><br>
<img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Open%20Access-Yes-0b5a56?style=flat-square&amp;logo=openaccess&amp;logoColor=white.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Open Access"> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Status-Peer%20Reviewed-1f345c?style=flat-square.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Status"></p>
<!-- josta inline actions: pdf • copy citation • citation count -->
<div class="j-inline" style="margin-top:1rem;">
<p><a href="pdfs/JOSTA-202601-A408.pdf" download="" class="j-btn" aria-label="download pdf">  <span>download pdf</span> </a></p>
<p>  <span>copy citation</span> <span id="j-tip" class="j-tip" aria-live="polite">citation copied!</span> </p>
<p><span class="j-chip" data-doi="10.65287/josta.202601.A408" aria-label="citation count"> <span id="j-cite-count" class="j-chip-count">0</span> <span class="j-chip-label">citations</span> </span></p>
</div>
<!-- hidden citation text (kept as plain html) -->
<p id="j-citation-text" style="display:none;">
Krishna, P. R. K., Vasanth, P., &amp; Kannappan, M. (2026). Saline and Sodic Soil Reclamation: Recent Advances and Agronomic Implications. Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture, 2(1). https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202601.A408
</p>
<style>
/* row */
.j-inline{display:flex;align-items:center;gap:1rem;flex-wrap:nowrap}

/* button */
.j-btn{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.5rem;padding:.45rem 1rem;
  border-radius:999px;background:#8b6a3a;color:#fff;text-decoration:none;
  font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;
  box-shadow:0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.1);transition:background .25s ease}
.j-btn:hover{background:#6d532d}

/* copy link */
.j-copy{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.4rem;color:#1f345c;
  text-decoration:none;font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;position:relative}
.j-copy:hover{color:#0b5a56;text-decoration:underline}

/* tooltip */
.j-tip{visibility:hidden;opacity:0;transition:opacity .25s;
  background:#0b5a56;color:#fff;position:absolute;top:-34px;left:50%;
  transform:translateX(-50%);padding:.3rem .6rem;border-radius:6px;font-size:.75rem;white-space:nowrap}
.j-copy:focus .j-tip,.j-copy:active .j-tip{visibility:visible;opacity:1}

/* citation chip */
.j-chip{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.35rem;padding:.25rem .7rem;
  border:1px solid #ddd;border-radius:999px;background:#f8f7f5;
  font:400 .85rem/1 system-ui,"Segoe UI",Roboto,sans-serif;box-shadow:0 1px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.08)}
.j-chip-count{font-weight:700;font-size:1rem;color:#1f345c}
.j-chip-label{text-transform:uppercase;letter-spacing:.2px;color:#8b6a3a}

/* small screens: allow wrap with gentle spacing */
@media (max-width:540px){.j-inline{flex-wrap:wrap;row-gap:.6rem}}
</style>
<script>
function jCopyCitation(){
  const t=document.getElementById("j-citation-text").innerText.trim();
  navigator.clipboard.writeText(t);
  const tip=document.getElementById("j-tip");
  tip.style.visibility="visible"; tip.style.opacity="1";
  setTimeout(()=>{tip.style.visibility="hidden"; tip.style.opacity="0";},1600);
}

document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', async ()=>{
  const chip=document.querySelector('.j-chip'); if(!chip) return;
  const doi=chip.dataset.doi, el=document.getElementById('j-cite-count');
  const api=`https://api.crossref.org/works/${encodeURIComponent(doi)}?select=is-referenced-by-count`;
  try{
    const r=await fetch(api,{cache:'no-store'}); const j=await r.json();
    const n = j?.message?.['is-referenced-by-count'];
    el.textContent = (Number.isFinite(n) ? n : 0);
  }catch{ el.textContent='0'; }
});
</script>
<hr>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>Soil salinization and sodification constitute major forms of land degradation that significantly constrain agricultural productivity worldwide. Salt-affected soils are characterized by excessive concentrations of soluble salts and/or exchangeable sodium, leading to deterioration of soil structure, reduced water infiltration, nutrient deficiencies, and osmotic stress in plants. According to the FAO/UNESCO soil map, approximately 1030 million hectares of land globally are degraded due to excessive salt exposure, with an estimated 1.5 million hectares lost annually to salinization <span class="citation" data-cites="Luo2025">(Luo et al. 2025)</span>.</p>
<p>The problem is particularly acute in arid and semi-arid regions where scanty rainfall coupled with high temperatures facilitates salt accumulation. By 2050, it is predicted that nearly 50% of global arable land will be affected by salinization, which is characterized by high electrical conductivity, reduced water potential, and excess ionic salts, posing a significant threat to agricultural productivity <span class="citation" data-cites="Hafez2022a Jia2023">(Hafez, Abdallah, et al. 2022; Jia et al. 2023)</span>. The excessive salinity and sodium in soil lead to soil swelling and dispersion, deterioration of soil structure, resulting in significant negative impacts on permeability coefficient, water infiltration, and porosity <span class="citation" data-cites="Ivushkin2019 Zahedifar2020">(Ivushkin et al. 2019; Zahedifar 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>While natural processes contribute to soil salinization, human-induced factors such as poor agricultural practices, insufficient drainage systems, and inaccurate irrigation water management have accelerated the formation of salt-affected soils. This increase in salinity and sodicity, coupled with population growth, threatens crop production and soil productivity globally. Therefore, reclaiming salt-affected soils while improving plant resistance to salinity and sodicity has become critical for sustainable agriculture and food security.</p>
<p>Various reclamation and management approaches have been developed and refined over the past decades, including the application of chemical and organic amendments, cultivation of salt-tolerant genotypes, appropriate agricultural water management, and bioremediation techniques <span class="citation" data-cites="Hafez2022b Gao2024 Youssef2024">(Hafez, Ge, et al. 2022; Gao et al. 2024; Youssef et al. 2024)</span>. Recent advances have focused on integrated approaches that combine multiple strategies to achieve synergistic effects in soil improvement and crop performance. This review synthesizes current knowledge on saline and sodic soil reclamation, emphasizing recent innovations, underlying mechanisms, and agronomic implications for sustainable agricultural production.</p>
</section>
<section id="characterization-and-classification-of-salt-affected-soils" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="characterization-and-classification-of-salt-affected-soils"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Characterization and classification of salt-affected soils</h2>
<section id="soil-salinity-and-sodicity-parameters" class="level3" data-number="2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="soil-salinity-and-sodicity-parameters"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Soil salinity and sodicity parameters</h3>
<p>Salt-affected soils are typically characterized using several key parameters. Electrical conductivity of the saturation extract (ECe) serves as the primary measure of soil salinity, with values greater than 4 dS/m indicating saline conditions. Sodicity is commonly assessed through exchangeable sodium percentage (ESP) or sodium adsorption ratio (SAR), with ESP values exceeding 15% indicative of sodic conditions. According to the US Salinity Laboratory classification system, soils are categorized as: (1) saline soils (ECe &gt; 4 dS/m, ESP &lt; 15%, pH &lt; 8.5), (2) sodic soils (ECe &lt; 4 dS/m, ESP &gt; 15%, pH &gt; 8.5), and (3) saline-sodic soils (ECe &gt; 4 dS/m, ESP &gt; 15%, pH &lt; 8.5) <span class="citation" data-cites="Foronda2022">(Foronda 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>The high salt content, pH value, and sodium concentration in salt-affected soils lead to multiple adverse effects. Excessive salinity results in osmotic stress, limiting water availability to plants despite adequate soil moisture. High sodium content causes clay dispersion and soil structure deterioration, significantly impacting permeability coefficient, water infiltration capacity, and soil porosity. This impedes soil water conductivity and air permeability while causing decomposition of soil structure, loss of organic matter, and nutrient deficiency, ultimately leading to reduced soil fertility <span class="citation" data-cites="Tian2023">(Tian et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="chemical-amendment-strategies" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chemical-amendment-strategies"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Chemical amendment strategies</h2>
<section id="gypsum-applications" class="level3" data-number="3.1">
<h3 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gypsum-applications"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Gypsum applications</h3>
<p>Gypsum (CaSO₄·2H₂O) remains the most recognized and widely applied chemical amendment for sodic and saline-sodic soil reclamation. The mechanism of gypsum application involves substituting Na⁺ from clay particles with Ca²⁺, thus promoting better soil structure while decreasing sodicity <span class="citation" data-cites="Yang2021 Elmeknassi2024">(Yang et al. 2021; Elmeknassi et al. 2024)</span>. The process delivers numerous advantages to soil physical properties and enhances the ratio of Ca²⁺ to Na⁺, providing sulphur needed for amino acid production and protein synthesis.</p>
<p>Recent field experiments have demonstrated the effectiveness of gypsum in reducing soil pH, ECe, and SAR while improving soil quality and boosting agricultural production. In saline-sodic soils from Egypt, application of phosphogypsum and standard gypsum based on gypsum requirement equations significantly reduced ESP from initial values of 29.8 to acceptable levels <span class="citation" data-cites="Kotb2000">(Kotb et al. 2000)</span>. The efficiency of gypsum reclamation varies with soil texture, with sandy clay loam soils responding more favorably than clay loam soils <span class="citation" data-cites="Murtaza2017">(Murtaza et al. 2017)</span>.</p>
<p>However, calcium input must be carefully controlled to avoid exceeding optimal amounts. Excessive gypsum application may lead to increased soil salinity and counterproductive results <span class="citation" data-cites="Mao2016">(Mao et al. 2016)</span>. Recent research has revealed that the traditional view of Na⁺ as harmful and Ca²⁺ as beneficial does not always apply in multi-cationic soil solutions. Initially, adding Ca²⁺ promotes Na⁺ leaching and reduces salinity, but excess Ca²⁺ becomes counterproductive. As Na⁺ leaches, the soil cation composition shifts from Ca²⁺ - Na⁺ - Mg²⁺ to Ca²⁺ - K⁺ - Mg²⁺, and Ca²⁺ function changes, potentially causing opposite effects.</p>
</section>
<section id="elemental-sulphur-and-other-chemical-amendments" class="level3" data-number="3.2">
<h3 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="elemental-sulphur-and-other-chemical-amendments"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> Elemental sulphur and other chemical amendments</h3>
<p>Elemental sulphur represents another effective chemical amendment for saline-sodic soil reclamation. When applied to soil, elemental sulphur undergoes microbial oxidation to produce sulphuric acid, which lowers soil pH and enhances the dissolution of native soil calcium carbonate. This released Ca²⁺ then replaces exchangeable Na⁺ on soil exchange sites. Recent studies by <span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2023">(Rezapour et al. 2023)</span> demonstrated that combined treatments of elemental sulphur with organic amendments achieved substantial improvements in soil health indices, with increases of 116% compared to control treatments.</p>
<p>Other chemical amendments investigated include aluminum sulfate, which also contributes to soil acidification and Na⁺ displacement. A study on calcareous sodic soils found that the combination of walnut-shell biochar with a mixture of gypsum and aluminum sulfate provided optimal results in reducing soil pH and SAR while enhancing soil EC and nutrient availability <span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2021">(Rezapour et al. 2021)</span>. Flue gas desulphurization gypsum, a by-product of industrial processes, has also shown promise in soil reclamation while addressing waste valorization in a circular economy approach <span class="citation" data-cites="Chen2015">(Chen et al. 2015)</span>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="organic-amendment-approaches" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="organic-amendment-approaches"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Organic amendment approaches</h2>
<section id="biochar-applications" class="level3" data-number="4.1">
<h3 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biochar-applications"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Biochar applications</h3>
<p>Biochar, a carbon-rich material produced through pyrolysis of organic waste, has emerged as a primary organic amendment under investigation for saline-sodic soil reclamation due to its numerous benefits including nutrient enrichment, improved availability, and non-destructive properties <span class="citation" data-cites="dosSantos2021 Hafez2021 Malik2023">(Santos et al. 2021; Hafez, Popov, and Rashad 2021; Malik, Mor, and Tokas 2023)</span>. The effectiveness of biochar in reclaiming salt-affected soils depends on its specific chemical and physical characteristics, which vary based on feedstock sources such as crop residues, wood, and manure materials.</p>
<p>According to <span class="citation" data-cites="Amini2017">(Amini et al. 2017)</span>, effective reclamation of salt-affected soils with biochar requires careful consideration of soil properties such as texture, nutrient content, and native carbon, as well as biochar characteristics including pH and feedstock source. In saline soils, biochar may increase or decrease EC depending on its nature, while enhancing soil organic carbon stocks and improving plant growth and yield. In saline-sodic soils, biochar can raise SOC, alter pH and SAR based on its properties, and improve water-holding capacity and hydraulic conductivity.</p>
<p>Recent field studies have demonstrated significant improvements with biochar application. In a study on saline-sodic soil from the High Valley of Cochabamba, Bolivia, biochar at 2% application rate effectively reduced ECe below 4 dS/m and contributed to ESP reduction, though cattle manure proved superior in overall soil reclamation <span class="citation" data-cites="Foronda2022">(Foronda 2022)</span>. The porous structure and extensive surface area of biochar provide favorable habitat and protection for soil microorganisms, while biochar can release dissolved organic matter into the surrounding environment, enhancing cation exchange capacity and hydrophilicity attributes, positively influencing soil organic carbon content and nutrient availability <span class="citation" data-cites="Song2023">(Song et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="vermicompost-and-humic-substances" class="level3" data-number="4.2">
<h3 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vermicompost-and-humic-substances"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Vermicompost and humic substances</h3>
<p>Vermicompost and humic substances represent valuable organic amendments that contribute to both chemical and biological improvement of saline-sodic soils. Vermicompost, produced through earthworm-mediated decomposition of organic materials, is rich in plant nutrients, beneficial microorganisms, and growth-promoting substances. Recent research has demonstrated remarkable synergistic effects when vermicompost is combined with chemical amendments for soil reclamation.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2023">(Rezapour et al. 2023)</span> investigated the synergistic impact of gypsum, elemental sulphur, vermicompost, biochar, and microbial inoculation on calcareous saline-sodic soils. The combined inoculated treatments of gypsum plus vermicompost and elemental sulphur plus vermicompost achieved substantial improvements in nonlinear soil health indices, with increases of 134% and 116% respectively compared to control. The overall soil health index ranged between 12% to 134% improvement across different treatments. Notably, microbial inoculation further enhanced the impact of treatments on soil health, and the derived soil health properties explained 29% to 87% of the variance in wheat growth.</p>
<p>Humic substances have been shown to stimulate root growth through indole acetic acid production, resulting in enhanced root surface area and enabling plants to access nutrients more effectively, thereby boosting yield. In quinoa cultivation experiments on saline-sodic soils, the combination of biochar, humic substances, and gypsum resulted in significant increases in root biomass of 206% and 176% in two different genotypes, while seed yield doubled in several treatments <span class="citation" data-cites="Alcivar2018">(Alcívar et al. 2018)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="cattle-manure-and-other-organic-materials" class="level3" data-number="4.3">
<h3 data-number="4.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cattle-manure-and-other-organic-materials"><span class="header-section-number">4.3</span> Cattle manure and other organic materials</h3>
<p>Cattle manure has demonstrated superior efficacy in reclaiming saline-sodic soils due to its contributions of organic matter, Ca²⁺, and Mg²⁺, which improve soil aggregation and leaching efficiency. In comparative studies, cattle manure at 2% application rate was most effective in reducing soil ESP from 66.6% to 27.6%, surpassing biochar and peat treatments <span class="citation" data-cites="Foronda2022">(Foronda 2022)</span>. All three amendments were efficient in lowering ECe below 4 dS/m, indicating their potential for reclaiming saline-sodic soils when combined with appropriate leaching practices.</p>
<p>The superiority of cattle manure can be explained by improvements in soil aggregation and leaching efficiency through its organic matter and divalent cation contributions. However, the choice of organic amendment should consider local availability, cost-effectiveness, and specific soil conditions. Rice straw, green waste compost, and biosolids have also shown promise in various reclamation scenarios, particularly when combined with chemical amendments and appropriate leaching regimes.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="combined-amendment-strategies-and-synergistic-effects" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="combined-amendment-strategies-and-synergistic-effects"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Combined amendment strategies and synergistic effects</h2>
<p>Recent research has increasingly focused on combined amendment strategies that leverage synergistic effects between chemical and organic materials. These integrated approaches have consistently demonstrated superior performance compared to single amendment applications, offering enhanced soil health improvement and crop productivity benefits.</p>
<p>In a comprehensive study on calcareous saline-sodic soils, Rezapour et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2023">(Rezapour et al. 2023)</span> developed both linear and nonlinear soil health quantification frameworks to assess the efficacy of remedial practices. Their findings revealed that combined inoculated chemical and organic treatments achieved remarkable soil health improvements. The gypsum plus vermicompost combination increased the nonlinear soil health index by 134% (from 0.29 to 0.68), while elemental sulphur plus vermicompost improved it by 116% (from 0.29 to 0.62). These combined approaches significantly outperformed individual amendments, which showed improvements ranging from 12% to 134%.</p>
<p>The mechanisms underlying synergistic effects involve multiple pathways. Chemical amendments primarily address sodium displacement through cation exchange, while organic amendments enhance soil structure, water retention, and microbial activity. When combined, chemical amendments facilitate rapid Na⁺ removal while organic materials improve the physical matrix for sustainable soil health. Furthermore, organic amendments can enhance the dissolution and effectiveness of chemical amendments through pH modification and increased microbial activity.</p>
<p>In quinoa performance studies, the triple combination of biochar, humic substances, and gypsum resulted in the highest increases in root biomass for both tested genotypes (206% and 176%), while electrical conductivity, sodium adsorption ratio, and exchangeable sodium percentage decreased significantly in all treated soils <span class="citation" data-cites="Alcivar2018">(Alcívar et al. 2018)</span>. The ESP decreased 11-fold with gypsum treatment alone and 9-13-fold with combined treatments involving biochar, demonstrating the enhanced effectiveness of integrated approaches.</p>
</section>
<section id="microbial-interventions-and-bioremediation" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microbial-interventions-and-bioremediation"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Microbial interventions and bioremediation</h2>
<section id="microbial-inoculation-for-soil-health" class="level3" data-number="6.1">
<h3 data-number="6.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microbial-inoculation-for-soil-health"><span class="header-section-number">6.1</span> Microbial inoculation for soil health</h3>
<p>Microbial inoculation represents a promising biological approach to enhance saline-sodic soil reclamation. Salt-tolerant microorganisms can contribute to soil improvement through multiple mechanisms including bioaccumulation of salt ions, production of exopolysaccharides that improve soil structure, secretion of growth-promoting substances, and enhancement of nutrient cycling processes.</p>
<p>Under salt stress, halophilic microbes can absorb salt ions through bioaccumulation processes <span class="citation" data-cites="Zhang2023">(Zhang et al. 2023)</span>. According to Xing et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Xing2024">(Xing et al. 2024)</span>, the application of inoculated microbes can decrease Na⁺ ions in soil by stimulating the abundance of microorganisms harboring Na⁺/H⁺ transport proteins, Na⁺/Ca²⁺ transport proteins, and Na⁺/K⁺ transport proteins. This microbially-mediated ion exchange contributes significantly to salinity reduction.</p>
<p>Research on combined chemical and organic amendments with microbial inoculation has revealed substantial enhancements in treatment efficacy. Rezapour et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2023">(Rezapour et al. 2023)</span> found that microbial inoculation further enhanced the impact of chemical and organic treatments on soil health, with soil health properties explaining 29% to 87% of variance in wheat growth. The study found negative correlations between sodium-containing soil and microbial biomass carbon, indicating that salt-affected soils reduce microbial activity and biomass, which can be ameliorated through appropriate amendment strategies.</p>
</section>
<section id="plant-microbe-interactions-in-saline-conditions" class="level3" data-number="6.2">
<h3 data-number="6.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plant-microbe-interactions-in-saline-conditions"><span class="header-section-number">6.2</span> Plant-microbe interactions in saline conditions</h3>
<p>Plant-microbe relationships, particularly with synergistic bacteria and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF), have been recommended as potential solutions to mitigate salinity and sodicity stress in both halophytes and glycophytes. Nitrogen-fixing bacteria collections can increase salt and sodicity tolerance by creating specific enzymes and hormones, fixing atmospheric N₂, and converting water-insoluble phosphates to bioavailable forms.</p>
<p>Recent research on microbial network-driven remediation has revealed that salt-tolerant plants enrich beneficial bacteria in soil by releasing organic acids and enzymes that promote plant growth under saline stress <span class="citation" data-cites="Zahra2024">(Zahra et al. 2024)</span>. Jerusalem artichoke, for instance, enhances microbial diversity in saline-alkali soils through root exudates <span class="citation" data-cites="Shao2019">(Shao et al. 2019)</span>. Different salt-tolerant plant species release varying organic compounds, which attract beneficial rhizosphere bacteria under saline stress, thereby aiding host plants in mitigating salt-induced damage <span class="citation" data-cites="Xiong2020">(Xiong et al. 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>Network analysis has provided insights into the role of keystone taxa in saline soil remediation. These taxa, serving as central components of the core microbiome, play critical roles in facilitating plant-soil interactions and enhancing soil improvement <span class="citation" data-cites="Trivedi2020 Liu2023mSystems">(Trivedi et al. 2020; Liu et al. 2023)</span>. Partial least squares path modeling has shown that soil quality improvements are primarily driven by shifts in bacterial composition, offering a novel mechanistic framework for understanding microbial contributions to soil restoration.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="phytoremediation-using-salt-tolerant-plants" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="phytoremediation-using-salt-tolerant-plants"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Phytoremediation using salt-tolerant plants</h2>
<section id="mechanisms-and-principles-of-halophyte-based-phytoremediation" class="level3" data-number="7.1">
<h3 data-number="7.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mechanisms-and-principles-of-halophyte-based-phytoremediation"><span class="header-section-number">7.1</span> Mechanisms and principles of halophyte-based phytoremediation</h3>
<p>Phytoremediation using salt-tolerant plants (halophytes) has emerged as a sustainable and effective approach for reclaiming saline-sodic soils. Halophytes, representing approximately 1% of world flora, can survive, grow, and reproduce at salt concentrations exceeding 20 dS/m. These plants possess unique anatomical and morphological features including succulence, osmotic adjustment, ion compartmentalization, selective uptake and transport mechanisms, enhanced antioxidant systems, and salt inclusion or discharge capabilities <span class="citation" data-cites="Flowers2008">(Flowers and Colmer 2008)</span>.</p>
<p>Halophytes are classified into three main groups based on salt tolerance mechanisms: (1) Excluders, which possess root ultra-filtration mechanisms preventing salt uptake; (2) Accumulators, which sequester salts in vacuoles within above-ground biomass; and (3) Excretors (recretohalophytes), which possess specialized salt glands allowing accumulated salt to be excreted onto leaf surfaces and dispersed via wind through haloconduction processes. The potential of halophytic plants to accumulate enormous salt quantities depends primarily on the capacity of their above-ground biomass, with hyperaccumulating plants showing particular promise.</p>
<p>During phytoremediation, CO₂ released by plant roots during respiration produces H₂CO₃, which increases solubility of CaCO₃ in deeper soil layers. This process releases Ca²⁺, which replaces Na⁺ and other salts from soil exchange sites, thereby reducing sodicity <span class="citation" data-cites="Robbins1986">(Robbins 1986)</span>. Comparative studies have shown that phytoremediation can reduce sodicity by 52% compared to 62% reduction using gypsum, demonstrating its effectiveness as an alternative or complementary approach to chemical amendments <span class="citation" data-cites="Qadir2007">(Qadir and Oster 2007)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="effective-halophyte-species-for-soil-reclamation" class="level3" data-number="7.2">
<h3 data-number="7.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effective-halophyte-species-for-soil-reclamation"><span class="header-section-number">7.2</span> Effective halophyte species for soil reclamation</h3>
<p>Numerous halophyte species have been evaluated for their phytoremediation potential. In studies from the bed of Urmia Lake, Iran, <em>Salicornia europaea</em> and <em>Halocnemum strobilaceum</em> proved most effective in salinity-remediation, achieving significant reductions in electrical conductivity and exchangeable sodium percentage <span class="citation" data-cites="Ghorbanpour2022">(Ghorbanpour et al. 2022)</span>. These species demonstrated high concentrations of Fe²⁺ (511.85 mg/kg), Zn²⁺ (99.97 mg/kg), and Na⁺ (25.65 mg/kg) in shoots, with maximum dry matter (38%), protein (16%), and oil percentage (3.5%) found in Salicornia.</p>
<p>Research on <em>Haloxylon recurvum</em>, <em>Suaeda nudiflora</em>, and <em>Salsola baryosma</em> demonstrated sodium removal capacities of 17, 15.6, and 9 g per plant respectively during three-month growth periods. <em>Pennisetum giganteum</em> has emerged as a promising salt-accumulating and salt-tolerant non-conventional crop for sustainable saline agriculture and simultaneous phytoremediation <span class="citation" data-cites="Hayat2020">(Hayat et al. 2020)</span>. This species effectively reduces soil salinity by 30% within 30 days when grown in saline soil, and when co-cultivated with barley, wheat, and tomato, it reduces negative salt effects on sensitive crops.</p>
<p>Salt-tolerant legumes such as Glycine soja and Sesbania cannabina have successfully rehabilitated saline soils by reducing soil electrical conductivity and accumulating carbon and nitrogen, while enriching microbial communities at different soil depths <span class="citation" data-cites="Zheng2023">(Zheng et al. 2023)</span>. Atriplex species, particularly Atriplex halimus and Atriplex hortensis, have shown considerable promise for reclamation while providing economic benefits as forage crops. Recent field studies confirmed that Atriplex hortensis maintains relatively stable water potential and high relative water content under saline stress, indicating physiological resilience suitable for salt-affected agroecosystems.</p>
</section>
<section id="microbial-network-driven-phytoremediation" class="level3" data-number="7.3">
<h3 data-number="7.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microbial-network-driven-phytoremediation"><span class="header-section-number">7.3</span> Microbial network-driven phytoremediation</h3>
<p>Recent advances in network analysis have revealed the critical role of microbial communities in halophyte-mediated soil reclamation. Salt-tolerant plants enhance the complexity of both bacterial and fungal networks in rhizosphere soils. Network analysis showed that planting salt-tolerant plants increases the number of nodes, average path length, and modularity of fungal communities, indicating enhanced network complexity <span class="citation" data-cites="Liu2023mSystems">(Liu et al. 2023)</span>. The presence of generalists (connectors and module hubs) in saline-alkali soils under phytoremediation supports improved stability and efficiency of fungal communities.</p>
<p>Keystone taxa, identified through within-module connectivity and among-module connectivity analysis, play significant impacts on soil enzyme activity and nutrient cycling <span class="citation" data-cites="Wen2024">(Wen et al. 2024)</span>. Phytoremediation has been shown to strengthen cooperative interactions among fungi while diminishing competitive dynamics, as evidenced by higher ratios of positive correlations within fungal networks following salt-tolerant plant establishment. Salt-tolerant plants increase rhizosphere ecosystem multifunctionality by reducing soil salinity, with planting halophytes enriching microbial diversity and network complexity <span class="citation" data-cites="Hu2024">(Hu et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="emerging-technologies-in-soil-reclamation" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="emerging-technologies-in-soil-reclamation"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Emerging technologies in soil reclamation</h2>
<section id="nanotechnology-applications" class="level3" data-number="8.1">
<h3 data-number="8.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nanotechnology-applications"><span class="header-section-number">8.1</span> Nanotechnology applications</h3>
<p>Nanotechnology represents an emerging frontier in saline-sodic soil reclamation, offering innovative solutions through the unique properties of nanomaterials. Nanoparticles have demonstrated promising results in alleviating salt stress, improving soil properties, and enhancing plant performance in salt-affected soils. The application of zinc oxide nanoparticles combined with soil amendments has been shown to improve wheat yield, physiological attributes, and soil properties in saline-sodic soils <span class="citation" data-cites="ElSharkawy2022">(El-Sharkawy et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>Different types of nanoparticles exhibit varied mechanisms of action in salt stress mitigation. Magnesium oxide nanoparticles alleviate stress by modulating photosynthetic function, nutrient uptake, and antioxidant potential. Silicon nanoparticle-based biochar has demonstrated effectiveness in improving wheat growth, enhancing antioxidant systems, and optimizing nutrient concentrations under salinity stress <span class="citation" data-cites="Gill2024">(Gill et al. 2024)</span>. Biosynthesized zinc oxide nanoparticles have been shown to modulate phytoremediation potential and influence rhizocompartment-associated microbial community structure <span class="citation" data-cites="Li2024ZnONP">(Li et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Recent research by Ahmed et al. <span class="citation" data-cites="Ahmed2023">(Ahmed et al. 2023)</span> demonstrated differential responses of nano zinc sulfate compared to conventional zinc sources in mitigating salinity stress in rice grown on saline-sodic soil. The study revealed that nano-formulations enhanced zinc bioavailability and uptake efficiency, leading to improved plant growth and stress tolerance. Nanomaterials also show promise in enhancing the efficiency of phytoremediation through improved nutrient delivery and stress mitigation mechanisms.</p>
<p>However, the application of nanotechnology in soil management faces several challenges. Concerns about potential ecotoxicity, environmental persistence, and long-term impacts on soil biota require careful evaluation. The development of smart nanomaterials with surface functionality or coatings that resist suppression by biomacromolecules and tolerate climate and environmental triggers remains a formidable challenge. Nevertheless, nanotechnology holds significant potential for improving soil quality through innovative approaches including nano-fertilizers, nano-enabled remediation strategies, and enhanced delivery systems.</p>
</section>
<section id="advanced-genetic-and-biotechnological-approaches" class="level3" data-number="8.2">
<h3 data-number="8.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="advanced-genetic-and-biotechnological-approaches"><span class="header-section-number">8.2</span> Advanced genetic and biotechnological approaches</h3>
<p>Advanced plant breeding and biotechnological approaches offer promising avenues for developing salt-tolerant crop varieties. Recent identification of the Alkali Tolerance 1 locus in sorghum, which regulates aquaporin phosphorylation for hydrogen peroxide transport to alleviate oxidative stress, represents a significant breakthrough. The loss-of-function of this gene in sorghum, millet, rice, and maize improves field performance in sodic land <span class="citation" data-cites="Wang2024SaltTolerance">(Wang et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Novel biotechnologies including CRISPR/Cas gene editing, marker-assisted breeding, and double haploid production hold great potential to accelerate breeding processes and cultivate crops with enhanced salt tolerance. However, certain limitations remain, including advanced technology dependence, lengthy processes, unexpected genetic gains, and complex genotype-environment correlations. Despite considerable progress in understanding salinity tolerance mechanisms, obstacles remain in transferring molecular knowledge into practical plant breeding activities.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="mechanisms-of-soil-improvement-and-restoration" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mechanisms-of-soil-improvement-and-restoration"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> Mechanisms of soil improvement and restoration</h2>
<section id="physical-and-chemical-transformation-processes" class="level3" data-number="9.1">
<h3 data-number="9.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="physical-and-chemical-transformation-processes"><span class="header-section-number">9.1</span> Physical and chemical transformation processes</h3>
<p>The reclamation of saline-sodic soils involves complex physical and chemical transformation processes. Chemical amendments primarily work through cation exchange mechanisms, where Ca²⁺ from gypsum or other calcium sources replaces Na⁺ on soil exchange sites. This displacement is significantly influenced by soil cation exchange capacity and water movement within the soil profile. The process of reclamation is further influenced by soil texture, with ion replacement occurring more readily in coarser-textured soils <span class="citation" data-cites="Ahmad2016">(Ahmad et al. 2016)</span>.</p>
<p>Organic amendments enhance physical properties through multiple mechanisms. Biochar increases soil porosity and water retention capacity while providing surfaces for microbial colonization. The porous structure creates favorable microhabitats that protect microorganisms from environmental stresses. Furthermore, biochar releases dissolved organic matter that enhances cation exchange capacity and influences soil pH, thereby affecting nutrient availability and microbial activity <span class="citation" data-cites="Li2022Biochar">(Li et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>The presence of CaSO₄ contributes to decreasing water-soluble Na⁺ content through both chemical replacement and enhanced leaching. Recent studies showed that proper amendment application resulted in reduced soil ESP and pH by 14.64% and 7.42% respectively. The dissolution of native soil carbonates, enhanced by increased CO₂ partial pressure from organic amendment decomposition, further contributes to Ca²⁺ availability for Na⁺ exchange.</p>
</section>
<section id="microbial-mediated-carbon-and-nitrogen-cycles" class="level3" data-number="9.2">
<h3 data-number="9.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microbial-mediated-carbon-and-nitrogen-cycles"><span class="header-section-number">9.2</span> Microbial-mediated carbon and nitrogen cycles</h3>
<p>Microbial communities play crucial roles in carbon and nitrogen cycling within reclaimed soils. The carbon cycle represents a fundamental biogeochemical process regulating soil material dynamics and gas exchange between soil and atmosphere <span class="citation" data-cites="Meloni2003">(Meloni et al. 2003)</span>. Microbes can decrease salt ion concentrations through bioaccumulation and can utilize CO₃²⁻ or HCO₃⁻ as carbon sources, contributing to salinity reduction <span class="citation" data-cites="Zhao2021">(Zhao and Tian 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>Phytoremediation using salt-tolerant plants significantly alters soil microbial composition. The relative abundance of Acidobacteria, which decompose plant residues and enhance soil carbon cycling, increases following phytoremediation, suggesting effective pH reduction and improved saline-alkali conditions. Proteobacteria, including various nitrogen-fixing bacteria, remain dominant and play vital roles in nitrogen cycling processes <span class="citation" data-cites="Kim2021 Jiang2024">(Kim et al. 2021; Jiang et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Network analysis reveals that soil microbes tend to cooperate more than compete under nutrient-limiting conditions, often establishing symbiotic relationships to obtain essential nutrients and mitigate salt stress. The strengthening of cooperative interactions among microbial communities following amendment application contributes to enhanced ecosystem stability and improved nutrient cycling efficiency.</p>
</section>
<section id="soil-enzyme-activities-and-nutrient-dynamics" class="level3" data-number="9.3">
<h3 data-number="9.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="soil-enzyme-activities-and-nutrient-dynamics"><span class="header-section-number">9.3</span> Soil enzyme activities and nutrient dynamics</h3>
<p>Soil enzyme activities serve as sensitive indicators of soil health and recovery following reclamation efforts. The combination of chemical and organic amendments significantly enhances activities of key enzymes including urease and phosphatase. These enzymes exert positive influences on soil organic matter content by facilitating transformation and cycling of nitrogen and phosphorus. Urease increases soil nitrogen content by promoting nitrogen transformation, while phosphatase enhances phosphorus availability, jointly contributing to organic matter formation and accumulation.</p>
<p>Amendment applications significantly improve nutrient availability in reclaimed soils. Organic and combined approaches significantly increase available phosphorus and potassium, as well as bioavailable iron, manganese, and zinc concentrations. These improvements in nutritional quality directly correlate with enhanced crop growth and productivity. Studies have shown that amendments can increase soil organic matter content substantially, with combined treatments of gypsum and organic materials demonstrating synergistic effects on both enzyme activities and nutrient availability.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="agronomic-implications-and-crop-performance" class="level2" data-number="10">
<h2 data-number="10" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="agronomic-implications-and-crop-performance"><span class="header-section-number">10</span> Agronomic implications and crop performance</h2>
<section id="crop-yield-and-quality-improvements" class="level3" data-number="10.1">
<h3 data-number="10.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="crop-yield-and-quality-improvements"><span class="header-section-number">10.1</span> Crop yield and quality improvements</h3>
<p>Effective reclamation of saline-sodic soils translates directly into improved crop performance and productivity. Recent field studies have demonstrated substantial yield improvements following integrated amendment strategies. In wheat cultivation on reclaimed saline-sodic soils, derived soil health indices explained 29% to 87% of variance in wheat growth, demonstrating strong linkages between soil improvement and crop performance <span class="citation" data-cites="Rezapour2023">(Rezapour et al. 2023)</span>. The combined application of gypsum and organic amendments significantly increased wheat biomass accumulation and grain yields.</p>
<p>Quinoa cultivation studies have revealed significant improvements in both yield and quality parameters following amendment applications. Seed yield doubled in treatments involving gypsum and humic substances, while all amended soils showed significant increases in stomatal conductance and SPAD index compared to controls <span class="citation" data-cites="Alcivar2018">(Alcívar et al. 2018)</span>. Seed protein content was positively affected by biochar and humic substance applications, indicating improvements not only in quantity but also in nutritional quality.</p>
<p>The increase in crop biomass primarily depends on photosynthetic function enhancement. Applications of gypsum and organic amendments significantly boost net photosynthetic rates, with improvements of 50.7%, 25.3%, and 143.6% observed at different growth stages in maize cultivation. These photosynthetic enhancements directly correlate with dry matter accumulation and final yields, attributed to improved soil properties including lower pH, higher nutrient content, and enhanced organic matter <span class="citation" data-cites="Wang2024SaltTolerance">(Wang et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="root-development-and-plant-physiology" class="level3" data-number="10.2">
<h3 data-number="10.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="root-development-and-plant-physiology"><span class="header-section-number">10.2</span> Root development and plant physiology</h3>
<p>Root system development represents a critical factor in plant adaptation to saline-sodic conditions and response to soil reclamation efforts. Combined amendments significantly enhance root biomass, with increases of 206% and 176% reported in quinoa genotypes treated with biochar, humic substances, and gypsum <span class="citation" data-cites="Alcivar2018">(Alcívar et al. 2018)</span>. Enhanced root development provides plants with greater access to water and nutrients, improving overall stress tolerance and productivity.</p>
<p>Plant physiological responses to reclamation include maintenance of water relations, enhanced photosynthetic capacity, and improved ion homeostasis. Halophytes maintain relatively stable water potential and high relative water content under saline stress, indicating efficient osmotic adjustment and sustained cellular hydration. These physiological adaptations, combined with improved soil conditions from amendments, enable sustained growth and productivity under saline conditions.</p>
</section>
<section id="economic-viability-and-sustainability" class="level3" data-number="10.3">
<h3 data-number="10.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="economic-viability-and-sustainability"><span class="header-section-number">10.3</span> Economic viability and sustainability</h3>
<p>The economic viability of reclamation strategies represents a critical consideration for adoption by farmers. While chemical amendments like gypsum have historically been cost-effective, increases in industrial demand and reductions in government subsidies have made amendment costs prohibitive in several developing countries. This economic reality has driven interest toward biological approaches including phytoremediation and microbial interventions, which offer lower-cost alternatives with additional environmental benefits.</p>
<p>Phytoremediation using halophytes offers multiple economic advantages. Beyond soil improvement, many halophyte species provide valuable products including forage, biofuel feedstock, essential oils, and food crops. <em>Salicornia bigelovii</em>, for instance, represents a potential oilseed crop for coastal and saline lands. The integration of salt-tolerant forage species into livestock production systems can enhance ecosystem resilience while generating income during the reclamation period.</p>
<p>Sustainable reclamation approaches emphasize waste valorization in circular economy frameworks. The use of biosolids, green waste compost, rice straw, and industrial by-products like flue gas desulphurization gypsum transforms waste materials into valuable soil amendments. This approach reduces disposal costs while providing affordable amendment options for farmers. However, comprehensive life-cycle assessments considering energy inputs, transportation costs, and long-term maintenance requirements remain necessary for informed decision-making.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="challenges-and-limitations" class="level2" data-number="11">
<h2 data-number="11" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-and-limitations"><span class="header-section-number">11</span> Challenges and limitations</h2>
<section id="technical-and-practical-constraints" class="level3" data-number="11.1">
<h3 data-number="11.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="technical-and-practical-constraints"><span class="header-section-number">11.1</span> Technical and practical constraints</h3>
<p>Despite significant advances, several technical and practical constraints limit widespread implementation of soil reclamation strategies. The efficiency of amendments varies considerably with soil texture, salinity levels, and sodicity conditions, requiring site-specific optimization. The relationship between amendment rates and soil response is not always linear, with excessive applications potentially causing counterproductive results. For instance, excessive gypsum can increase soil salinity, while improper organic matter addition may temporarily decrease oxygen availability during decomposition.</p>
<p>Water availability represents a critical limitation for many reclamation approaches. Both chemical leaching and phytoremediation require adequate water supplies, which may be limited in arid regions where saline soils predominate. The quality of irrigation water also significantly affects reclamation outcomes, with moderately saline water potentially suitable for leaching when combined with appropriate amendments, but requiring careful management to prevent secondary salinization.</p>
<p>Time requirements for effective reclamation vary widely among approaches. Chemical amendments combined with leaching can achieve rapid initial improvements, while biological approaches including phytoremediation and microbial interventions typically require multiple growing seasons for substantial effects. This temporal aspect affects economic feasibility and farmer adoption, particularly where immediate productivity improvements are necessary for farm viability.</p>
</section>
<section id="knowledge-gaps-and-research-needs" class="level3" data-number="11.2">
<h3 data-number="11.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="knowledge-gaps-and-research-needs"><span class="header-section-number">11.2</span> Knowledge gaps and research needs</h3>
<p>Several critical knowledge gaps require addressing for advancing saline-sodic soil reclamation. The long-term sustainability of various reclamation approaches remains incompletely understood, particularly regarding maintenance requirements and potential for re-salinization. While short-term studies demonstrate effectiveness, multi-decadal assessments of soil quality, productivity, and ecosystem functioning are scarce.</p>
<p>The interactions between different amendment types, rates, and timing require systematic investigation across diverse soil types and climatic conditions. Current understanding of optimal amendment combinations derives primarily from controlled experiments and limited field trials. Scaling these findings to farm-level implementation under variable environmental conditions necessitates additional research. Furthermore, the role of climate variability and extreme weather events on reclamation outcomes requires attention given accelerating climate change.</p>
<p>Microbial community dynamics during reclamation remain incompletely characterized. While recent network analysis has revealed the importance of keystone taxa and cooperative interactions, predictive frameworks for managing microbial communities toward desired outcomes are lacking. The stability and resilience of engineered microbial communities under field conditions, particularly during stress periods, requires investigation. Additionally, the potential for developing designer microbial consortia optimized for specific soil conditions represents an emerging research frontier.</p>
</section>
<section id="environmental-and-ecological-considerations" class="level3" data-number="11.3">
<h3 data-number="11.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="environmental-and-ecological-considerations"><span class="header-section-number">11.3</span> Environmental and ecological considerations</h3>
<p>Environmental impacts of reclamation practices require careful consideration. While improving soil quality, amendment applications may have unintended consequences. Excess nutrient leaching from organic amendments could contribute to groundwater contamination or eutrophication of adjacent water bodies. The carbon footprint associated with amendment production, transportation, and application should be evaluated within comprehensive sustainability frameworks.</p>
<p>Nanotechnology applications, while promising, raise concerns about environmental persistence and ecotoxicity. The fate and transport of engineered nanoparticles in soil ecosystems, their interactions with soil biota, and potential accumulation in food chains require thorough investigation before widespread implementation. Regulatory frameworks for nanomaterial use in agriculture remain under development, reflecting ongoing uncertainty regarding risk assessment and management.</p>
<p>Biodiversity impacts of reclamation efforts deserve attention. While improving conditions for agricultural production, intensive reclamation may affect native halophytic vegetation and associated fauna. Balancing agricultural productivity with ecosystem conservation requires landscape-level planning that maintains habitat corridors and preserves representative areas of natural saline ecosystems. The role of reclaimed lands in regional hydrology and their effects on groundwater recharge and quality warrant consideration in integrated watershed management.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="future-perspectives-and-research-directions" class="level2" data-number="12">
<h2 data-number="12" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-perspectives-and-research-directions"><span class="header-section-number">12</span> Future perspectives and research directions</h2>
<section id="integrated-management-strategies" class="level3" data-number="12.1">
<h3 data-number="12.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="integrated-management-strategies"><span class="header-section-number">12.1</span> Integrated management strategies</h3>
<p>The future of saline-sodic soil reclamation lies in integrated management strategies that combine traditional practices with innovative technologies. Comprehensive management approaches should integrate physical methods (drainage, tillage), chemical amendments, organic materials, biological interventions, and genetic improvements in crop salt tolerance. These integrated systems must be tailored to local conditions, considering soil properties, climate, water availability, crop preferences, and economic constraints.</p>
<p>Precision agriculture technologies offer opportunities for optimizing amendment applications and monitoring reclamation progress. Remote sensing, soil sensors, and geographic information systems enable site-specific management at field scales, improving efficiency and reducing costs. Digital agriculture platforms integrating real-time data with predictive models could guide adaptive management decisions, adjusting strategies based on response monitoring and changing conditions.</p>
</section>
<section id="climate-change-adaptation-and-mitigation" class="level3" data-number="12.2">
<h3 data-number="12.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="climate-change-adaptation-and-mitigation"><span class="header-section-number">12.2</span> Climate change adaptation and mitigation</h3>
<p>Climate change will likely exacerbate salinization problems through altered precipitation patterns, increased evapotranspiration, and sea-level rise affecting coastal areas. Reclamation strategies must account for these changing conditions, emphasizing approaches that enhance soil resilience and adaptive capacity. Halophyte-based systems may play increasingly important roles, providing both reclamation and climate adaptation benefits while supporting biodiversity conservation.</p>
<p>Carbon sequestration potential of reclamation practices deserves greater emphasis. Biochar applications and establishment of perennial halophyte vegetation can contribute significantly to soil carbon stocks while improving soil quality. Quantifying these carbon benefits within climate mitigation frameworks could provide additional economic incentives for reclamation through carbon credit markets. Life-cycle assessments incorporating greenhouse gas emissions and carbon sequestration across different reclamation approaches would inform climate-smart land management decisions.</p>
</section>
<section id="biotechnology-and-genetic-engineering" class="level3" data-number="12.3">
<h3 data-number="12.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biotechnology-and-genetic-engineering"><span class="header-section-number">12.3</span> Biotechnology and genetic engineering</h3>
<p>Advances in plant biotechnology offer promising avenues for developing superior salt-tolerant crop varieties. CRISPR/Cas9 gene editing enables precise modifications of salt tolerance genes, potentially accelerating development of crops suitable for saline conditions. Understanding complex regulatory networks controlling salt tolerance responses will facilitate multi-gene engineering approaches addressing various aspects of salt stress simultaneously.</p>
<p>Synthetic biology approaches could enable design of microbial consortia optimized for saline soil improvement. Engineering microorganisms with enhanced salt tolerance, exopolysaccharide production, or nutrient cycling capabilities could improve bioremediation efficiency. However, careful risk assessment and regulatory oversight are essential for environmental release of genetically modified organisms.</p>
</section>
<section id="policy-and-institutional-frameworks" class="level3" data-number="12.4">
<h3 data-number="12.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="policy-and-institutional-frameworks"><span class="header-section-number">12.4</span> Policy and institutional frameworks</h3>
<p>Effective policy and institutional frameworks are crucial for widespread implementation of soil reclamation strategies. Government policies should provide incentives for sustainable land management, including subsidies for amendments, technical assistance programs, and research support. Land tenure security encourages long-term investments in soil improvement. Collaborative approaches involving researchers, extension services, farmers, and policymakers facilitate knowledge transfer and adaptive management.</p>
<p>International cooperation is essential given the global scale of salinization problems. Sharing best practices, technologies, and genetic resources across countries accelerates progress. Investment in agricultural research and development focused on salt-affected soils must increase, particularly in developing countries where impacts are most severe. Capacity building programs training farmers and extension workers in reclamation techniques ensure practical implementation of research advances.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2" data-number="13">
<h2 data-number="13" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">13</span> Conclusion</h2>
<p>Saline and sodic soil reclamation represents a critical challenge and opportunity for global agriculture. Recent advances have demonstrated the effectiveness of diverse strategies ranging from traditional chemical amendments to innovative biological and nanotechnological approaches. Combined amendment strategies incorporating both chemical and organic materials have consistently shown superior performance, achieving soil health improvements exceeding 130% in recent studies. The synergistic effects between different amendment types provide enhanced benefits for soil properties, microbial communities, and crop productivity.</p>
<p>Phytoremediation using halophytes has emerged as a sustainable and cost-effective approach, offering multiple benefits including salt removal, soil structure improvement, and potential economic returns from halophyte products. Recent research has revealed the importance of plant-microbe interactions in successful reclamation, with microbial network analysis providing insights into keystone taxa and cooperative relationships that enhance soil recovery. These biological approaches complement chemical amendments, providing long-term sustainability and ecosystem service benefits.</p>
<p>Emerging technologies including nanotechnology and advanced biotechnology show promise for addressing specific constraints in salt-affected soils. However, careful evaluation of environmental safety, economic feasibility, and long-term sustainability remains necessary before widespread implementation. Future research should focus on integrated management strategies tailored to local conditions, incorporating precision agriculture technologies for optimized resource use.</p>
<p>The agronomic implications of soil reclamation are substantial, with successful strategies demonstrating significant improvements in crop yields, quality, and resource use efficiency. However, challenges remain including water availability constraints, time requirements for biological approaches, and knowledge gaps regarding long-term sustainability. Addressing these challenges requires continued research investment, improved policy frameworks, and international cooperation.</p>
<p>Looking forward, comprehensive management approaches integrating traditional knowledge with innovative technologies offer the greatest potential for sustainable reclamation of salt-affected soils. Given projections that nearly half of global arable land will be affected by salinization by 2050, accelerating development and implementation of effective reclamation strategies is imperative for food security and environmental sustainability. Success will require collaborative efforts across disciplines, sectors, and nations to develop and deploy solutions appropriate for diverse agroecological contexts worldwide.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<!-- References will be rendered here -->
<div id="ref-Ahmad2016" class="csl-entry">
Ahmad, S., A. Ghafoor, M. Akhtar, and M. Khan. 2016. <span>“Implication of Gypsum Rates to Optimize Hydraulic Conductivity for Variable-Texture Saline-Sodic Soils Reclamation.”</span> <em>Land Degradation &amp; Development</em> 27 (3): 550–60. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.2298">https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.2298</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ahmed2023" class="csl-entry">
Ahmed, R., M. Zia-ur-Rehman, M. Sabir, M. Usman, M. Rizwan, Z. Ahmad, and A. A. Bamagoos. 2023. <span>“Differential Response of Nano Zinc Sulphate with Other Conventional Sources of Zn in Mitigating Salinity Stress in Rice Grown on Saline-Sodic Soil.”</span> <em>Chemosphere</em> 327: 138479. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138479">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138479</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Alcivar2018" class="csl-entry">
Alcívar, M., A. Zurita-Silva, M. Sandoval, C. Muñoz, and M. Schoebitz. 2018. <span>“Reclamation of Saline-Sodic Soils with Combined Amendments: Impact on Quinoa Performance and Biological Soil Quality.”</span> <em>Sustainability</em> 10 (9): 3083. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/su10093083">https://doi.org/10.3390/su10093083</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Amini2017" class="csl-entry">
Amini, S., H. Ghadiri, C. Chen, and P. Marschner. 2017. <span>“Salt-Affected Soils, Reclamation, Carbon Dynamics, and Biochar: A Review.”</span> <em>Journal of Soils and Sediments</em> 17 (3): 939–53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11368-016-1593-2">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11368-016-1593-2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Chen2015" class="csl-entry">
Chen, Q., W. Shi, X. Wang, L. Zhang, Z. Liu, and X. Zhan. 2015. <span>“Influence of Flue Gas Desulfurization Gypsum Amendments on Heavy Metal Distribution in Reclaimed Sodic Soils.”</span> <em>Environmental Engineering Science</em> 32 (6): 470–78. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1089/ees.2014.0462">https://doi.org/10.1089/ees.2014.0462</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Elmeknassi2024" class="csl-entry">
Elmeknassi, M., R. El Moustaine, H. El Khalil, A. Elgamouz, and M. Benaissa. 2024. <span>“<a href="">A Review on the Application of Sustainable Organic Amendments for Soil Reclamation and Plant Growth</a>.”</span> <em>Journal of Plant Growth Regulation</em> 43: 1–20.
</div>
<div id="ref-ElSharkawy2022" class="csl-entry">
El-Sharkawy, M., E. Mahmoud, M. Abd El-Aziz, and T. Khalifa. 2022. <span>“Effect of Zinc Oxide Nanoparticles and Soil Amendments on Wheat Yield, Physiological Attributes, and Soil Properties Grown in Saline-Sodic Soil.”</span> <em>Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis</em> 53 (17): 2170–86. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00103624.2022.2090862">https://doi.org/10.1080/00103624.2022.2090862</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Flowers2008" class="csl-entry">
Flowers, T. J., and T. D. Colmer. 2008. <span>“Salinity Tolerance in Halophytes.”</span> <em>New Phytologist</em> 179 (4): 945–63. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02531.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2008.02531.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Foronda2022" class="csl-entry">
Foronda, D. A. 2022. <span>“Reclamation of a Saline-Sodic Soil with Organic Amendments and Leaching.”</span> <em>Environmental Sciences Proceedings</em> 16 (1): 56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/environsciproc2022016056">https://doi.org/10.3390/environsciproc2022016056</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Gao2024" class="csl-entry">
Gao, Y., Y. Li, J. Zhang, W. Liu, Z. Dang, W. Ye, and Y. Cheng. 2024. <span>“New Insights of Salinity Impacts on Natural Organic Matter and Disinfection Byproducts Formation During Chlorination.”</span> <em>Chemical Engineering Journal</em> 466: 143334. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cej.2023.143334">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cej.2023.143334</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ghorbanpour2022" class="csl-entry">
Ghorbanpour, M., M. Omidvari, P. Abbaszadeh-Dahaji, R. Omidvar, and K. Kariman. 2022. <span>“Halophytes Play Important Role in Phytoremediation of Salt-Affected Soils in the Bed of Urmia Lake, Iran.”</span> <em>Scientific Reports</em> 12 (1): 12269. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16552-5">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-16552-5</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Gill2024" class="csl-entry">
Gill, S., M. Ramzan, G. Naz, L. Ali, S. Danish, M. J. Ansari, and S. H. Salmen. 2024. <span>“Effect of Silicon Nanoparticle-Based Biochar on Wheat Growth, Antioxidants, and Nutrients Concentration Under Salinity Stress.”</span> <em>Scientific Reports</em> 14 (1): 6380. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56798-9">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-56798-9</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hafez2022a" class="csl-entry">
Hafez, M., A. M. Abdallah, A. E. Mohamed, and M. Rashad. 2022. <span>“Influence of Environmental-Friendly Bio-Organic Ameliorants on Abiotic Stress to Sustainable Agriculture in Arid Regions.”</span> <em>Journal of King Saud University - Science</em> 34: 102212. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jksus.2022.102212">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jksus.2022.102212</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hafez2022b" class="csl-entry">
Hafez, M., S. Ge, K. I. Tsivka, A. I. Popov, and M. Rashad. 2022. <span>“Enhancing Calcareous and Saline-Sodic Soils Fertility by Increasing Organic Matter Decomposition and Enzyme Activities.”</span> <em>Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis</em> 53 (15): 1942–59. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00103624.2022.2068345">https://doi.org/10.1080/00103624.2022.2068345</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hafez2021" class="csl-entry">
Hafez, M., A. I. Popov, and M. Rashad. 2021. <span>“Integrated Use of Bio-Organic Fertilizers for Enhancing Soil Fertility–Plant Nutrition and Initial Growth of Corn.”</span> <em>Environmental Technology &amp; Innovation</em> 21: 101329. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eti.2020.101329">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eti.2020.101329</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hayat2020" class="csl-entry">
Hayat, K., Y. Zhou, S. Menhas, J. Bundschuh, S. Hayat, A. Ullah, and D. Ding. 2020. <span>“Pennisetum Giganteum: An Emerging Salt Accumulating Crop for Sustainable Saline Agriculture.”</span> <em>Environmental Pollution</em> 265: 114876. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114876">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114876</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hu2024" class="csl-entry">
Hu, J. P., Y. Y. He, J. H. Li, Z. L. Lü, Y. W. Zhang, Y. H. Li, and W. Wang. 2024. <span>“Planting Halophytes Increases the Rhizosphere Ecosystem Multifunctionality via Reducing Soil Salinity.”</span> <em>Environmental Research</em> 261: 119707. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2024.119707">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2024.119707</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ivushkin2019" class="csl-entry">
Ivushkin, K., H. Bartholomeus, A. K. Bregt, A. Pulatov, B. Kempen, and L. de Sousa. 2019. <span>“Global Mapping of Soil Salinity Change.”</span> <em>Remote Sensing of Environment</em> 231: 111260. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2019.111260">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2019.111260</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jia2023" class="csl-entry">
Jia, X., Y. Zhao, T. Liu, S. Huang, and Y. Chang. 2023. <span>“Elevated CO2 Affects the Dynamics of Soil Dissolved Organic Matter in a Desert Ecosystem.”</span> <em>Science of the Total Environment</em> 857: 159710. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159710">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159710</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jiang2024" class="csl-entry">
Jiang, Y., Y. Lei, W. Qin, H. Korpelainen, and C. Li. 2024. <span>“Revealing the Role of Endophytic Bacteria in the Adaptive Strategies of Submerged Macrophytes to Eutrophic Water.”</span> <em>Science of the Total Environment</em> 912: 169618. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169618">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.169618</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kim2021" class="csl-entry">
Kim, J. M., A. S. Roh, S. C. Choi, E. J. Kim, M. T. Choi, B. K. Ahn, and Y. H. Lee. 2021. <span>“Soil pH and Electrical Conductivity Are Key Edaphic Factors Shaping Bacterial Communities of Greenhouse Soils in Korea.”</span> <em>Journal of Microbiology</em> 54 (12): 838–45. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12275-016-6434-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12275-016-6434-6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kotb2000" class="csl-entry">
Kotb, T. H. S., T. Watanabe, Y. Ogino, and K. K. Tanji. 2000. <span>“Soil Salinization in the Nile Delta and Related Policy Issues in Egypt.”</span> <em>Agricultural Water Management</em> 43 (2): 239–61. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-3774(99)00052-9">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-3774(99)00052-9</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Li2022Biochar" class="csl-entry">
Li, H., X. Liang, Y. Chen, Y. Lian, G. Tian, and W. Ni. 2022. <span>“Effect of Biochar Amendment on Soil Properties, Nitrogen Mineralization and Microbial Community Structure During Pig Manure Composting with Corn Stalk.”</span> <em>Bioresource Technology</em> 346: 126591. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2021.126591">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biortech.2021.126591</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Li2024ZnONP" class="csl-entry">
Li, H., A. Rehman, N. A. Yasin, J. Yao, M. Ali, Z. Hasnain, and P. Zhou. 2024. <span>“Biosynthesized Zinc Oxide Nanoparticles Modulate the Phytoremediation Potential of Pennisetum Giganteum.”</span> <em>Journal of Cleaner Production</em> 434: 140346. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.140346">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.140346</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Liu2023mSystems" class="csl-entry">
Liu, Z., T. Zhou, P. Cui, Z. Li, X. Huang, Y. Jing, and H. Xu. 2023. <span>“Keystone Rare Microbial Taxa Promote the Occurrence of Soil Aggregate-Associated Functions.”</span> <em>mSystems</em> 8 (2): e01178–22. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/msystems.01178-22">https://doi.org/10.1128/msystems.01178-22</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Luo2025" class="csl-entry">
Luo, S., Z. Chen, X. Zhang, M. Zhou, Y. Peng, J. Wu, and Y. Kuzyakov. 2025. <span>“<a href="">Rehabilitation of Soil Salinity and Sodicity Using Diverse Amendments and Plants: A Critical Review</a>.”</span> <em>Discover Environment</em> 3: 199.
</div>
<div id="ref-Malik2023" class="csl-entry">
Malik, A., S. Mor, and J. Tokas. 2023. <span>“Emission of Greenhouse Gases and Volatile Organic Compounds During Composting of Agricultural Crop Residues.”</span> <em>Science of the Total Environment</em> 866: 161312. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161312">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161312</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mao2016" class="csl-entry">
Mao, Y., X. Li, W. A. Dick, and L. Chen. 2016. <span>“Remediation of Saline–Sodic Soil with Flue Gas Desulfurization Gypsum in a Reclaimed Tidal Flat of Southeast China.”</span> <em>Journal of Environmental Sciences</em> 45: 224–32. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jes.2015.10.021">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jes.2015.10.021</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Meloni2003" class="csl-entry">
Meloni, D. A., M. A. Oliva, C. A. Martinez, and J. Cambraia. 2003. <span>“Photosynthesis and Antioxidant Enzyme Activity in Cotton Under Salt Stress.”</span> <em>Environmental and Experimental Botany</em> 49 (1): 69–76. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0098-8472(02)00058-8">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0098-8472(02)00058-8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Murtaza2017" class="csl-entry">
Murtaza, B., G. Murtaza, M. Sabir, G. Owens, G. Abbas, M. Imran, and G. M. Shah. 2017. <span>“Amelioration of Saline-Sodic Soil with Gypsum Can Increase Yield and Nitrogen Use Efficiency.”</span> <em>Archives of Agronomy and Soil Science</em> 63 (9): 1267–80. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03650340.2016.1258118">https://doi.org/10.1080/03650340.2016.1258118</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Qadir2007" class="csl-entry">
Qadir, M., and J. D. Oster. 2007. <span>“Crop and Irrigation Management Strategies for Saline-Sodic Soils.”</span> <em>Science of the Total Environment</em> 323 (1–3): 1–19. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.10.006">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.10.006</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rezapour2021" class="csl-entry">
Rezapour, S., A. Nouri, F. Asadzadeh, S. Oustan, and S. Khosravi. 2021. <span>“Reclamation of a Calcareous Sodic Soil with Combined Amendments.”</span> <em>Archives of Agronomy and Soil Science</em> 67 (1): 1–15. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/03650340.2019.1685496">https://doi.org/10.1080/03650340.2019.1685496</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rezapour2023" class="csl-entry">
———. 2023. <span>“Combining Chemical and Organic Treatments Enhances Remediation Performance.”</span> <em>Communications Earth &amp; Environment</em> 4: 285. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-023-00940-4">https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-023-00940-4</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Robbins1986" class="csl-entry">
Robbins, C. W. 1986. <span>“Carbon Dioxide Partial Pressure in Lysimeter Soils.”</span> <em>Agronomy Journal</em> 78 (4): 151–58. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2134/agronj1986.00021962007800040035x">https://doi.org/10.2134/agronj1986.00021962007800040035x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dosSantos2021" class="csl-entry">
Santos, T. B. dos, A. F. Ribas, S. G. H. de Souza, I. G. F. Budzinski, and D. S. Domingues. 2021. <span>“Physiological Responses to Drought, Salinity, and Heat Stress in Plants: A Review.”</span> <em>Stresses</em> 1 (1): 42–61. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/stresses1010004">https://doi.org/10.3390/stresses1010004</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Shao2019" class="csl-entry">
Shao, S., Y. Zhao, W. Zhang, G. Hu, H. Xie, W. Yan, and D. She. 2019. <span>“Linkage of Microbial Residue Dynamics with Soil Organic Carbon Accumulation.”</span> <em>Soil Biology and Biochemistry</em> 114: 114–20. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2017.07.021">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2017.07.021</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Song2023" class="csl-entry">
Song, Y., Y. Li, Y. Cai, S. Fu, Y. Luo, H. Wang, and Y. Li. 2023. <span>“Biochar Decreases Soil N2O Emissions in Moso Bamboo Plantations.”</span> <em>Geoderma</em> 348: 183–95. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geoderma.2019.114631">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geoderma.2019.114631</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Tian2023" class="csl-entry">
Tian, X., D. Wang, G. Chai, Z. Zhang, and R. Song. 2023. <span>“Effects of Biochar Application on the Physical Properties and Water Retention of Saline-Alkali Soils.”</span> <em>Sustainability</em> 15 (3): 2796. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/su15032796">https://doi.org/10.3390/su15032796</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Trivedi2020" class="csl-entry">
Trivedi, P., J. E. Leach, S. G. Tringe, T. Sa, and B. K. Singh. 2020. <span>“Plant–Microbiome Interactions: From Community Assembly to Plant Health.”</span> <em>Nature Reviews Microbiology</em> 18 (11): 607–21. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-020-0412-1">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-020-0412-1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Wang2024SaltTolerance" class="csl-entry">
Wang, H., R. Xu, L. You, Z. Liang, J. Li, W. Wang, and B. Liu. 2024. <span>“Comprehensive Strategies for Improving Salt Tolerance in Crops.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Plant Science</em> 15: 1362647. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2024.1362647">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2024.1362647</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Wen2024" class="csl-entry">
Wen, T., M. Zhao, T. Liu, Q. Huang, J. Yuan, and Q. Shen. 2024. <span>“High Abundance of Proteobacteria in Enrichment Soil Amendments Increases Crop Yields.”</span> <em>Plant and Soil</em> 478 (1–2): 287–302. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11104-023-06089-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11104-023-06089-6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Xing2024" class="csl-entry">
Xing, Y., T. Zhang, W. Jiang, P. Li, P. Shi, G. Xu, and J. Guo. 2024. <span>“Effects of Irrigation with Magnetically Treated Saline Water on Soil Water-Salt Distribution and Cotton Growth.”</span> <em>Agricultural Water Management</em> 295: 108775. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2024.108775">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2024.108775</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Xiong2020" class="csl-entry">
Xiong, Y. W., X. W. Li, T. T. Wang, Y. Gong, C. M. Zhang, K. Xing, and S. Qin. 2020. <span>“Root Exudates-Driven Rhizosphere Recruitment of Bacillus Flexus KLBMP 4941 Under Salt Stress.”</span> <em>Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety</em> 194: 110374. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.110374">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecoenv.2020.110374</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Yang2021" class="csl-entry">
Yang, F., S. Huang, R. Gao, W. Liu, T. Yong, X. Wang, and W. Yang. 2021. <span>“Growth of Soybean Seedlings in Relay Strip Intercropping Systems in Relation to Light Quantity and Red:far-Red Ratio.”</span> <em>Field Crops Research</em> 155: 245–53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fcr.2010.10.002">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fcr.2010.10.002</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Youssef2024" class="csl-entry">
Youssef, M. A., J. Liu, G. M. Chescheir, R. W. Skaggs, L. M. Negm, and S. Tian. 2024. <span>“DRAINMOD-DSSAT Model for Simulating Hydrology, Soil Temperature, Crop Growth and Nitrogen Dynamics.”</span> <em>Agricultural Water Management</em> 295: 108745. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2024.108745">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2024.108745</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zahedifar2020" class="csl-entry">
Zahedifar, M. 2020. <span>“Assessing Alteration of Soil Quality, Degradation, and Resistance Indices Under Different Land Uses.”</span> <em>Catena</em> 185: 104309. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2019.104309">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2019.104309</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zahra2024" class="csl-entry">
Zahra, N., M. S. Al Hinai, M. B. Hafeez, A. Rehman, A. Wahid, K. H. Siddique, and M. Farooq. 2024. <span>“Regulation of Photosynthesis Under Salt Stress and Associated Tolerance Mechanisms.”</span> <em>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</em> 178: 55–69. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2022.11.006">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2022.11.006</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zhang2023" class="csl-entry">
Zhang, W., X. Jin, D. Liu, C. Lang, and B. Shan. 2023. <span>“Temporal and Spatial Variation of Nitrogen and Phosphorus and Eutrophication Assessment.”</span> <em>Journal of Environmental Sciences</em> 55: 41–48. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jes.2016.07.014">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jes.2016.07.014</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zhao2021" class="csl-entry">
Zhao, Y., and X. Tian. 2021. <span>“Effect of Biochar Amendment on the Transformation of Cadmium and Lead in Contaminated Paddy Soils.”</span> <em>Environmental Science and Pollution Research</em> 28: 15542–53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-11835-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11356-020-11835-0</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zheng2023" class="csl-entry">
Zheng, S., Y. Xia, Y. Hu, X. Chen, Y. Rui, A. Gunina, and Y. Kuzyakov. 2023. <span>“Stoichiometry of Carbon, Nitrogen, and Phosphorus in Soil.”</span> <em>Soil and Tillage Research</em> 209: 104903. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.still.2021.104903">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.still.2021.104903</a>.
</div>
</div>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled" title="Publication &amp; Reviewer Details">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Publication &amp; Reviewer Details
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><strong>Publication Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Submitted:</strong> <em>30 January 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Accepted:</strong> <em>16 February 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Published (Online):</strong> <em>18 February 2026</em></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Reviewer Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 1:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 2:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer/Publisher’s Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of the publisher and/or the editor(s).<br>
The publisher and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>© Copyright (2025): Author(s). The licensee is the journal publisher. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>, which permits non-commercial use, sharing, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and no modifications or adaptations are made.</p>
</blockquote>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0</a></div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Review-Article</category>
  <category>Environment</category>
  <category>Soil</category>
  <category>SmartFarming</category>
  <guid>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA202601A408/JOSTA202601A408.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TILLING and Eco-TILLING: Reverse Genetics Approaches for Crop Improvement</title>
  <dc:creator>Noru Raja Sekhar Reddy*</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Deepthy Antony P</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Asish I Edakkalathur</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jiji Joseph</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA2026016BCE/JOSTA2026016BCE.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 

<section class="josta-issue-banner" aria-label="Journal issue banner">
  <div class="jib-wrap">


    <div class="jib-cover">
      <img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA2026016BCE/cover.webp" alt="Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture – cover image">
    </div>


    <div class="jib-meta">
      <p class="jib-journal-tag">Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture</p>

      <h2 class="jib-subtitle anchored">
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Volume 02</a>
        •
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Issue 01</a>
        • 2026
      </h2>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">ISSN (online)</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://portal.issn.org/resource/ISSN/3107-6882" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-issn-link">
            3107-6882
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">License</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-license-link">
            CC BY-NC-ND 4.0
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>
    </div>

  </div>
</section>

<style>
  :root {
    --j-navy:#0053ed;
    --j-brown:#8b6a3a;
    --j-green:#0b5a56;
    --j-beige:#f8f3ea;
  }

  .josta-issue-banner {
    background: linear-gradient(115deg, var(--j-beige), #ffffff);
    border-bottom: 2px solid rgba(31, 52, 92, 0.12);
    padding: 1.8rem 1.4rem;
    margin-bottom: 1.6rem;
    font-family: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, "Segoe UI", sans-serif;
  }

  .jib-wrap {
    max-width: 1100px;
    margin: 0 auto;
    display: flex;
    gap: 1.6rem;
    align-items: center;
  }

  /* Cover image — NO ROUNDED CORNERS */
  .jib-cover img {
    display: block;
    max-width: 120px;
    height: auto;
    border-radius: 0;      /* removed curve */
    box-shadow: 0 6px 16px rgba(0,0,0,0.12);
  }

  .jib-journal-tag {
    margin: 0 0 0.4rem 0;
    font-size: 1.15rem;
    font-weight: 700;
    color: var(--j-green);
  }

  .jib-subtitle {
    margin: 0 0 0.7rem 0;
    font-size: 1rem;
    font-weight: 500;
    color: var(--j-navy);
    opacity: 0.85;
  }

  /* Volume/Issue links */
  .jib-vi-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-vi-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  .jib-line {
    margin: 0.15rem 0;
    font-size: 0.95rem;
    display: flex;
    gap: 0.4rem;
    align-items: baseline;
    color: #333;
  }

  .jib-label {
    font-weight: 600;
    color: var(--j-navy);
  }

  /* ISSN link */
  .jib-issn-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
  }
  .jib-issn-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  /* License link */
  .jib-license-link {
    color: var(--j-green);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-license-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: row; align-items: flex-start; }
    .jib-cover img { max-width: 90px; }
    .jib-journal-tag { font-size: 1.05rem; }
    .jib-subtitle { font-size: 0.9rem; }
  }

  @media (max-width: 480px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: column; align-items: flex-start; }
  }
</style>




<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202601.6BCE"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/DOI-10.65287%2Fjosta.202601.6BCE-blue?logo=doi" class="img-fluid" alt="DOI"></a> <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/18616311"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/View%20on-Zenodo-0b5a56?logo=zenodo&amp;labelColor=d9d9d9.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Zenodo"></a><br>
<img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Open%20Access-Yes-0b5a56?style=flat-square&amp;logo=openaccess&amp;logoColor=white.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Open Access"> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Status-Peer%20Reviewed-1f345c?style=flat-square.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Status"></p>
<!-- josta inline actions: pdf • copy citation • citation count -->
<div class="j-inline" style="margin-top:1rem;">
<p><a href="pdfs/JOSTA-202601-6BCE.pdf" download="" class="j-btn" aria-label="download pdf">  <span>download pdf</span> </a></p>
<p>  <span>copy citation</span> <span id="j-tip" class="j-tip" aria-live="polite">citation copied!</span> </p>
<p><span class="j-chip" data-doi="10.65287/josta.202601.6BCE" aria-label="citation count"> <span id="j-cite-count" class="j-chip-count">0</span> <span class="j-chip-label">citations</span> </span></p>
</div>
<!-- hidden citation text (kept as plain html) -->
<p id="j-citation-text" style="display:none;">
REDDY, N. R. S., Antony P, D., edakkalathur, . asish ., &amp; Joseph, J. (2026). TILLING and Eco-TILLING: Reverse Genetics Approaches for Crop Improvement. Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture, 2(1). https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202601.6BCE
</p>
<style>
/* row */
.j-inline{display:flex;align-items:center;gap:1rem;flex-wrap:nowrap}

/* button */
.j-btn{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.5rem;padding:.45rem 1rem;
  border-radius:999px;background:#8b6a3a;color:#fff;text-decoration:none;
  font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;
  box-shadow:0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.1);transition:background .25s ease}
.j-btn:hover{background:#6d532d}

/* copy link */
.j-copy{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.4rem;color:#1f345c;
  text-decoration:none;font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;position:relative}
.j-copy:hover{color:#0b5a56;text-decoration:underline}

/* tooltip */
.j-tip{visibility:hidden;opacity:0;transition:opacity .25s;
  background:#0b5a56;color:#fff;position:absolute;top:-34px;left:50%;
  transform:translateX(-50%);padding:.3rem .6rem;border-radius:6px;font-size:.75rem;white-space:nowrap}
.j-copy:focus .j-tip,.j-copy:active .j-tip{visibility:visible;opacity:1}

/* citation chip */
.j-chip{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.35rem;padding:.25rem .7rem;
  border:1px solid #ddd;border-radius:999px;background:#f8f7f5;
  font:400 .85rem/1 system-ui,"Segoe UI",Roboto,sans-serif;box-shadow:0 1px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.08)}
.j-chip-count{font-weight:700;font-size:1rem;color:#1f345c}
.j-chip-label{text-transform:uppercase;letter-spacing:.2px;color:#8b6a3a}

/* small screens: allow wrap with gentle spacing */
@media (max-width:540px){.j-inline{flex-wrap:wrap;row-gap:.6rem}}
</style>
<script>
function jCopyCitation(){
  const t=document.getElementById("j-citation-text").innerText.trim();
  navigator.clipboard.writeText(t);
  const tip=document.getElementById("j-tip");
  tip.style.visibility="visible"; tip.style.opacity="1";
  setTimeout(()=>{tip.style.visibility="hidden"; tip.style.opacity="0";},1600);
}

document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', async ()=>{
  const chip=document.querySelector('.j-chip'); if(!chip) return;
  const doi=chip.dataset.doi, el=document.getElementById('j-cite-count');
  const api=`https://api.crossref.org/works/${encodeURIComponent(doi)}?select=is-referenced-by-count`;
  try{
    const r=await fetch(api,{cache:'no-store'}); const j=await r.json();
    const n = j?.message?.['is-referenced-by-count'];
    el.textContent = (Number.isFinite(n) ? n : 0);
  }catch{ el.textContent='0'; }
});
</script>
<hr>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>Global agriculture is facing challenges due to changing climate conditions, declining soil health, a rising human population, and increasing incidence of pests, diseases, and environmental stresses <span class="citation" data-cites="Prajapati2024">(Prajapati et al. 2024)</span>. Addressing these challenges requires the development of high-yielding, climate-resilient crop varieties supported by efficient identification and utilization of genetic variation. While conventional breeding remains essential, its reliance on phenotypic selection and long breeding cycles limits the rapid deployment of improved cultivars. Similarly, transgenic technologies, despite their effectiveness, face regulatory constraints and public acceptance issues in many regions <span class="citation" data-cites="Ahmar2020 Bhattacharya2023">(Ahmar et al. 2020; Bhattacharya, Parkhi, and Char 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>In this context, reverse genetics approaches such as Targeting Induced Local Lesions IN Genomes (TILLING) and Eco-TILLING have emerged as practical, non-transgenic alternatives for functional genomics and crop improvement <span class="citation" data-cites="Selvakumar2023 Siddique2023">(Selvakumar, Jat, and Manjunathagowda 2023; Siddique et al. 2023)</span>. These methods allow precise identification of nucleotide-level variation without foreign DNA integration, making them socially and regulatorily acceptable. TILLING is particularly valuable for species with large, polyploid, or poorly annotated genomes, whereas Eco-TILLING enables the exploration of naturally occurring variation in landraces, wild relatives, and germplasm collections <span class="citation" data-cites="Cheng2021 Mohapatra2023">(Cheng et al. 2021; Mohapatra et al. 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Earlier reviews have established the conceptual and methodological foundations of TILLING and Eco-TILLING as reverse genetics platforms <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007a">(Till, Comai, and Henikoff 2007)</span>. However, substantial advances have occurred in both detection technologies and applied breeding contexts since those syntheses. In particular, the adoption of high-resolution melting (HRM) analysis and next-generation sequencing-assisted TILLING has improved mutation detection efficiency, scalability, and precision. At the same time, recent studies have demonstrated the application of these approaches in underutilized, polyploid, and climate-sensitive crops, where regulatory or technical constraints may limit genome editing strategies.</p>
<p>This review extends prior syntheses by incorporating recent methodological advances alongside crop-specific case studies and by positioning TILLING-based approaches within the broader context of climate-resilient and resource-efficient breeding. By linking technological innovation with contemporary breeding priorities, this review offers an updated perspective on the sustained relevance of TILLING and Eco-TILLING in modern crop improvement strategies</p>
</section>
<section id="tilling" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tilling"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Tilling</h2>
<p>Targeting Induced Local Lesions in Genomes (TILLING) is a reverse genetics approach that enables systematic identification of induced point mutations within specific target genes through enzymatic mismatch cleavage. The foundational framework of TILLING was established in the early 2000s with the development of population-based mutagenesis and heteroduplex-based detection systems in Arabidopsis thaliana <span class="citation" data-cites="McCallum2000 Till2004">(McCallum et al. 2000; Till et al. 2004)</span>. Subsequent reviews consolidated these principles and formalized TILLING and Eco-TILLING as broadly applicable reverse genetics platforms for crop improvement <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007b">(Till et al. 2007)</span>. These early studies defined the core methodological workflow while also identifying practical constraints, including optimization of mutation density, nuclease specificity, and throughput limitations.</p>
<p>The approach combines chemical or physical mutagenesis with high-throughput molecular screening to detect sequence variation in target loci <span class="citation" data-cites="Khan2018 Siddique2023">(Khan et al. 2018; Siddique et al. 2023)</span>. Mutant populations are generated, genomic DNA is extracted, and pooled samples are screened following PCR amplification of the region of interest. Denaturation and re-annealing steps produce heteroduplex DNA, which is subsequently cleaved by single-strand–specific nucleases such as CEL I (Celery Extract Nuclease I) and ENDO1 (Endonuclease I) at sites of single-base mismatches or small insertions/deletions <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2004">(Till et al. 2004)</span>. While CEL I is widely used for its broad mismatch recognition and high sensitivity, non-specific cleavage may occur under suboptimal conditions. ENDO1 can offer improved specificity in certain systems, although enzyme performance may vary depending on reaction parameters <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007b">(Till et al. 2007)</span>. A schematic representation of the TILLING workflow, from mutagenesis to mutation detection, is presented in Figure&nbsp;1.</p>
<p>Associated seed stocks and DNA libraries are typically preserved to support long-term functional genomics and breeding applications <span class="citation" data-cites="Jiang2022">(Jiang et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<div id="fig-figure1" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-figure1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA2026016BCE/figures/fig1.png" style="width:80.0%" class="figure-img">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-figure1-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: Schematic workflow of the TILLING process
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unlike conventional mutation breeding, which often recovers a limited subset of desirable alleles, TILLING enables systematic detection of a wide spectrum of induced variants. In EMS-based populations, mutation densities generally range from approximately 1 per 200–1000 kb, depending on mutagen dosage, genome size, and ploidy level. Effective recovery of functional alleles for a single gene typically requires screening populations of 1,000–5,000 M2 individuals, with larger populations needed for polyploid species or rare knockout variants <span class="citation" data-cites="Cooper2008">(Cooper et al. 2008)</span>. By linking induced nucleotide variation to phenotypic outcomes, TILLING provides a non-transgenic platform for targeted trait discovery and incorporation of beneficial alleles into breeding pipelines <span class="citation" data-cites="Cheng2021 Sun2024">(Cheng et al. 2021; Sun et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<section id="innovative-techniques-derived-from-tilling" class="level3" data-number="2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="innovative-techniques-derived-from-tilling"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Innovative techniques derived from TILLING</h3>
<p>Several mutation detection methods have evolved from the original TILLING platform by exploiting structural differences between homoduplex and heteroduplex DNA. These include Single-Strand Conformation Polymorphism (SSCP), Denaturing Gradient Gel Electrophoresis (DGGE), Conformation-Sensitive Gel Electrophoresis (CSGE), Temperature Gradient Capillary Electrophoresis (TGCE), Denaturing High-Performance Liquid Chromatography (dHPLC), and High-Resolution Melting (HRM) analysis <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007b SzurmanZubrzycka2017 Selvakumar2023">(Till et al. 2007; Szurman-Zubrzycka et al. 2017; Selvakumar, Jat, and Manjunathagowda 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Among these, HRM has gained prominence for its rapid detection of sequence variation based on the differential melting behavior of PCR amplicons. Unlike nuclease-based approaches, HRM eliminates enzymatic cleavage steps and enables scalable, high-throughput screening <span class="citation" data-cites="Selvakumar2023">(Selvakumar, Jat, and Manjunathagowda 2023)</span>. It has been successfully applied in crops such as tomato, pepper, potato, and broccoli <span class="citation" data-cites="Mohan2016">(Mohan et al. 2016)</span>.</p>
<p>The integration of next-generation sequencing (NGS) has fundamentally reshaped TILLING workflows, transitioning the approach from gel-dependent mutation detection to scalable genomic platforms. In NGS-assisted TILLING, pooled PCR amplicons or targeted genomic regions are directly sequenced, enabling digital identification of induced nucleotide variants at single-base resolution <span class="citation" data-cites="Fanelli2021 Jiang2022">(Fanelli et al. 2021; Jiang et al. 2022)</span>. Compared with enzymatic mismatch cleavage and fragment analysis methods <span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007a">(Till, Comai, and Henikoff 2007)</span>, sequencing-based platforms enhance sensitivity, support multiplexed screening of multiple loci within large mutant populations, and reduce reliance on capillary or gel-based systems.</p>
<p>Reference-guided amplicon sequencing platforms have demonstrated improved mutation discovery efficiency and reduced manual processing in crops such as barley and sunflower <span class="citation" data-cites="Fanelli2021 Jiang2022">(Fanelli et al. 2021; Jiang et al. 2022)</span>. Beyond targeted amplicon sequencing, targeted resequencing and exome-capture approaches allow simultaneous interrogation of broader gene sets, particularly in species with available reference genomes. Although initial sequencing infrastructure may require higher investment, per-sample costs decrease substantially at scale, making NGS-assisted TILLING increasingly cost-effective for large breeding programs. Moreover, digital variant datasets facilitate allele frequency estimation, precise validation, and integration with genomic databases, thereby improving data interpretation and traceability. Collectively, these advances position sequencing-assisted TILLING as a central component of contemporary reverse genetics and crop improvement strategies.</p>
<div id="tbl-techniques" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-techniques-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Techniques developed from TILLING
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-techniques-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 24%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 22%">
<col style="width: 17%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Technique</th>
<th>Developed for</th>
<th>Advantage</th>
<th>Disadvantage</th>
<th>Reference</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>iTILLING (individualized TILLING)</td>
<td>Arabidopsis reduces cost and time to carry out mutation screening</td>
<td>low cost</td>
<td>can be performed only for a small number of genes because the population used for screening is of short duration.</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Bush2010">(Bush and Krysan 2010)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>DeTILLING (Deletion TILLING)</td>
<td>This technique employs the spectrum of available reverse genetic, molecular tools for the functional characterization of genes.</td>
<td>overcomes the shortage of null mutations and exclusively detects knockout mutations.</td>
<td>disruption of multiple genes, complicating gene-function analysis.</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Rogers2009">(Rogers et al. 2009)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>EcoTILLING (Ecotypic TILLING)</td>
<td>to evaluate naturally occurring variations</td>
<td>Enables low-cost discovery of natural genetic variants in wild crops unsuitable for induced mutagenesis.</td>
<td>Limited to existing natural variation, making it less effective in species with low genetic diversity.</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Comai2004">(Comai et al. 2004)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
<p>TILLING has evolved from a basic chemical mutagenesis approach into a versatile platform adapted to a wide range of crop species and breeding systems. Its modern variants support both functional genomics research and applied crop improvement across diverse agricultural contexts. Table&nbsp;2 provides a comparative overview of key TILLING approaches, highlighting their applications, advantages, and limitations in contemporary breeding strategies.</p>
<div id="tbl-crop" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-crop-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;2: Comparison of traditional and modern TILLING variants used in crop improvement
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-crop-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 16%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 12%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>TILLING type</th>
<th>Target crops/species</th>
<th>Key features</th>
<th>Advantages</th>
<th>Limitations</th>
<th>Reference</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Traditional TILLING</td>
<td>Autogamous, seed-producing crops</td>
<td>Uses chemical mutagenesis, M1/M2 population development, DNA pooling, endonuclease-based mutation screening</td>
<td>Broad applicability across crops, long-term seed storage</td>
<td>Time-intensive; low mutation frequency</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Borevitz2003 Till2007a Till2007b">(Borevitz et al. 2003; Till, Comai, and Henikoff 2007; Till et al. 2007)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>techTILLING</td>
<td>Lotus, tomato, pepper, pea, melon, lettuce, etc.</td>
<td>Platform integrating forward genetics and reverse genetics for crop screening</td>
<td>Applied to various vegetable crops via centralized platforms</td>
<td>Requires infrastructure and genomic resources</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Perry2003 Perry2009">(J. A. Perry et al. 2003; J. Perry et al. 2009)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>mutTILLING</td>
<td>General crop species</td>
<td>Uses diverse mutagens to induce mutations for reverse genetics</td>
<td>Allows customized mutation spectrum targeting specific alleles</td>
<td>Variability in mutation recovery</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="McCallum2000">(McCallum et al. 2000)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>proTILLING</td>
<td>Tomato, capsicum, melon, potato, tobacco, etc.</td>
<td>Utilizes non-GM, proven mutagenesis methods suitable for breeders</td>
<td>Bypasses GMO regulations; directly applicable in breeding programs</td>
<td>Slower than transgenic approaches; may lose functional alleles</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Piron2010 Blomstedt2012">(Piron et al. 2010; Blomstedt et al. 2012)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>polyTILLING</td>
<td>Polyploids (potato, sweet potato, leek)</td>
<td>Exploits high mutation rates in polyploid genomes for gene discovery</td>
<td>Suitable for high-throughput allele mining despite genetic redundancy</td>
<td>High mutation loads; potential sterility in some polyploids</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Lawrence2003 Bush2010">(Lawrence and Pikaard 2003; Bush and Krysan 2010)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>VeggieTILLING</td>
<td>Vegetatively propagated crops (cassava, yams, etc.)</td>
<td>Mutagenizes vegetative parts (e.g., apical meristems); screens for mutations via phenotypic/genotypic tools</td>
<td>Enables TILLING in crops without seeds; useful for perennial and asexually propagated vegetables</td>
<td>Lack of meiosis limits classical breeding approaches; chimeras can occur</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Mba2009">(Mba et al. 2009)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="eco-tilling" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="eco-tilling"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Eco TILLING</h2>
<p>Eco-TILLING, first described by <span class="citation" data-cites="Comai2004">(Comai et al. 2004)</span>, is a modification of the original TILLING platform designed to detect naturally occurring nucleotide polymorphisms within populations. Unlike induced mutagenesis-based TILLING, Eco-TILLING relies on heteroduplex formation between reference and test DNA samples to identify sequence variation such as single nucleotide polymorphisms and small insertions or deletions.</p>
<p>Early implementations of Eco-TILLING utilized LI-COR gel-based detection systems for visualization of nuclease cleavage products <span class="citation" data-cites="Comai2004">(Comai et al. 2004)</span>. However, many laboratories have transitioned toward capillary electrophoresis and, more recently, sequencing-based detection platforms, which provide higher throughput, improved resolution, and reduced dependence on specialized gel imaging systems <span class="citation" data-cites="SzurmanZubrzycka2017 Selvakumar2023">(Szurman-Zubrzycka et al. 2017; Selvakumar, Jat, and Manjunathagowda 2023)</span>. Integration with next-generation sequencing now allows more precise haplotype identification and improved scalability in diverse germplasm collections.</p>
<p>Eco-TILLING has proven particularly valuable for allele mining in landraces, wild relatives, and pre-breeding materials. By identifying naturally occurring variation in candidate genes, it supports the introgression of favorable alleles into elite backgrounds without induced mutation load. Applications include the discovery of functional polymorphisms associated with nutritional traits, stress tolerance, and disease resistance <span class="citation" data-cites="Upadhyaya2017 Mohapatra2023">(Upadhyaya et al. 2017; Mohapatra et al. 2023)</span>. Because Eco-TILLING does not involve mutagenesis, it is especially suitable for crops with high natural diversity and for breeding programs focused on broadening the genetic base. In contrast to induced TILLING, which generates novel alleles, Eco-TILLING primarily facilitates characterization and deployment of existing variation. Together, the two approaches provide complementary strategies for functional genomics and crop improvement.</p>
</section>
<section id="applications" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Applications</h2>
<p>TILLING has been applied successfully to improve disease resistance, metabolic composition, and quality traits in several crop species. Representative case studies are summarized in Table&nbsp;3, and selected examples are discussed below to illustrate practical outcomes. In tomato, a proTILLING approach identified mutations in the eIF4E gene that conferred resistance to two potyviruses <span class="citation" data-cites="Piron2010">(Piron et al. 2010)</span>. Because these alleles were generated through chemical mutagenesis rather than transgenic modification, they were directly incorporated into breeding programs without regulatory constraints. This study demonstrated the effectiveness of TILLING in translating molecular knowledge of host–virus interactions into deployable resistance traits.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Blomstedt2012">(Blomstedt et al. 2012)</span> combined biochemical screening with TILLING to target genes involved in cyanogenic glucoside biosynthesis in sorghum. Mutant lines with reduced cyanogenic potential were identified, resulting in improved forage safety while maintaining agronomic performance. This study highlights the use of TILLING to modify complex metabolic pathways relevant to crop utilization. Oil quality improvement has also been achieved through TILLING. In soybean, mutations in fatty acid desaturase genes were detected using TILLING, leading to altered fatty acid composition and increased oleic acid content <span class="citation" data-cites="Cooper2008">(Cooper et al. 2008)</span>. Such modifications improve oxidative stability and nutritional quality, demonstrating the role of TILLING in compositional trait improvement.</p>
<p>Recent advances integrating next-generation sequencing with TILLING have improved mutation detection efficiency and scalability, as demonstrated in barley through amplicon-based TILLING-by-sequencing platforms <span class="citation" data-cites="Jiang2022">(Jiang et al. 2022)</span>. Eco-TILLING has further enabled identification of natural allelic variation within germplasm collections, supporting allele mining and biofortification strategies, such as folate enhancement in tomato <span class="citation" data-cites="Upadhyaya2017">(Upadhyaya et al. 2017)</span>. Together, these studies confirm that TILLING and Eco-TILLING function as practical platforms for functional allele discovery and direct trait improvement within conventional breeding systems.</p>
<div id="tbl-crops" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-crops-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;3: Applications of TILLING and Eco-TILLING in crop improvement
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-crops-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 36%">
<col style="width: 16%">
<col style="width: 13%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Crop species</th>
<th>Target gene</th>
<th>Target trait / improvement</th>
<th>Methodology</th>
<th>Reference</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Rice (<em>Oryza sativa</em>)</td>
<td>Wx (Waxy gene)</td>
<td>Reduced amylose content; improved grain quality</td>
<td>Traditional TILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Till2007b">(Till et al. 2007)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Tomato (<em>Solanum lycopersicum</em>)</td>
<td>eIF4E</td>
<td>Resistance to potyviruses</td>
<td>proTILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Piron2010">(Piron et al. 2010)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Soybean (<em>Glycine max</em>)</td>
<td>FAD2-1A / FAD2-1B</td>
<td>Increased oleic acid content</td>
<td>Traditional TILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Cooper2008">(Cooper et al. 2008)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Barley (<em>Hordeum vulgare</em>)</td>
<td>HvCslF6</td>
<td>Modified β-glucan content</td>
<td>TILLING-by-Sequencing (NGS-assisted)</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Jiang2022">(Jiang et al. 2022)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><em>Brassica rapa</em></td>
<td>Multiple flowering genes</td>
<td>Flowering time modification</td>
<td>Traditional TILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Stephenson2010">(Stephenson et al. 2010)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><em>Lotus japonicus</em></td>
<td>Symbiosis-related genes</td>
<td>Improved nodulation efficiency</td>
<td>techTILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Perry2009">(J. Perry et al. 2009)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Sorghum (<em>Sorghum bicolor</em>)</td>
<td>Cyanogenic glucoside pathway genes</td>
<td>Reduced cyanogenic potential</td>
<td>proTILLING</td>
<td><span class="citation" data-cites="Blomstedt2012">(Blomstedt et al. 2012)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="comparison-of-tilling-and-eco-tilling-with-other-reverse-genetics-tools" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparison-of-tilling-and-eco-tilling-with-other-reverse-genetics-tools"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Comparison of TILLING and Eco-TILLING with other reverse genetics tools</h2>
<p>TILLING and Eco-TILLING operate alongside other reverse genetics and allele discovery tools such as CRISPR-based genome editing and genome-wide association studies (GWAS). CRISPR technologies enable precise, targeted modification of specific loci but often require efficient transformation systems, and efficient tissue culture regeneration systems may be subject to regulatory constraints <span class="citation" data-cites="Pacesa2024">(Pacesa, Pelea, and Jinek 2024)</span>. In contrast, TILLING generates allelic variation through mutagenesis without introducing foreign DNA, making it broadly applicable and regulatorily simpler in many breeding contexts. GWAS-based approaches rely on existing natural variation to identify trait-associated loci, whereas TILLING can create novel alleles, including rare loss-of-function variants not present in germplasm collections <span class="citation" data-cites="Park2025">(Park et al. 2025)</span>. Consequently, TILLING remains particularly valuable in orphan, polyploid, and transformation-recalcitrant crops, while also functioning complementarily with genome editing and genomic selection in integrated breeding pipelines.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Challenges</h2>
<p>Despite their advantages, TILLING and Eco-TILLING face limitations. Most induced mutations are silent or result in partial functional changes, making true knockout alleles relatively rare <span class="citation" data-cites="Kashtwari2019">(Kashtwari, Wani, and Rather 2019)</span>. Mutation detection requires specialized equipment, such as LI-COR systems and capillary electrophoresis platforms, which may be inaccessible in resource-limited settings <span class="citation" data-cites="Siyal2024">(Siyal et al. 2024)</span>. Additionally, Eco-TILLING may have limited power to detect rare alleles in highly diverse populations <span class="citation" data-cites="Gunnaiah2023">(Gunnaiah and Naika 2023)</span>. Successful implementation in orphan crops often depends on genomic resources, technical expertise, and infrastructure availability <span class="citation" data-cites="Kumari2024">(Kumari and Chatterjee 2024)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-directions"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Future directions</h2>
<p>The continued relevance of TILLING and Eco-TILLING will depend not only on methodological refinement but also on strategic implementation within national breeding systems. For developing countries, investment in shared mutation screening and sequencing facilities can substantially reduce costs while expanding access to high-throughput platforms. Prioritizing regionally important, climate-resilient, and underutilized crops, particularly those lacking efficient transformation systems, would enhance the impact of these approaches. Integration of mutant populations with existing germplasm collections and pre-breeding resources can strengthen allele discovery and minimize redundancy. Furthermore, building bioinformatics capacity, standardized data management frameworks, and coordinated training programs will be essential for sustainable deployment. When aligned with national crop improvement priorities, TILLING-based platforms offer cost-effective, non-transgenic tools for accelerating trait discovery and varietal development.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, TILLING and Eco-TILLING stand out as cost-effective, reliable, and non-transgenic approaches for detecting genetic variation, with great potential for application across a wide range of plant species, including underutilized and non-model crops. These techniques offer significant promise for crop improvement, particularly in species where traditional mutagenesis methods have proven challenging. However, realizing their full potential requires overcoming key obstacles, such as optimizing protocols for orphan crops, building local capacity, and integrating advanced genomic tools like next-generation sequencing. As technological advancements continue to lower costs and improve accessibility, TILLING is ready to become a central component in functional genomics and breeding programs, ultimately contributing to enhanced crop productivity and food security, especially for resource-limited farming communities.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<!-- References will be rendered here -->
<div id="ref-Ahmar2020" class="csl-entry">
Ahmar, S., R. A. Gill, K. H. Jung, A. Faheem, M. U. Qasim, M. Mubeen, and W. Zhou. 2020. <span>“Conventional and Molecular Techniques from Simple Breeding to Speed Breeding in Crop Plants: Recent Advances and Future Outlook.”</span> <em>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</em> 21 (7): 2590. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21072590">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21072590</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bhattacharya2023" class="csl-entry">
Bhattacharya, A., V. Parkhi, and B. Char, eds. 2023. <em>TILLING and Eco-TILLING for Crop Improvement</em>. Singapore: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Blomstedt2012" class="csl-entry">
Blomstedt, C. K., R. M. Gleadow, N. O’Donnell, P. Naur, K. Jensen, T. Laursen, C. E. Olsen, et al. 2012. <span>“A Combined Biochemical Screen and TILLING Approach Identifies Mutations in Sorghum Bicolor Resulting in Acyanogenic Forage Production.”</span> <em>Plant Biotechnology Journal</em> 10 (1): 54–66. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-7652.2011.00646.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-7652.2011.00646.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Borevitz2003" class="csl-entry">
Borevitz, J. O., D. Liang, D. Plouffe, H. S. Chang, T. Zhu, D. Weigel, C. C. Berry, E. Winzeler, and J. Chory. 2003. <span>“Large-Scale Identification of Single-Feature Polymorphisms in Complex Genomes.”</span> <em>Genome Research</em> 13 (3): 513–23. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.1093103">https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.1093103</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bush2010" class="csl-entry">
Bush, S. M., and P. J. Krysan. 2010. <span>“iTILLING: A Personalized Approach to the Identification of Induced Mutations in Arabidopsis.”</span> <em>Plant Physiology</em> 154 (1): 25–35. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.110.159897">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.110.159897</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Cheng2021" class="csl-entry">
Cheng, L., Y. Li, Q. Qi, P. Xu, R. Feng, L. Palmer, J. Chen, et al. 2021. <span>“Single-Nucleotide-Level Mapping of DNA Regulatory Elements That Control Fetal Hemoglobin Expression.”</span> <em>Nature Genetics</em> 53 (6): 869–80. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-021-00861-8">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-021-00861-8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Comai2004" class="csl-entry">
Comai, L., K. Young, B. J. Till, S. H. Reynolds, E. A. Greene, C. A. Codomo, L. C. Enns, et al. 2004. <span>“Efficient Discovery of DNA Polymorphisms in Natural Populations by EcoTILLING.”</span> <em>The Plant Journal</em> 37 (5): 778–86. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0960-7412.2003.01999.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0960-7412.2003.01999.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Cooper2008" class="csl-entry">
Cooper, J. L., B. J. Till, R. G. Laport, M. C. Darlow, J. M. Kleffner, A. Jamai, T. El-Mellouki, et al. 2008. <span>“TILLING to Detect Induced Mutations in Soybean.”</span> <em>BMC Plant Biology</em> 8: 9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-8-9">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-8-9</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Fanelli2021" class="csl-entry">
Fanelli, V., K. J. Ngo, V. L. Thompson, B. R. Silva, H. Tsai, W. Sabetta, C. Montemurro, L. Comai, and S. L. Harmer. 2021. <span>“A TILLING-by-Sequencing Approach to Identify Induced Mutations in Sunflower Genes.”</span> <em>Scientific Reports</em> 11: 9885. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-89237-w">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-89237-w</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Gunnaiah2023" class="csl-entry">
Gunnaiah, R., and M. B. Naika. 2023. <span>“Bioinformatics and Candidate Gene Mining for TILLING.”</span> In <em>TILLING and Eco-TILLING for Crop Improvement</em>, 61–74. Singapore: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jiang2022" class="csl-entry">
Jiang, C., M. Lei, Y. Guo, G. Gao, L. Shi, Y. Jin, Y. Cai, et al. 2022. <span>“A Reference-Guided TILLING by Amplicon Sequencing Platform Supports Forward and Reverse Genetics in Barley.”</span> <em>Plant Communications</em> 3 (4): 100343. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xplc.2022.100317">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xplc.2022.100317</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kashtwari2019" class="csl-entry">
Kashtwari, M., A. A. Wani, and R. N. Rather. 2019. <span>“TILLING: An Alternative Path for Crop Improvement.”</span> <em>Journal of Crop Improvement</em> 33 (1): 83–109. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/15427528.2018.1544954">https://doi.org/10.1080/15427528.2018.1544954</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Khan2018" class="csl-entry">
Khan, A., I. Abidi, M. A. Bhat, Z. A. Dar, G. Ali, A. B. Shikari, and M. A. Khan. 2018. <span>“TILLING and Eco-TILLING: A Reverse Genetic Approach for Crop Improvement.”</span> <em>International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences</em> 7 (6): 15–21.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kumari2024" class="csl-entry">
Kumari, K., and A. Chatterjee. 2024. <em>Advancing Plant Breeding Through TILLING: Uncovering Genetic Diversity for Sustainable Agriculture</em>. Harvesting Tomorrow.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lawrence2003" class="csl-entry">
Lawrence, R. J., and C. S. Pikaard. 2003. <span>“Transgene-Induced RNA Interference: A Strategy for Overcoming Gene Redundancy in Polyploids to Generate Loss-of-Function Mutations.”</span> <em>The Plant Journal</em> 36 (1): 114–21. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-313x.2003.01857.x">https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-313x.2003.01857.x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mba2009" class="csl-entry">
Mba, C., R. Afza, S. Bado, and S. M. Jain. 2009. <span>“Induced Mutagenesis in Plants Using Physical and Chemical Agents.”</span> <em>Plant Cell, Tissue and Organ Culture</em> 104 (2): 149–66. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-010-9856-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-010-9856-0</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-McCallum2000" class="csl-entry">
McCallum, C. M., L. Comai, E. A. Greene, and S. Henikoff. 2000. <span>“Targeted Screening for Induced Mutations.”</span> <em>Nature Biotechnology</em> 18 (4): 455–57. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/74542">https://doi.org/10.1038/74542</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mohan2016" class="csl-entry">
Mohan, V., S. Gupta, S. Thomas, H. Mickey, C. Charakana, V. S. Chauhan, K. Sharma, et al. 2016. <span>“Tomato Fruits Show Wide Phenomic Diversity but Fruit Developmental Genes Show Low Genomic Diversity.”</span> <em>PLoS ONE</em> 11 (4): e0152907. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0152907">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0152907</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mohapatra2023" class="csl-entry">
Mohapatra, S. R., P. K. Majhi, K. Mondal, and K. Samantara. 2023. <span>“TILLING and Eco-TILLING: Concept, Progress and Role in Crop Improvement.”</span> In <em>Advanced Crop Improvement, Volume 1: Theory and Practice</em>, 349–77. Cham: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Pacesa2024" class="csl-entry">
Pacesa, M., O. Pelea, and M. Jinek. 2024. <span>“Past, Present, and Future of CRISPR Genome Editing Technologies.”</span> <em>Cell</em> 187: 1076–1100. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2024.01.042">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2024.01.042</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Park2025" class="csl-entry">
Park, T. C., P. C. Silva, T. Lübberstedt, and M. P. Scott. 2025. <span>“Beyond the Genome: The Role of Functional Markers in Contemporary Plant Breeding.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Plant Science</em> 16: 1637299. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2025.1637299">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2025.1637299</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Perry2003" class="csl-entry">
Perry, J. A., T. L. Wang, T. J. Welham, S. Gardner, J. M. Pike, S. Yoshida, and M. Parniske. 2003. <span>“A TILLING Reverse Genetics Tool and a Web-Accessible Collection of Mutants of Lotus Japonicus.”</span> <em>Plant Physiology</em> 131 (3): 866–71. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.102.017384">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.102.017384</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Perry2009" class="csl-entry">
Perry, J., A. Brachmann, T. Welham, A. Binder, M. Charpentier, M. Groth, K. Haage, K. Markmann, T. L. Wang, and M. Parniske. 2009. <span>“TILLING in Lotus Japonicus Identified Large Allelic Series for Symbiosis Genes.”</span> <em>Plant Physiology</em> 151 (3): 1281–91. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.142190">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.142190</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Piron2010" class="csl-entry">
Piron, F., M. Nicolaï, S. Minoïa, E. Piednoir, A. Moretti, A. Salgues, D. Zamir, C. Caranta, and A. Bendahmane. 2010. <span>“An Induced Mutation in Tomato eIF4E Leads to Immunity to Two Potyviruses.”</span> <em>PLoS ONE</em> 5 (6): e11313. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0011313">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0011313</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Prajapati2024" class="csl-entry">
Prajapati, V., S. K. Verma, A. Alam, and N. Khare. 2024. <span>“Impact of Climate Change in India: Challenges to Human Health.”</span> In <em>Climate Change in India</em>, 88–106. CRC Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rogers2009" class="csl-entry">
Rogers, C., J. Wen, R. Chen, and G. Oldroyd. 2009. <span>“Deletion-Based Reverse Genetics in Medicago Truncatula.”</span> <em>Plant Physiology</em> 151 (3): 1077–86. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.142919">https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.109.142919</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Selvakumar2023" class="csl-entry">
Selvakumar, R., G. S. Jat, and D. C. Manjunathagowda. 2023. <span>“Allele Mining Through TILLING and Eco-TILLING Approaches in Vegetable Crops.”</span> <em>Planta</em> 258 (1): 15. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00425-023-04176-2">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00425-023-04176-2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Siddique2023" class="csl-entry">
Siddique, M. I., A. Younis, M. A. Gururani, and J. Venkatesh. 2023. <span>“Application of TILLING as a Reverse Genetics Tool to Discover Mutations in Plant Genomes.”</span> In <em>Mutation Breeding for Sustainable Food Production and Climate Resilience</em>, 233–68. Singapore: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Siyal2024" class="csl-entry">
Siyal, A. L., S. Sial, A. Hossain, and A. G. Chang. 2024. <span>“Targeting Induced Local Lesions in Genomes Under Climate Change.”</span> In <em>Food Production, Diversity, and Safety Under Climate Change</em>, 223–33. Cham: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Stephenson2010" class="csl-entry">
Stephenson, P., D. Baker, T. Girin, A. Perez, S. Amoah, G. J. King, and L. Østergaard. 2010. <span>“A Rich TILLING Resource for Studying Gene Function in Brassica Rapa.”</span> <em>BMC Plant Biology</em> 10: 62. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-10-62">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-10-62</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Sun2024" class="csl-entry">
Sun, L., M. Lai, F. Ghouri, M. A. Nawaz, F. Ali, F. S. Baloch, M. A. Nadeem, M. Aasim, and M. Q. Shahid. 2024. <span>“Modern Plant Breeding Techniques in Crop Improvement and Genetic Diversity.”</span> <em>Plants</em> 13 (19): 2676. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/plants13192676">https://doi.org/10.3390/plants13192676</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SzurmanZubrzycka2017" class="csl-entry">
Szurman-Zubrzycka, M., B. Chmielewska, P. Gajewska, and I. Szarejko. 2017. <span>“Mutation Detection by Analysis of DNA Heteroduplexes in TILLING Populations.”</span> In <em>Biotechnologies for Plant Mutation Breeding: Protocols</em>, 281–303. New York: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Till2004" class="csl-entry">
Till, B. J., C. Burtner, L. Comai, and S. Henikoff. 2004. <span>“Mismatch Cleavage by Single-Strand-Specific Nucleases.”</span> <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em> 32 (8): 2632–41. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh599">https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh599</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Till2007a" class="csl-entry">
Till, B. J., L. Comai, and S. Henikoff. 2007. <span>“TILLING and EcoTILLING for Crop Improvement.”</span> In <em>Genomics-Assisted Crop Improvement</em>, 333–49. Dordrecht: Springer.
</div>
<div id="ref-Till2007b" class="csl-entry">
Till, B. J., J. Cooper, T. H. Tai, P. Colowit, E. A. Greene, S. Henikoff, and L. Comai. 2007. <span>“Discovery of Chemically Induced Mutations in Rice by TILLING.”</span> <em>BMC Plant Biology</em> 7: 19. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-7-19">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-7-19</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Upadhyaya2017" class="csl-entry">
Upadhyaya, P., K. Tyagi, S. Sarma, V. Tamboli, Y. Sreelakshmi, and R. Sharma. 2017. <span>“Natural Variation in Folate Levels Among Tomato Accessions.”</span> <em>Food Chemistry</em> 217: 610–19. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.09.031">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.09.031</a>.
</div>
</div>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled" title="Publication &amp; Reviewer Details">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Publication &amp; Reviewer Details
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><strong>Publication Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Submitted:</strong> <em>30 January 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Accepted:</strong> <em>11 February 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Published (Online):</strong> <em>12 February 2026</em></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Reviewer Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 1:</strong><br>
<strong>Dr.&nbsp;Gayathri G</strong><br>
<em>Assistant Professor</em><br>
<em>Kerala Agricultural University</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 2:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer/Publisher’s Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of the publisher and/or the editor(s).<br>
The publisher and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>© Copyright (2025): Author(s). The licensee is the journal publisher. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>, which permits non-commercial use, sharing, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and no modifications or adaptations are made.</p>
</blockquote>



</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Review-Article</category>
  <category>Genetics</category>
  <category>PlantScience</category>
  <guid>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA2026016BCE/JOSTA2026016BCE.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Date Palm Propagation Techniques: A Comprehensive Review</title>
  <dc:creator>Muhammad Ammar Amjad*</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Beenish Chaudhary</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haram Murtaza</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mohsin Raza</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Maham Sajid</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Aiman Shahid</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/JOSTA20251224E0.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 

<section class="josta-issue-banner" aria-label="Journal issue banner">
  <div class="jib-wrap">


    <div class="jib-cover">
      <img src="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/cover.webp" alt="Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture – cover image">
    </div>


    <div class="jib-meta">
      <p class="jib-journal-tag">Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture</p>

      <h2 class="jib-subtitle anchored">
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Volume 02</a>
        •
        <a href="https://www.jostapubs.com/volume1.html#vol1issue2" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-vi-link">Issue 01</a>
        • 2026
      </h2>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">ISSN (online)</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://portal.issn.org/resource/ISSN/3107-6882" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-issn-link">
            3107-6882
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>

      <p class="jib-line">
        <span class="jib-label">License</span>
        <span class="jib-value">
          <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" class="jib-license-link">
            CC BY-NC-ND 4.0
          </a>
        </span>
      </p>
    </div>

  </div>
</section>

<style>
  :root {
    --j-navy:#0053ed;
    --j-brown:#8b6a3a;
    --j-green:#0b5a56;
    --j-beige:#f8f3ea;
  }

  .josta-issue-banner {
    background: linear-gradient(115deg, var(--j-beige), #ffffff);
    border-bottom: 2px solid rgba(31, 52, 92, 0.12);
    padding: 1.8rem 1.4rem;
    margin-bottom: 1.6rem;
    font-family: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, "Segoe UI", sans-serif;
  }

  .jib-wrap {
    max-width: 1100px;
    margin: 0 auto;
    display: flex;
    gap: 1.6rem;
    align-items: center;
  }

  /* Cover image — NO ROUNDED CORNERS */
  .jib-cover img {
    display: block;
    max-width: 120px;
    height: auto;
    border-radius: 0;      /* removed curve */
    box-shadow: 0 6px 16px rgba(0,0,0,0.12);
  }

  .jib-journal-tag {
    margin: 0 0 0.4rem 0;
    font-size: 1.15rem;
    font-weight: 700;
    color: var(--j-green);
  }

  .jib-subtitle {
    margin: 0 0 0.7rem 0;
    font-size: 1rem;
    font-weight: 500;
    color: var(--j-navy);
    opacity: 0.85;
  }

  /* Volume/Issue links */
  .jib-vi-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-vi-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  .jib-line {
    margin: 0.15rem 0;
    font-size: 0.95rem;
    display: flex;
    gap: 0.4rem;
    align-items: baseline;
    color: #333;
  }

  .jib-label {
    font-weight: 600;
    color: var(--j-navy);
  }

  /* ISSN link */
  .jib-issn-link {
    color: var(--j-navy);
    text-decoration: none;
  }
  .jib-issn-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  /* License link */
  .jib-license-link {
    color: var(--j-green);
    text-decoration: none;
    font-weight: 600;
  }
  .jib-license-link:hover { text-decoration: underline; }

  @media (max-width: 640px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: row; align-items: flex-start; }
    .jib-cover img { max-width: 90px; }
    .jib-journal-tag { font-size: 1.05rem; }
    .jib-subtitle { font-size: 0.9rem; }
  }

  @media (max-width: 480px) {
    .jib-wrap { flex-direction: column; align-items: flex-start; }
  }
</style>




<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202512.24E0"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/DOI-10.65287%2Fjosta.202512.24E0-blue?logo=doi" class="img-fluid" alt="DOI"></a> <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/18322008"><img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/View%20on-Zenodo-0b5a56?logo=zenodo&amp;labelColor=d9d9d9.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Zenodo"></a><br>
<img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Open%20Access-Yes-0b5a56?style=flat-square&amp;logo=openaccess&amp;logoColor=white.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Open Access"> <img src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Status-Peer%20Reviewed-1f345c?style=flat-square.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Status"></p>
<!-- josta inline actions: pdf • copy citation • citation count -->
<div class="j-inline" style="margin-top:1rem;">
<p><a href="pdfs/JOSTA-202512-24E0.pdf" download="" class="j-btn" aria-label="download pdf">  <span>download pdf</span> </a></p>
<p>  <span>copy citation</span> <span id="j-tip" class="j-tip" aria-live="polite">citation copied!</span> </p>
<p><span class="j-chip" data-doi="10.65287/josta.202512.24E0" aria-label="citation count"> <span id="j-cite-count" class="j-chip-count">0</span> <span class="j-chip-label">citations</span> </span></p>
</div>
<!-- hidden citation text (kept as plain html) -->
<p id="j-citation-text" style="display:none;">
Muhammad, A. A., Chaudhary, B., Murtaza, H., Raza, M., Sajid, M., &amp; Shahid, A. (2026). Date Palm (Phoenix dactylifera) Propagation Techniques: A Comprehensive Review. Journal of Sustainable Technology in Agriculture, 2(1). https://doi.org/10.65287/josta.202512.24E0
</p>
<style>
/* row */
.j-inline{display:flex;align-items:center;gap:1rem;flex-wrap:nowrap}

/* button */
.j-btn{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.5rem;padding:.45rem 1rem;
  border-radius:999px;background:#8b6a3a;color:#fff;text-decoration:none;
  font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;
  box-shadow:0 2px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.1);transition:background .25s ease}
.j-btn:hover{background:#6d532d}

/* copy link */
.j-copy{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.4rem;color:#1f345c;
  text-decoration:none;font:500 0.9rem/1 "Segoe UI",Roboto,system-ui,sans-serif;position:relative}
.j-copy:hover{color:#0b5a56;text-decoration:underline}

/* tooltip */
.j-tip{visibility:hidden;opacity:0;transition:opacity .25s;
  background:#0b5a56;color:#fff;position:absolute;top:-34px;left:50%;
  transform:translateX(-50%);padding:.3rem .6rem;border-radius:6px;font-size:.75rem;white-space:nowrap}
.j-copy:focus .j-tip,.j-copy:active .j-tip{visibility:visible;opacity:1}

/* citation chip */
.j-chip{display:inline-flex;align-items:center;gap:.35rem;padding:.25rem .7rem;
  border:1px solid #ddd;border-radius:999px;background:#f8f7f5;
  font:400 .85rem/1 system-ui,"Segoe UI",Roboto,sans-serif;box-shadow:0 1px 4px rgba(0,0,0,.08)}
.j-chip-count{font-weight:700;font-size:1rem;color:#1f345c}
.j-chip-label{text-transform:uppercase;letter-spacing:.2px;color:#8b6a3a}

/* small screens: allow wrap with gentle spacing */
@media (max-width:540px){.j-inline{flex-wrap:wrap;row-gap:.6rem}}
</style>
<script>
function jCopyCitation(){
  const t=document.getElementById("j-citation-text").innerText.trim();
  navigator.clipboard.writeText(t);
  const tip=document.getElementById("j-tip");
  tip.style.visibility="visible"; tip.style.opacity="1";
  setTimeout(()=>{tip.style.visibility="hidden"; tip.style.opacity="0";},1600);
}

document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', async ()=>{
  const chip=document.querySelector('.j-chip'); if(!chip) return;
  const doi=chip.dataset.doi, el=document.getElementById('j-cite-count');
  const api=`https://api.crossref.org/works/${encodeURIComponent(doi)}?select=is-referenced-by-count`;
  try{
    const r=await fetch(api,{cache:'no-store'}); const j=await r.json();
    const n = j?.message?.['is-referenced-by-count'];
    el.textContent = (Number.isFinite(n) ? n : 0);
  }catch{ el.textContent='0'; }
});
</script>
<hr>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>The date palm (Phoenix dactylifera L.) is not merely a tree; it serves as a vital element of life in arid and semi-arid regions, representing significant economic and cultural value <span class="citation" data-cites="Chao2007">(Chao and Krueger 2007)</span>. This fruit-bearing tree plays a crucial role in sustaining food supplies and enhancing economies in several developing countries, emphasizing the importance of effective cultivation and multiplication methods for these trees <span class="citation" data-cites="Soomro2023">(Soomro, Marri, and Shaikh 2023)</span>. However, increasing the number of date palms is more complex than it appears, primarily due to their distinctive biology <span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2015">(Jaradat 2015)</span>. Being long-lived, single-stemmed plants that don’t reproduce naturally, the conventional methods we have used can frequently seem a bit limiting <span class="citation" data-cites="AlKhayri2018">(Al-Khayri et al. 2018)</span>. This inherently slow reproductive rate means that advancing date palm populations or enhancing their characteristics through standard breeding takes time, underscoring the necessity for diverse propagation strategies to navigate these natural limitations <span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span>.</p>
<p>Proficiently propagating date palms is not only about increasing the number of trees planted. It is also crucial for establishing new farms, replacing aging and less efficient trees, and promoting superior varieties that yield larger harvests, have better-tasting fruit, or are resistant to common pests and diseases <span class="citation" data-cites="Hadrami2009">(Hadrami and Hadrami 2009)</span>. The capacity to cultivate more of the top date palm varieties is vital for the sustained health and profitability of the entire date industry <span class="citation" data-cites="Supriatna2024">(Supriatna et al. 2024)</span>. This article intends to thoroughly examine the different methods employed in date palm propagation. This narrative review highlights the details of each technique, evaluate their advantages and disadvantages, compare their effectiveness based on existing research, consider the reasons behind choosing one method over another, delve into the latest innovations in the field, and specifically contrast traditional practices with modern techniques.</p>
</section>
<section id="literature-search-and-selection" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="literature-search-and-selection"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Literature search and selection</h2>
<p>The material was searched from Google Scholar database and the material was searched using different keywords (date palm, propagation, tissue culture, <em>in vitro</em> propagation, date palm biotechnology, CRISPR-CAS9) for integrative reviews published between 1990 to 2025. The total number of papers 36, including research articles, review articles, book chapters, reports and statistical reports.</p>
</section>
<section id="traditional-propagation-by-seed" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="traditional-propagation-by-seed"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Traditional propagation by seed</h2>
<p>Cultivating date palms from seeds, or sexual propagation, is an effective method to produce new plants using seeds from ripe dates. It typically begins with selecting the best seeds from fully matured dates <span class="citation" data-cites="Wakil2015">(Wakil et al. 2015)</span>. After sourcing the seeds, it’s crucial to clean them thoroughly to eliminate any sticky fruit pulp that may be present <span class="citation" data-cites="Alotaibi2023">(Alotaibi et al. 2023)</span>. To enhance the chances of germination, these cleansed seeds are generally soaked in fresh water for approximately 48 to 72 hours, with daily water changes to prevent mold or bacterial growth <span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2013">(Jaradat 2013)</span>. Occasionally, a technique called stratification is utilized, where the soaked seeds are placed in a moist medium, such as sand or vermiculite, and then refrigerated for one to three months. This simulates winter conditions and can significantly improve germination rates <span class="citation" data-cites="Robinson2009">(Robinson 2009)</span>. These preliminary steps are essential for breaking the seed’s dormancy and preparing them for growth, demonstrating a solid grasp of seed biology <span class="citation" data-cites="Nonogaki2017">(Nonogaki 2017)</span>. Once prepared, the seeds can be sown in a potting mixture that provides good drainage, ideally one designed specifically for palm trees, typically made from a blend of peat, perlite, and sand <span class="citation" data-cites="Maid2019">(Maid, Kitingan, and Kodoh 2019)</span>. Maintaining the right moisture level not too wet, and not too dry along with a warm temperature between 80 to 100°F (27°C to 38°C) and some indirect light is crucial for successful germination <span class="citation" data-cites="Bareke2018">(Bareke 2018)</span>. However, one should not anticipate rapid results; date palm seeds can take their time, often requiring several weeks to a few months to germinate, influenced by factors such as temperature and seed quality <span class="citation" data-cites="Mubaiwa2025">(Mubaiwa, Linnemann, and Maqsood 2025)</span>. The particular environmental requirements for these seeds to sprout emphasize the necessity of a controlled environment, especially in their initial stages, reflecting the date palm’s tropical or subtropical nature and its preference for warm, humid conditions during germination <span class="citation" data-cites="Klupczynska2021">(Klupczyńska and Pawłowski 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>One of the major advantages of growing plants from seeds is its straightforward nature, making it easy to start. It is also the fastest method to begin the propagation process <span class="citation" data-cites="Sallon2008">(Sallon et al. 2008)</span>. Perhaps most crucially, seed propagation brings genetic variety into the creation of new plants. This genetic diversity is a significant benefit for breeding initiatives aiming to cultivate improved varieties of date palms, potentially offering greater resistance to diseases, better tolerance for challenging environmental factors such as saline or arid soils, or simply enhancing the quality of the fruit <span class="citation" data-cites="Forneck2005">(Forneck 2005)</span>. Although it may not be the preferred approach for producing exact replicas for commercial agriculture, seed propagation plays an essential role in the long-term genetic enhancement and adaptation of date palms to evolving conditions <span class="citation" data-cites="Salgotra2023">(Salgotra and Chauhan 2023)</span>.</p>
<p>Despite its ease, seed propagation has some notable disadvantages that make it less suitable for commercial date farming, where the primary objective is to maintain consistent traits of a selected variety. Date palms are dioecious, meaning they consist of separate male and female trees. Therefore, when seeds are planted, roughly half will turn out to be male, which do not yield fruit. Additionally, it is impossible to distinguish between males and females until they bloom, which typically occurs around seven years later. This inherent unpredictability results in wasted resources in commercial orchards as growers may invest in trees that will never produce fruit. Furthermore, since date palms are heterozygous, offspring grown from seeds will not be exact replicas of the parent trees. Seedlings exhibit significant genetic variation, which can lead to inconsistent fruit quality, differences in ripening times, and unpredictable yields compared to the parent palm. In fact, it is relatively uncommon for more than 10 percent of seed-grown palms to yield fruit suitable for commercial sale. To add to the challenges, date palms grown from seeds require a lengthy maturation period, often taking 8 to 10 years or even more before they begin to produce fruit, significantly diminishing the return on investment for growers. The inconsistency in fruit quality and the timing of harvest further complicates marketing the dates as a uniform product, creating a substantial obstacle in commercial environments. The numerous drawbacks of seed propagation in commercial date production explain why vegetative propagation methods are preferred when the goal is to preserve the purity of a cultivar and guarantee dependable fruit quality and yield <span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012 McDonald2012">(Jain 2012; McDonald and Copeland 2012)</span>.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="traditional-propagation-by-offshoots" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="traditional-propagation-by-offshoots"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Traditional propagation by offshoots</h2>
<p>Cultivating date palms through offshoots, also referred to as asexual or vegetative propagation, is a time-honored technique that utilizes the young plants, known as offshoots or suckers, which grow from buds at the base of the mother plant during its early growth stages <span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span>. These offshoots are genetic clones of the mother plant, ensuring they share the same genetic traits and produce identical desirable qualities. The procedure for detaching these offshoots requires a gentle approach and generally involves several steps. Firstly, you carefully excavate the soil surrounding the base of the offshoot to uncover its connection to the mother plant. Next, most of the leaves are trimmed back, leaving only about a dozen of the newest leaves tied together for easier handling. The roots of the offshoot are then cut back to a length ranging from 2 to 10 cm. Finally, a robust, wide chisel is driven between the offshoot and the mother plant, often utilizing a sledgehammer, to sever their bond. This detachment process demands skill to minimize stress on both the mother plant and the offshoot, as any damage can significantly influence the survival and growth of the offshoot.</p>
<p>The size of the offshoot is a critical factor in its ability to successfully take root and flourish. An ideal base diameter is typically between 10 and 35 cm. Offshoots within this size range usually possess more roots already developed and higher levels of stored carbohydrates and substances that promote root growth, which are essential for their survival and growth after separation. After being detached, the offshoots are usually replanted directly into the field where the new date palm plantation will be set up. Occasionally, they may first spend a year or two in a nursery to establish a stronger foundation before being relocated to their final site. Planting them at the correct depth is also crucial, with the area from which the roots emerge ideally placed 25 to 50 cm below the soil level. Regular watering is essential to maintain adequate soil moisture, particularly during the initial establishment period when the offshoot is forming its new root system.</p>
<p>Propagation through offshoots provides several notable benefits. Primarily, the offspring are genetically identical to the parent plant, guaranteeing that the fruit they yield will maintain the same high standards and desirable properties. This form of “true-to-type” propagation is crucial for commercial cultivators aiming to uphold the specific traits of their selected varieties. Moreover, palms that are cultivated from offshoots tend to bear fruit sooner, generally within 3 to 5 years of planting, which is considerably earlier than the extended timeline required for palms grown from seeds. This early production can lead to significant financial advantages, delivering a quicker return on investment.</p>
<p>On the flip side, there are also certain drawbacks associated with using offshoots. A significant limitation is the number of offshoots that a single mother plant can produce throughout its lifetime, usually ranging from 20 to 30, with only 3 to 4 being viable for planting in a given year. Some high-quality varieties may yield very few or even no offshoots, which further limits the application of this method for expanding their numbers. Consequently, the rate of propagation tends to be relatively slow and often fails to meet the swiftly rising demand for date palm trees. Additionally, the process of separating and planting offshoots demands considerable labor and requires skilled personnel. There is also the potential risk of introducing diseases and pests from the parent palm to the offshoots, with the red palm weevil posing a particularly vital threat. To prevent infestation, cut surfaces must be dressed with insecticides immediately after maintenance operations. This creates a chemical barrier at the injury site, countering the risk posed by semiochemicals released from the wound that otherwise signal suitable egg-laying locations to female weevils <span class="citation" data-cites="Naveed2023">(Naveed et al. 2023)</span>. The survival rates of offshoots can vary significantly, ranging from as low as 10% to as high as 90%, influenced by factors such as the offshoot’s size, the specific variety, and the surrounding environmental conditions. For example, offshoots from the Medjool variety tend to be more difficult to establish than those from varieties like Deglet Nour or Zahidi. Finally, mother palms only generate offshoots during their juvenile stage, which typically lasts around 10 to 15 years, thus limiting the long-term availability of these young plants from older, potentially superior palm specimens.</p>
</section>
<section id="modern-propagation-by-tissue-culture" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modern-propagation-by-tissue-culture"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Modern propagation by tissue culture</h2>
<p>Tissue culture, also known as micropropagation, provides a contemporary approach to the propagation of date palms, enabling the rapid production of numerous plants. This method entails the extraction of small segments of plant tissue, including stem tips, nodes, meristems, embryos, or seeds, and cultivating them into complete plants in a sterile and nutrient-rich environment with precisely managed conditions. Tissue culture significantly surpasses traditional propagation methods by allowing for the production of a larger number of plants in a shorter time. There are two primary pathways for date palm tissue culture: somatic embryogenesis and organogenesis. Somatic embryogenesis refers to the creation of somatic embryos from somatic cells, often beginning with a callus stage, which consists of a cluster of undifferentiated plant cells. These somatic embryos progress through various developmental phases until they mature into fully formed plantlets. Due to its potential for quick and extensive plant production, somatic embryogenesis is commonly chosen in many commercial laboratories. Conversely, organogenesis is characterized by the direct or indirect emergence of new buds or shoots from the initial plant tissue, which later transform into plantlets. A popular technique within organogenesis is shoot tip culture. Direct organogenesis, which bypasses the callus phase, is often preferred as it minimizes the likelihood of genetic variations <span class="citation" data-cites="Rajmohan2011 Zaid2011">(Rajmohan 2011; Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span>.</p>
<p><strong>Steps involved in date palm tissue culture</strong></p>
<p>The general steps involved in date palm tissue culture typically include as indicated <span class="citation" data-cites="CoskunKaplan2025">(Coşkun and Kaplan 2025)</span>:</p>
<p><strong>Selecting and sterilizing the plant material (explant):</strong> The procedure starts with the selection of appropriate plant material, or explants, which may include shoot tips from seedlings or offsets, young flower clusters, or seeds’ embryos. These explants undergo careful sterilization to remove any surface impurities such as bacteria and fungi, as ensuring a sterile environment is essential for the success of tissue culture.</p>
<p><strong>Initiating the culture:</strong> The sterilized explant is placed onto a nutrient-dense culture medium, typically a gel made from agar, which is enriched with specific plant growth regulators like auxins (for example, naphthaleneacetic acid - NAA, 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid - 2,4-D) and cytokinin (such as 6-benzylaminopurine - BA, kinetin). These growth regulators are crucial for either promoting the formation of a callus or the direct development of shoots or embryos, depending on the selected technique. Activated charcoal is frequently incorporated into the medium to absorb any inhibitory substances released by the explant.</p>
<p><strong>Multiplication:</strong> After the initial cultures are established, they are moved to a multiplication medium, which consists of a different ratio of plant growth regulators designed to encourage the proliferation of additional shoots or embryos. To enhance multiplication rates, some laboratories utilize liquid media or temporary immersion systems (TIS), which periodically submerge the cultures in a nutrient solution, thereby improving nutrient absorption and gas exchange.</p>
<p><strong>Rooting:</strong> The multiplied shoots are then separated and placed onto a rooting medium, usually containing a higher concentration of auxins and minimal to no cytokinin. This hormonal configuration stimulates the formation of a robust root system, which is vital for the survival of the plantlets once they are transferred to soil.</p>
<p><strong>Acclimatization:</strong> The final stage consists of gradually acclimating the rooted plantlets to the external environment outside the laboratory. This process, also referred to as hardening, involves slowly decreasing humidity while increasing light intensity and temperature variations to prepare the plantlets for the conditions they will encounter in a greenhouse or nursery before being planted in the field.</p>
<p>Tissue culture provides numerous benefits compared to conventional propagation techniques. It facilitates quick and extensive production of uniform plants in a relatively short timeframe, effectively addressing the slow rate of offshoot production. Plants cultivated through tissue culture are generally free from diseases since they are raised in sterile environments, unlike offshoots, which may transmit illnesses. The plants generated are typically genetically identical (clones), ensuring consistency in growth, development, and fruit quality, which is highly advantageous for commercial production and marketing. Tissue culture can be conducted throughout the year, independent of seasonal changes, ensuring a steady supply of planting material. It is also crucial for preserving elite genotypes, particularly rare or endangered varieties, or those that do not produce offshoots. Moreover, tissue culture methods can be integrated with genetic enhancement techniques such as in vitro mutagenesis and genetic transformation to create improved date palm varieties. Finally, tissue culture plantlets are often more compact and easier to transport than bulky offshoots, thereby lowering transportation expenses and logistical issues <span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span>.</p>
<p>While tissue culture offers numerous advantages, it also presents various challenges. Establishing and maintaining a tissue culture laboratory can involve considerable initial expenses, necessitating investments in specialized infrastructure, equipment, chemicals, and trained personnel. The process requires a certain level of technical skill, as it relies on technicians and researchers who possess specific expertise in plant tissue culture. There exists the risk of soma clonal variation, which can occur when genetic changes arise during tissue culture, especially through somatic embryogenesis that includes a callus stage, resulting in the production of plants that may not be true to the original type. Transferring tissue culture plantlets to their natural habitats can be complicated, and improper acclimatization may result in elevated mortality rates. There is a persistent threat of bacterial and fungal contamination in tissue cultures, which may lead to the loss of entire batches. Physiological issues such as tissue browning and vitrification (hyperhydricity) can also arise in culture, adversely impacting the growth and development of the plantlets; furthermore, premature rooting of buds can disrupt the multiplication phase. Some research has indicated the likelihood of abnormal fruit formation in plants that have been propagated through somatic embryogenesis <span class="citation" data-cites="Herman2015 Oseni2018">(Herman 2015; Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="comparison-of-success-rates-of-different-propagation-techniques" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparison-of-success-rates-of-different-propagation-techniques"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Comparison of success rates of different propagation techniques</h2>
<p>Multiple factors influence the establishment success of offshoots, including their size and specific variety. For instance, Medjool offshoots tend to have lower survival rates compared to varieties like Deglet Nour or Zahidi <span class="citation" data-cites="Alasasfa2022">(Alasasfa 2022)</span>. Typically, offshoots with a base diameter ranging from 10 to 35 cm exhibit the highest survival rates, which can span from 83% to 95%. This highlights the importance of selecting appropriately sized offshoots to enhance their chances of successful establishment.</p>
<p>Conversely, tissue culture frequently achieves very high survival rates once the plants have been properly acclimatized, with certain studies reporting rates nearing 100%. However, the initial stages of tissue culture are at risk of contamination. The time required for the plants to mature and start producing fruit varies between the methods used. Offshoot-grown palms typically begin yielding harvestable fruits within 3 to 5 years. Tissue culture plants can also start fruiting relatively early, usually around 4 years after they are planted. In contrast, palms grown from seeds have a significantly longer juvenile phase, often taking 8 to 10 years or even longer to bear fruit. Research has also compared various tissue culture methods, revealing that temporary immersion systems (TIS) may enhance vigor and achieve a higher acclimatization rate (95%) compared to traditional gel-based systems (82%) <span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2024">(Zaid 2024)</span>.</p>
<div id="tbl-technique" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-tbl figure">
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-top quarto-float-caption quarto-float-tbl" id="tbl-technique-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Table&nbsp;1: Comparison of different propagation techniques
</figcaption>
<div aria-describedby="tbl-technique-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 30%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Feature</th>
<th>Seed Propagation</th>
<th>Offshoot Propagation</th>
<th>Tissue Culture</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Success Rate</td>
<td>Low and variable (low percentage female, poor quality)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
<td>Moderate to high (size and cultivar dependent)<span class="citation" data-cites="Drummond1919 Alasasfa2022">(Drummond 1919; Alasasfa 2022)</span></td>
<td>High (after acclimatization), initial contamination risk <span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2024">(Zaid 2024)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Time to Maturity</td>
<td>Very long (8–10+ years)<span class="citation" data-cites="McDonald2012">(McDonald and Copeland 2012)</span></td>
<td>Medium (3–5 years)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>Medium (around 4 years)<span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Genetic Uniformity</td>
<td>Low (off-type progeny)<span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span></td>
<td>High (true-to-type)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>High (generally true-to-type, risk of somaclonal variation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Herman2015 Oseni2018">(Herman 2015; Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Multiplication Rate</td>
<td>High (number of seeds)<span class="citation" data-cites="Jaradat2015">(Jaradat 2015)</span></td>
<td>Low (limited number of offshoots)<span class="citation" data-cites="Hadrami2009">(Hadrami and Hadrami 2009)</span></td>
<td>Very high (potential for mass propagation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Disease Transmission Risk</td>
<td>Low (if seeds are clean)<span class="citation" data-cites="Alotaibi2023">(Alotaibi et al. 2023)</span></td>
<td>Moderate to high (from mother plant)<span class="citation" data-cites="Wakil2015">(Wakil et al. 2015)</span></td>
<td>Low (disease-free plants)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Cost</td>
<td>Low initial cost<span class="citation" data-cites="Sallon2008">(Sallon et al. 2008)</span></td>
<td>Moderate (labor-intensive)<span class="citation" data-cites="Chao2007">(Chao and Krueger 2007)</span></td>
<td>High initial cost (lab setup, expertise)<span class="citation" data-cites="Oseni2018">(Oseni, Pande, and Nailwal 2018)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Scalability</td>
<td>Potentially high for breeding<span class="citation" data-cites="Forneck2005">(Forneck 2005)</span></td>
<td>Low for rapid expansion<span class="citation" data-cites="Jain2012">(Jain 2012)</span></td>
<td>High for commercial production<span class="citation" data-cites="Mehbub2022">(Mehbub et al. 2022)</span></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Complexity</td>
<td>Simple<span class="citation" data-cites="Bareke2018">(Bareke 2018)</span></td>
<td>Moderate (requires skill for separation)<span class="citation" data-cites="Bhansali2009">(Bhansali 2009)</span></td>
<td>High (requires technical expertise)<span class="citation" data-cites="Zaid2011">(Zaid, El-Korchi, and Visser 2011)</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="choosing-appropriate-propagation-technique" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="choosing-appropriate-propagation-technique"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Choosing Appropriate propagation technique</h2>
<p>Selecting the most appropriate technique for propagating date palms largely depends on several factors, with cost frequently being a significant aspect. Propagating through seeds typically acquires the lowest initial expenses but requires a lengthy period before bearing fruit and presents uncertainties regarding fruit quality. Offshoot propagation involves moderate costs, largely due to the labor needed for the separation and planting process. Although tissue culture demands a considerable upfront investment for laboratory setup and staff training, it can become more economically viable over time for large-scale production of high-value varieties, particularly when considering the potential for increased yields and consistent quality. The volume of propagation required is also a crucial factor in determining which method to select. Seed propagation is not ideal for commercially cultivating specific varieties due to the variability in genetics. Offshoot propagation is constrained by the number of offshoots produced by a parent palm. Tissue culture thus emerges as the optimal solution for extensive multiplication to satisfy significant demands for planting material <span class="citation" data-cites="Mehbub2022">(Mehbub et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>For commercial endeavors, preserving the desired traits of a particular variety is essential, making offshoot and tissue culture the favored options over seed propagation. The resources and infrastructure available also influence the practicality of a method. For instance, tissue culture requires specialized lab facilities and a skilled team. The purpose for which the propagated plants will be used is an additional vital consideration. While seed propagation is unsuitable for commercial orchards, it still serves as an important method in breeding programs that aim to create new varieties with enhanced characteristics. Lastly, although the suitability of a region for date palm cultivation is primarily determined by climate and soil conditions, these elements indirectly influence the choice of propagation by affecting the overall success and productivity of the resulting plantation.</p>
</section>
<section id="recent-advancements-and-novel-techniques-in-date-palm-propagation-research" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-advancements-and-novel-techniques-in-date-palm-propagation-research"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Recent advancements and novel techniques in date palm propagation research</h2>
<p>Recent advancements in date palm propagation have shifted from general protocol optimization to targeted solutions for critical production bottlenecks, specifically addressing scalability, genetic fidelity, and biotic stress resistance. Advances in tissue culture techniques include the creation and application of bioreactor-based systems and temporary immersion systems (TIS), which have demonstrated significant potential in boosting the multiplication rate of plants and aiding their adaptation to external growth conditions <span class="citation" data-cites="Anuradha2025">(Anuradha et al. 2025)</span>. Researchers have also been looking into alternative plant material sources for tissue culture, such as young female flower clusters, which may be more accessible than offshoots, especially for uncommon varieties, and could help expedite the overall propagation timeline.</p>
<p>The use of molecular markers (including SSRs, SNPs, DArT) and genetic engineering approaches like CRISPR-Cas9 is increasingly prominent in date palm propagation studies. These methodologies allow for precise identification of various cultivars, ensuring that tissue-cultured plants maintain genetic fidelity, and enable the introduction of advantageous traits such as pest and disease resistance, environmental stress tolerance, and enhanced fruit quality. In vitro mutagenesis, frequently utilizing gamma radiation, is being explored as a strategy to generate genetic variation and develop mutant types with desirable characteristics, including resistance to Bayoud disease, a significant fungal threat to date palms <span class="citation" data-cites="Pandey2024">(Pandey et al. 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>One particularly intriguing research avenue involves resurrecting ancient date palm varieties from seeds discovered at archaeological sites, some of which date back 2000 years. These endeavors underscore the impressive durability of date palm seeds and present a distinctive chance to recover potentially valuable traits that may have vanished over time. Moreover, there is ongoing research aimed at creating cost-effective tissue culture methods to make micropropagation more feasible for a broader spectrum of growers, especially in areas where date palm farming plays a crucial economic role <span class="citation" data-cites="GrosBalthazard2021">(Gros-Balthazard et al. 2021)</span>.</p>
<p>Recent advancements in date palm propagation have shifted from general protocol optimization to targeted solutions for critical production bottlenecks, specifically addressing scalability, genetic fidelity, and biotic stress resistance. To overcome the limitations of low multiplication rates and high acclimatization losses in conventional tissue culture, bioreactor-based Temporary Immersion Systems (TIS) have been introduced, which significantly enhanced nutrient uptake and have been shown to boost acclimatization success rates, compared to traditional gel-based systems. Simultaneously, the risk of somaclonal variation a major threat to commercial uniformity is being addressed through the integration of molecular markers (SSRs, SNPs, DArT), which allow for the precise validation of genetic fidelity at the <em>in vitro</em> stage. Furthermore, to bypass the date palm’s long juvenile breeding phase and combat specific threats like Bayoud disease, researchers are utilizing <em>in vitro</em> mutagenesis and CRISPR-Cas9 gene editing to introduce targeted resistance traits and improve fruit quality. Finally, novel efforts to recover lost genetic diversity involve the resurrection of ancient germplasm from 2,000-year-old seeds, providing a unique reservoir of traits for future breeding programs <span class="citation" data-cites="Pandey2024 Zaid2024">(Pandey et al. 2024; Zaid 2024)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-and-future-perspectives" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-and-future-perspectives"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> Conclusion and future perspectives</h2>
<p>This review has examined the various techniques for propagating date palms, ranging from conventional methods like seed and offshoot propagation to contemporary strategies such as tissue culture. Each technique has its unique advantages and disadvantages, making the selection of a method contingent on particular objectives, operational scale, available resources, and expected results. In commercial production aimed at preserving variety purity and ensuring consistent fruit quality, vegetative propagation through offshoots and increasingly, tissue culture, are favored methods. Although offshoot propagation has historically been the preferred approach, its limitations regarding the speed of plant multiplication and the risk of disease transmission are being mitigated by progress in tissue culture technology.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, future research and development in date palm propagation should target several critical areas. It is essential to further improve tissue culture techniques, particularly for varieties that have proven difficult to grow in vitro. Creating cost-effective and accessible tissue culture solutions will be vital for broader adoption, especially in developing regions where date palm farming is crucial. Ongoing research into in vitro mutagenesis and genetic engineering shows great potential for producing enhanced date palm varieties that exhibit better resistance to environmental stresses and pests, along with superior fruit quality. Investigations aimed at enhancing the acclimatization of tissue culture plantlets will be important for boosting survival rates across various environmental settings. Long-term studies assessing the performance and stability of date palms grown from tissue culture are necessary to thoroughly evaluate their viability throughout their productive lifespan. Lastly, looking into traditional knowledge and practices in regions like Pakistan and exploring how they can be combined with modern techniques could foster more sustainable and culturally relevant methods of date palm farming. Ultimately, choosing the most appropriate propagation technique is crucial for ensuring the sustainable expansion and productivity of the global date palm industry. However, tissue culture is a suitable propagation method in Large-scale commercial production and rapid expansion of elite varieties.</p>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">
<h2 class="unnumbered anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<!-- References will be rendered here -->
<div id="ref-Alasasfa2022" class="csl-entry">
Alasasfa, M. 2022. <span>“Effect of Cultivar and Offshoots Weight on Survival Rate and Some Vegetative Parameters of Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera) in Jordan Valley.”</span> <em>International Journal of Mechanical Engineering Education, Kalahari Journal</em> 7: 110–14.
</div>
<div id="ref-AlKhayri2018" class="csl-entry">
Al-Khayri, J. M., P. M. Naik, S. M. Jain, and D. V. Johnson. 2018. <span>“Advances in Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.) Breeding.”</span> In <em>Advances in Plant Breeding Strategies: Fruits</em>, 3:727–71. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91944-7_18">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91944-7_18</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Alotaibi2023" class="csl-entry">
Alotaibi, K. D., H. A. Alharbi, M. W. Yaish, I. Ahmed, S. A. Alharbi, F. Alotaibi, and Y. Kuzyakov. 2023. <span>“Date Palm Cultivation: A Review of Soil and Environmental Conditions and Future Challenges.”</span> <em>Land Degradation &amp; Development</em> 34: 2431–44. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.4619">https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.4619</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Anuradha2025" class="csl-entry">
Anuradha, M., S. Balasubramanya, G. Subbalakshmi, and P. Shilpa. 2025. <span>“Commercialization of in Vitro Secondary Metabolite Production: Challenges and Opportunities.”</span> In <em>In Vitro Production of Plant Secondary Metabolites: Theory and Practice</em>, 321–46. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-97-8808-8_25">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-981-97-8808-8_25</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bareke2018" class="csl-entry">
Bareke, T. 2018. <span>“Biology of Seed Development and Germination Physiology.”</span> <em>Advances in Plants &amp; Agriculture Research</em> 8: 336–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.15406/apar.2018.08.00335">https://doi.org/10.15406/apar.2018.08.00335</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bhansali2009" class="csl-entry">
Bhansali, R. R. 2009. <span>“Date Palm Cultivation in the Changing Scenario of Indian Arid Zones: Challenges and Prospects.”</span> In <em>Desert Plants: Biology and Biotechnology</em>, 423–59. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-02550-1_20">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-02550-1_20</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Chao2007" class="csl-entry">
Chao, C. T., and R. R. Krueger. 2007. <span>“The Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.): Overview of Biology, Uses, and Cultivation.”</span> <em>HortScience</em> 42: 1077–82. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTSCI.42.5.1077">https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTSCI.42.5.1077</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-CoskunKaplan2025" class="csl-entry">
Coşkun, Ö. F., and M. Kaplan. 2025. <span>“Edible Succulent Plants: Agricultural Value, Nutritional Characteristics and Micropropagation Approaches.”</span> In <em>Innovative Applications and Research Methods in Agriculture, Forestry and Aquaculture</em>, edited by İ. Daşdemir and H. Yazıcı, 289–312. Platanus Publishing. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18049952">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18049952</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Drummond1919" class="csl-entry">
Drummond, B. 1919. <em>Propagation and Culture of the Date Palm</em>. Bulletin 1016. U.S. Government Printing Office.
</div>
<div id="ref-Forneck2005" class="csl-entry">
Forneck, A. 2005. <span>“Plant Breeding: Clonality—a Concept for Stability and Variability During Vegetative Propagation.”</span> In <em>Progress in Botany: Genetics Physiology Systematics Ecology</em>, 164–83. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-27043-4_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-27043-4_8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-GrosBalthazard2021" class="csl-entry">
Gros-Balthazard, M., J. M. Flowers, K. M. Hazzouri, S. Ferrand, F. Aberlenc, S. Sallon, and M. D. Purugganan. 2021. <span>“The Genomes of Ancient Date Palms Germinated from 2,000 y Old Seeds.”</span> <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> 118: e2025337118. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2025337118">https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2025337118</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hadrami2009" class="csl-entry">
Hadrami, I. E., and A. E. Hadrami. 2009. <span>“Breeding Date Palm.”</span> In <em>Breeding Plantation Tree Crops: Tropical Species</em>, 191–216. New York: Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-71201-7_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-0-387-71201-7_6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Herman2015" class="csl-entry">
Herman, E. B. 2015. <span>“Plant Tissue Culture Contamination: Challenges and Opportunities.”</span> In <em>VI International Symposium on Production and Establishment of Micropropagated Plants</em>, 1155:231–38. Acta Horticulturae. Leuven, Belgium: International Society for Horticultural Science. <a href="https://doi.org/10.17660/ActaHortic.2017.1155.33">https://doi.org/10.17660/ActaHortic.2017.1155.33</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jain2012" class="csl-entry">
Jain, S. M. 2012. <span>“Date Palm Biotechnology: Current Status and Prospective—an Overview.”</span> <em>Emirates Journal of Food and Agriculture</em> 24: 386–99.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jaradat2013" class="csl-entry">
Jaradat, A. A. 2013. <span>“Date Palm: Production.”</span> In <em>Dates: Postharvest Science, Processing Technology and Health Benefits</em>, 29–55. Chichester, UK: Wiley-Blackwell. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118292419.ch2">https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118292419.ch2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Jaradat2015" class="csl-entry">
———. 2015. <span>“Biodiversity, Genetic Diversity, and Genetic Resources of Date Palm.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Genetic Resources and Utilization: Africa and the Americas</em>, 1:19–71. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-9694-1_2">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-9694-1_2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Klupczynska2021" class="csl-entry">
Klupczyńska, E. A., and T. A. Pawłowski. 2021. <span>“Regulation of Seed Dormancy and Germination Mechanisms in a Changing Environment.”</span> <em>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</em> 22: 1357. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Maid2019" class="csl-entry">
Maid, M., C. Kitingan, and J. Kodoh. 2019. <span>“Managing Planting Materials and Planting Stock Production of Tropical Tree Species.”</span> In <em>Prospects and Utilization of Tropical Plantation Trees</em>, 29–73. London, UK: IntechOpen. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22031357</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-McDonald2012" class="csl-entry">
McDonald, M. F., and L. O. Copeland. 2012. <em>Seed Production: Principles and Practices</em>. Springer Science &amp; Business Media.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mehbub2022" class="csl-entry">
Mehbub, H., A. Akter, M. A. Akter, M. S. H. Mandal, M. A. Hoque, M. Tuleja, and H. Mehraj. 2022. <span>“Tissue Culture in Ornamentals: Cultivation Factors, Propagation Techniques, and Its Application.”</span> <em>Plants</em> 11: 3208. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11233208">https://doi.org/10.3390/plants11233208</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mubaiwa2025" class="csl-entry">
Mubaiwa, J., A. R. Linnemann, and S. Maqsood. 2025. <span>“New Insights into the Influence of the Characteristic <span>‘Stone’</span> Feature of the Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera l.) Seeds on Its Sustainable Processing Approaches—a Review.”</span> <em>Food and Bioprocess Technology</em>, 1–33. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-024-03474-1">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11947-024-03474-1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Naveed2023" class="csl-entry">
Naveed, H., V. Andoh, W. Islam, L. Chen, and K. Chen. 2023. <span>“<a href="">Sustainable Pest Management in Date Palm Ecosystems: Unveiling the Ecological Dynamics of <span>Red Palm Weevil</span> (<span>Coleoptera</span>: <span>Curculionidae</span>) Infestations</a>.”</span> <em>Insects</em> 14: 859.
</div>
<div id="ref-Nonogaki2017" class="csl-entry">
Nonogaki, H. 2017. <span>“Seed Biology Updates–Highlights and New Discoveries in Seed Dormancy and Germination Research.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Plant Science</em> 8: 524. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.00524">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.00524</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Oseni2018" class="csl-entry">
Oseni, O. M., V. Pande, and T. K. Nailwal. 2018. <span>“A Review on Plant Tissue Culture, a Technique for Propagation and Conservation of Endangered Plant Species.”</span> <em>International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences</em> 7: 3778–86. <a href="https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2018.707.438">https://doi.org/10.20546/ijcmas.2018.707.438</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Pandey2024" class="csl-entry">
Pandey, N., P. Tripathi, N. Pandey, H. Nakum, and Y. S. Vala. 2024. <span>“Advancements in Date Palm Genomics and Biotechnology Genomic Resources to the Precision Agriculture: A Comprehensive Review.”</span> <em>Preprints</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202406.1327.v2">https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202406.1327.v2</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Rajmohan2011" class="csl-entry">
Rajmohan, K. 2011. <span>“Date Palm Tissue Culture: A Pathway to Rural Development.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Biotechnology</em>, 29–45. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_3">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Robinson2009" class="csl-entry">
Robinson, M. L. 2009. <span>“Cultivated Palm Seed Germination.”</span> SP-02-09. University of Nevada Cooperative Extension. <a href="https://naes.agnt.unr.edu/PMS/Pubs/2002-3243.pdf">https://naes.agnt.unr.edu/PMS/Pubs/2002-3243.pdf</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Salgotra2023" class="csl-entry">
Salgotra, R. K., and B. S. Chauhan. 2023. <span>“Genetic Diversity, Conservation, and Utilization of Plant Genetic Resources.”</span> <em>Genes</em> 14: 174. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14010174">https://doi.org/10.3390/genes14010174</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Sallon2008" class="csl-entry">
Sallon, S., E. Solowey, Y. Cohen, R. Korchinsky, M. Egli, I. Woodhatch, O. Simchoni, and M. Kislev. 2008. <span>“Germination, Genetics, and Growth of an Ancient Date Seed.”</span> <em>Science</em> 320: 1464. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1153600">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1153600</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Soomro2023" class="csl-entry">
Soomro, A. H., A. Marri, and N. Shaikh. 2023. <span>“Date Palm (Phoenix Dactylifera): A Review of Economic Potential, Industrial Valorization, Nutritional and Health Significance.”</span> In <em>Neglected Plant Foods of South Asia: Exploring and Valorizing Nature to Feed Hunger</em>, 319–50. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37077-9_13">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37077-9_13</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Supriatna2024" class="csl-entry">
Supriatna, J., A. B. Saluy, D. Kurniawan, and D. Djumarno. 2024. <span>“Promoting Sustainable Performance of Smallholder Oil Palm Farmers: An Analysis of Key Determinants and Strategic Priorities.”</span> <em>International Journal of Productivity and Performance Management</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/IJPPM-12-2023-0647">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJPPM-12-2023-0647</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Wakil2015" class="csl-entry">
Wakil, W., J. R. Faleiro, T. A. Miller, G. O. Bedford, and R. R. Krueger. 2015. <span>“Date Palm Production and Pest Management Challenges.”</span> In <em>Sustainable Pest Management in Date Palm: Current Status and Emerging Challenges</em>, 1–11. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24397-9_1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-24397-9_1</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zaid2024" class="csl-entry">
Zaid, A. 2024. <em>Date Palm Cultivation</em>. Food; Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4060/cc9251en">https://doi.org/10.4060/cc9251en</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zaid2011" class="csl-entry">
Zaid, A., B. El-Korchi, and H. J. Visser. 2011. <span>“Commercial Date Palm Tissue Culture Procedures and Facility Establishment.”</span> In <em>Date Palm Biotechnology</em>, 137–80. Springer. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-1318-5_8</a>.
</div>
</div>
<div style="page-break-after: always;"></div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled" title="Publication &amp; Reviewer Details">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Publication &amp; Reviewer Details
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><strong>Publication Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Submitted:</strong> <em>13 December 2025</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Accepted:</strong> <em>20 January 2026</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Published (Online):</strong> <em>22 January 2026</em></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Reviewer Information</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 1:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reviewer 2:</strong><br>
<em>Anonymous</em></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-simple callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Disclaimer/Publisher’s Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of the publisher and/or the editor(s).<br>
The publisher and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p>
</div>
</div>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>© Copyright (2025): Author(s). The licensee is the journal publisher. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</a>, which permits non-commercial use, sharing, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited and no modifications or adaptations are made.</p>
</blockquote>



</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Review-Article</category>
  <category>Horticulture</category>
  <category>Plantation-crops</category>
  <guid>https://www.jostapubs.com/volume2/issue1/JOSTA20251224E0/JOSTA20251224E0.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
